<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Several sermons, or, Declarations of Mr. Stephen Crisp, late of Colchester in Essex, deceased exactly taken in characters, or shorthand, as they were delivered by him at the publick meeting-houses of the people called Quakers, in Grace-Church-Street and Devonshire-House, London / and now faithfully transcribed and published ; together with his prayer at the end of every sermon.</title>
            <author>Crisp, Stephen, 1628-1692.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 247 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 100 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35001</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6941</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32375</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12652856</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12652856</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65307</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35001)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65307)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1525:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Several sermons, or, Declarations of Mr. Stephen Crisp, late of Colchester in Essex, deceased exactly taken in characters, or shorthand, as they were delivered by him at the publick meeting-houses of the people called Quakers, in Grace-Church-Street and Devonshire-House, London / and now faithfully transcribed and published ; together with his prayer at the end of every sermon.</title>
                  <author>Crisp, Stephen, 1628-1692.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 175, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Nath. Crouch ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:65307:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SEVERAL SERMONS OR Declarations OF Mr. Stephen Criſp, Late of <hi>Colcheſter</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> Deceaſed.</p>
            <p>Exactly taken in Characters or Short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, as they were Delivered by him at the Publick Meeting-Houſes of the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> In <hi>Grace-Church-ſtreet,</hi> and <hi>Devonſhire-Houſe, London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now Faithfully Tranſcribed and Publiſhed. Together with his Prayer at the end of every Sermon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Nath. Crouch</hi> at the <hi>Bell</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey</hi> near <hi>Cheapſide.</hi> 1693</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:65307:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:65307:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THough the Writer of theſe Sermons doth out of modeſty decline to Print his name, yet he is very willing to give all reaſonable ſatisfaction to any ſober Inquirer; that he has not in the leaſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered or impoſed upon the Authors ſenſe, either in the Taking or Tranſcribing of them; And he does further aſſure the Reader, that he neither is, nor ever was one of thoſe People called <hi>Quakers;</hi> but always of another Perſuaſion; Yet being willing according to the Apoſtles Rule, to <hi>Try all things;</hi> he has ſometimes been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at their Meetings, and having the Art of Short Writing, he has Taken many of their Sermons and Prayers from the Mouths of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of their Preachers, and among others, thoſe of Mr. <hi>Stephen Criſp</hi> deceaſed, which upon Review appeared to him, as well as to three or four other eminent Perſons of another
<pb facs="tcp:65307:3"/> Way, to contain ſo many Goſpel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ruths, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with ſuch Plainneſs, Zeal and Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, and generally agreeable to the known Doctrines of Chriſtianity, that it is hoped the Publiſhing of them may be uſeful to the World: And that the Deſign and Intent of them may be the more readily comprehended, there is a Title given to every Sermon, agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Subject Matter Chiefly Treated of. If any deſire to be further ſatisfied by ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the Writer, they may be gratified therein by applying themſelves to the Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Nath. Crouch.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:65307:3"/>
            <head>Sermon I. The Great Mediator of the Everlaſting Covenant. <hi>Preached at</hi> Grace-Church-Street, April 25. 1688.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HOW ſhould we all admire the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Holy Ghoſt? You may know from your own Experience, that all the Operations of the Holy Spirit from the beginning, have been in Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the Cleanſing, and Purifying, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring you for the Kingdom of God: This Experience is given to a little Remnant, of the the manner of his working, that the End, Aim and D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſign of all the Operations of his Pow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r, is for our good, and in order to our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Happineſs.</p>
            <p>Now this is a great ingagement upon the minds of the People of God, diligently to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:65307:4"/> wait upon him, that they may be opened more and more into the Myſtery of Life and Salvation, that hath been hid from Ages, and Generations, and is now revealed by his Spirit.</p>
            <p>And they that are thus exerciſed, with the meaſure of Grace given unto them, they do grow and increaſe, in Holineſs and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, by the working thereof; and they increaſe in Knowledge in the great things of his Law, and the Myſteries of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Grace, that the Eye which God hath opened, may diſcern that the working of his Power in all Ages, has been for the Extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pating, Rooting out, and Deſtroying of that Root of Iniquity, that hath brought forth ſuch a Crop of Sin, and Wickedneſs, which was not of his Planting, nor of his Creating.</p>
            <p>For from the beginning of the Creation of God, unto this day, God hath had a ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Love, and Favour to the Sons, and Daughters of Men, as being (as I may ſay) the Maſter-piece, or greateſt piece of the Creation, moſt nearly related to himſelf; Created in his own Image, in Righteouſneſs and Holineſs; and in that they now are not ſo, but Marred, and Spoiled from bearing the Heavenly Image, is not the Lords doing,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:65307:4"/> but hath been wrought by the Enemy both to God and Man; And the Lord continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Love unto the Work of his hands, hath from Age to Age, Revealed, and made Known hss Power, for the reſtoring and bringing back again Loſt Man, Fallen Man, Sinful Man, to be Reconciled unto him; that he might, as was intended, Enjoy and Poſſeſs the Love and Favour of his Maker; but there was no poſſibility found for his Reconciliation with the Holy God, but by making him Holy: For as the mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him Unholy, ſeparated him from his Maker; So the making of him Holy again, would Unite him again unto his Maker; So that there muſt be a way, and means for the Reducing of him to his Primitive State, before he could enjoy and obtain his Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Enjoyments, that is, the Love, and Favour of God: And there hath been a General Univerſal ſenſe upon the Sons and Daughters of Men, of this Alienation, and Eſtrangedneſs from God; and they have put themſelves upon divers ways, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods to obtain Reconciliation, and to try if they could reſtore themſelves, and they have found out ways, and tryed and prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Inventions, and Imaginations of their own Minds, in their fallen Wiſdom, what
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:65307:5"/> they might do to pleaſe God, and be Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to him.</p>
            <p>We are Sinners, and we will Sacrifice, we will bring a Sacrifice for our Sins; and when they have brought a Sacrifice, it hath not been accepted, becauſe there hath not been a Mediator known, that might Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate for them with the Lord; ſo that all the Sacrifices they have Offered have never been accepted with him, in order to an Attone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Reconciliation: Now only thoſe that have Relation to the Mediator by Faith in him, doth he Intercede for, that he might preſent them again to God; and this hath been the difference between Sacrificer, and Sacrificer, from the days of <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel,</hi> unto this day. Some have had Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Mediator in all their Services, and Sacrifices, and ſome have had Relation only to the thing offered, and the ſervice performed; but they have not in all Ages ſped alike: They whoſe Services and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip was performed to God, with a Relation to the Mediator, they have found Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; and they whoſe Worſhip and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, was performed only, with a Relation to the thing offered or done; that was but their own Act, that was but their Will-Worſhip, and that was always turned back again upon
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:65307:5"/> them: For there is no Name given under Heaven, by which any can be ſaved, but only the Name of Jeſus Chriſt, that is, the Mediator of the New Covenant, for the Old one was broken; And when <hi>Aaron</hi> was ſet up to be an High Prieſt to God, he was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to offer Sacrifices for the Sins of the People; and they that committed a Sin, was appointed by the Law to bring an Hee-Goat of the Flock, unto the Door of the Tabernacle, and to deliver it to the Prieſt, and he was to make an Offering for the Sin committed, after ſuch and ſuch a manner, and it was to be an Attonement with God for them: So here was ſeemingly a Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation by a Sacrifice: And ſome ſaw no farther than the bringing of a Goat, and a Ram, and the performance of the Prieſts Office, and they counted all was well: And others ſaw farther, long before the Apoſtle ſpake or wrote it: It was not the Blood of Bulls, or Goats; nor the Blood of a Ram that could purge away Sin from their Conſciences. And after the Apoſtle had opened the Myſtery of Divinity, who had a Divine, and Spiritual Skill, in unfold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Reſtoration of Mankind; he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared plainly that when the Offering was made by <hi>Aaron</hi> for Sinners, even then there
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:65307:6"/> remained ſtill a Conſcience of Sin; for it was not poſſible that the Blood of Bulls and Goats ſhould take away Sin; ſo that their outward performances, and their outward ſervices, they did but point out the Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor; they had a pointing finger as it were to the Real, True, and Everlaſting Mediator Chriſt Jeſus, who is made a Mediator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt God and Man; that by, and through him, man might be again Reconciled to God.</p>
            <p>So that now in theſe Goſpel days, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in God is opening the Myſteries of Life, and Salvation, to the intent and purpoſe, that the Sons and Daughters of Men might be reſtored again, unto their Primitive En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of the Favour of God: Now in theſe days, it is the Duty of all Chriſtians, and of all that are ſeeking the welfare of their Immortal Souls, that they have their Eyes and their Hearts unto Jeſus, as unto one that is able to Reconcile them unto God; To him it is committed; to him Wiſdom, and Power is committed, and to him Authority is committed, that he ſhould be an Everlaſting High Prieſt, and that all the Services, and all the Worſhip, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious performances that People offer up to God, ſhould be in his Name; that ſo by
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:65307:6"/> him they might be Recommended to God: For none will ever find Acceptance with the Father, unleſs in all their performances they have an Eye unto him.</p>
            <p>So that it comes plainly to paſs, according to that ſhort, and confident Aſſertion of the Author to the <hi>Hebrews, That without Faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God:</hi> But it is poſſible to Offer Sacrifices without Faith; and poſſible for People to perform Religious Services without Faith, as woful Experience have taught us in our days; That many have been exerciſed in a kind of a Religious Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and Worſhip, that never in their Lives had Faith enough to believe the things that they pray for: And they are without Faith. For when People Pray to God to ſend his Holy Spirit into their Hearts, that they may keep his Commandments to their Lives End; they have not Faith to believe it: And when they Pray, <hi>Thy will be done, on Earth; as it is in Heaven:</hi> This is a Religious perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, but I queſtion whether it be done in Faith, [if not] it is but an Increaſing in Sin, an Addition to Sin: Where is the Man that is exerciſed in praying to God, that believeth that ever ſuch a thing is like to come to paſs? Go where you will in this or the other Nation, and Inquire of People
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:65307:7"/> about their Faith; they believe there is no poſſibility of Extirpating, and Rooting out of Sin, while they live upon the Earth; therefore all their Prayers for it are vain, and their Faith a vain Faith; and it is high time, in ſuch a day as this when men are Faithleſs, and Unbelieving, to preach up the object of Faith, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: People are of divers Faiths; and of divers Beliefs; but we have found by experience, that they do them no good; they do not bring a thing to paſs, that of neceſſity muſt be brought to paſs ere they can be Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to God; their Faith doth not cleanſe the Heart, nor extend ſo far as to believe that ere they ſhall be cleanſed: In all the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Religion that they perform, they come not to this Faith that they ſhall be made clean: All that is done is but in ſin, and uncleanneſs, they cannot bring a clean Sacrifice out of an unclean Veſſel; And our Lord Jeſus Chriſt ſaith concerning this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; <hi>An Evil Tree cannot bring forth Good Fruit.</hi> But there muſt be good Fruit brought forth, how muſt we do it? Make the Tree good, and the Fruit will be good. When that Mens vain janglings about Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and Religious fancies muſt come to an end: Then all that Religion will appear
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:65307:7"/> to be in vain, and will not anſwer the end for which it is performed, till men believe that it will make the Tree good and cleanſe the Heart, and Tranſform men by Renewing the Spirit of their Minds. So that Religion it muſt begin within: And it is not our changing our forms of Worſhip, from one form to another, and taking up this, and the other Opinion, that doth change our hearts: Sad Experience doth teach us, that men may carry over their old Luſts into a new Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; we can carry over our old Inclinations into our new Opinions: For though the form of Worſhip be changed, the Heart remaining unchanged, and the Luſts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortified, their Religion is in vain, let them be of what perſuaſion they will.</p>
            <p>Now the remedy of this great Calamity, that hath overſpread all ſorts of People; for there is no ſort of People, but there are thoſe among them that are under this great Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, of holding the profeſſion of Godlineſs with an Ungodly mind, and the profeſſion of Truth, with a falſe and treacherous Spirit.</p>
            <p>Now for the remedying of this there is but one way, that all Mens Eyes be brought off from having their Eye unto their Performances, and to the Doctrines and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:65307:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:65307:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:65307:9"/> Tenents that they hold, and do, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith, <hi>Fix their Eye upon Chriſt, and look upon Jeſus:</hi> that is the firſt thing that muſt begin our Religion; for Chriſt muſt be the <hi>Alpha</hi> of our Religion, as well as the <hi>Omega</hi> of it. If I begin not there, let me begin where I will, I begin wrong: Let me begin at the moſt ſerious and ſound Doctrines and at the moſt Apoſtolical Religion: If Chriſt and his Apoſtles were here upon the Earth, if I walked among them, if I believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all they ſaid, and did; I ſhould begin wrong, if I did not fix mine Eye upon Jeſus Chriſt, that is the taker away of ſin, and is the ſanctifier of the Soul by his Spirit. There muſt be the firſt beginning; and there muſt be the concluſion: he is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, and, the finiſher of all true Faith: There are Authors of other Faiths, Men have different Faiths, and their Creeds, and Articles: And they have expoſed and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed them too; but this is the worſt of it; none of them are right, let them be expoſed, and impoſed with never ſo much force and violence, none of theſe will cleanſe the heart; but that Faith which is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered over by Chriſt J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſus, that hath the quality of cleanſing and purifying; that is the Faith when all is done that will do the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:65307:9"/> work, that is it that will ſave and ſanctifie, and do the buſineſs that all the World is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout; every one would have a Reconciler with God, and Sin rooted out, and be as God would have them be; this is the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick profeſſion of Chriſtendom, at leaſt they would find out ſomething by which it might be done.</p>
            <p>Others are willing enough to continue in Sin and Drunkeneſs Whoredom, Lying and Hypocriſie; theſe are a ſort of Fools, that make a mock of Sin, and that ſwim in the ſtream of pleaſure, and what care they ſo long as they make a profeſſion of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? But I am ſpeaking of a People that are ſtrugling under their corruptions, that would mortifie Sin, and ſerve God in Holineſs and Righteouſneſs; and do Gods will on Earth as it is done in Heaven; and do it not in form, but would have power to do it: And they try ſeveral ways to have it done, &amp; it is not done; &amp; many have been at this work till Gray Hairs are upon their Heads, and it is not done; Now God hath given Chriſt to make Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation; now how can we, that have the Love of God extended to us, But extend our Good-will to our Friends, and ſignifie to them, that all the travel and pains they are at, and all the Prayers they make, that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:65307:10"/> all will do nothing till they have their Faith fixt upon Jeſus, that is able to ſave and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver them, <hi>and ſave to the uttermoſt all that come to God by him.</hi> But here ſome will object and ſay, It is true what you ſay; But is it needful to preach ſuch Doctrines to us, for we all believe in Chriſt, that is the only Mediator and Saviour; We know that Chriſt Jeſus is the only Mediator, and that unleſs he Commend us to God, we cannot be Accepted of him? This is our General Doctrine, therefore what need it be urged and preſſed upon us, that are come into the the Faith already?</p>
            <p>Let me ſearch into the matter, it is of greater concernment than to ſearch into a Bargain of Worldly things; men would fain have others open and diſcover to them where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they may be Cheated, to prevent their being Impoſed on in a wordly bargain; I hope then they will hearken to know how, and wherein they may be deceived by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and deceived by others in matters of Eternal concernment: There are no Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, but they reject any Mediator but Jeſus Chriſt, and believe that no Mediator can Reconcile them to God, but Chriſt alone, and they ſay he is the Object of their Faith: I would ask them this Queſtion;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:65307:10"/> Whether they believe in Chriſt at a diſtance, or as preſent, really preſent with them? If their Faith be Hiſtorical and at a Diſtance, that they believe in Chriſt, as one born of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and was Crucified and Dead before they were born, and Aroſe again, and Aſcended into Heaven, and is ſet at the right hand of God; if the reaſon of my belief be, I have heard of this Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſt; Or whether the reaſon be, becauſe by his Spirit, he hath viſited me in this Age: The one is, I believe becauſe good men have told me ſo; but the other is, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve becauſe by this Spirit he hath promiſed to ſend to lead me into all truth, he hath viſited me; Now whether I am aware of ſuch a Spiritual viſitation, by this quickning Spirit, which is the Lord from Heaven, and not only the Lord in Heaven: Whether I am aware of ſuch a quickning Power and Vertue, which I have received upon my Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that he is not only at the right hand of God on high in Heaven; but that now he is come to knock at the door of my heart, and hath raiſed in me a Life, as oppoſite to ſin as his was.</p>
            <p>Now if I be aware of a ſecret touch of his quickning vertue upon my Soul, whereby he hath begotten me into a Life oppoſite to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:65307:11"/> ſin, ſo that if ſin remains, it remains as a Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, and Oppreſſion upon me, ſo that I am a ſufferer, forasmuch as I am quickned, and made ſenſible of a better life, of a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Life; I would fain be at it, and live in it; but Iniquity, Luſt, and Corruption, lies in the way: He that hath quickned me ſo far, as to bring me to a ſenſe of the Burthen of ſin, my Faith tells me, he will take the Burthen off, elſe my faith will do me no good, if that Corruption ſtill prevail upon me; if my Faith tells me this, it will tell the wickedeſt Man in the World as much: But if my faith tells me I am a ſinner and my ſin conſiſts of this, and the other evil thing I do, and am inclined to do; it tells me again that he that hath quickned me, and brought me to a ſenſe of ſin, he can take the burthen off from me.</p>
            <p>Here now is a true Faith, that begins in Conviction, and ends in true Converſion, this is the word of Faith, which was deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Saints, and which we are to Preach: They ſaid of O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d that the word of Faith, which they had to Preach, was that which was nigh in their mouth, that they might hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it and do it; I have ſomething nigh, that reproves me for ſin, if I be Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to it, then Faith giveth me victory over
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:65307:11"/> that which is ſinful, for which the word re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proveth me; and as I ſee Faith gives me victory over any Corruption, which I have been ſtrugling under. Here I am incourag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to fix my Faith upon him that hath thus quickned me; So that this is the difference between Faith in Chriſt at a diſtance, and Faith that quickneth me by Gods Spirit, that Spirit which hath been ſo much ſlighted in our days, by the higheſt Notioniſts in our Age; they have ſuppoſed it to be a meer fiction, ſome have mocked and derided, and others have been diſcouraged to ſpeak of the Spirit of Chriſt, and his operations upon the Soul; ſome have declared it, both in the Preſs and Pulpit, that they have had no experience of the touches of Gods Spirit upon their Souls.</p>
            <p>But our experience hath brought us to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther degree of knowledge: We know, and you may know if you pleaſe, and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you ſleep that there is a way opened: God hath made a way for his Spirit to reach the Spirits of men, to ſignifie immediately to their Spirits without means; herein thou doſt wrong, and herein thou mayeſt have life, and ſeek after it; Now the Spiritth at thus worketh, is the Spirit of Chriſt, the Spirit that proceeds from the Father and the Son, that Voice in Man that tells them they
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:65307:12"/> might believe and be ſaved: When he comes, ſaith Chriſt, <hi>He will lead you into all truth:</hi> How ſhall the World know this is he? <hi>He ſhall convince them of ſin.</hi> If there be any convincement that ariſeth in Man of this and the other ſin, it muſt be from the way the holy Spirit hath upon their Spirits; he hath a way to ſpeak to men; and every one that is a Lover of their own Souls, are bound to hearken unto that voice.</p>
            <p>In the latter days, ſaith the Lord, <hi>When I ſhall raiſe a Prophet in the midſt of you, whoſoever will not hear that Prophet ſhall be cut off:</hi> All Commentators agree on this Text, that that Prophet was no other than Chriſt Jeſus, it was not <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> nor <hi>Paul,</hi> nor <hi>Peter,</hi> but Chriſt that was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to be raiſed; there was ſuch an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Command went along with that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy, <hi>That all ſhould hear him,</hi> and it had a threatning at the end of it, <hi>That all that will not hear him ſhall be cut off:</hi> Are there not Whoremongers, and Drunkards, and Lyars, that will not hear this Prophet? They will not hear him, becauſe they love their Sins, what becomes of them? They are cut off from the enjoyment of the Love and Favour of God: And when they did draw nigh to God in Prayer, and other Religious
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:65307:12"/> exerciſes, it was with them, as it was with <hi>Cain,</hi> Sin lies at the Door. When they come into a ſtorm at Sea, or are Arreſted with ſickneſs; and Death looks them in the face, they would have Peace, but there is Diſtreſs, and Trouble in the Room of it; what is the matter, waſt thou not baptized into the Chriſtian Faith? Did not the Miniſter tell thee, <hi>That thou art a Child of God and an Inheriter of the Kingdom of Heaven?</hi> Alas! my Sin lies at my Door; Oh that I had time to live a better Life! What ails thy life Man? My Life hath been a Life of Deceit, Luſt, and Vanity; Corruption, and Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie. Did not thy Teacher teach thee, that a believer hath no guilt upon him; but that all his Sins are pardoned, from the day he became a believer? This Doctrine will not hold in a ſtorm, though it will do in fair Weather; when men are ſwimming in their pleaſures, it will ſerve them; but when they come to deal with their Maker, no Faith will ſerve them but that which purifies the heart, and that which makes a change from the Earthly Image to the Heavenly.</p>
            <p>It were better for you and I, and every one of us; to take theſe things into conſideration, while we have health and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:65307:13"/> ſtrength, and while ſome Sand, (as I may ſo ſpeak) is in our Glaſſes, to conſider, what is my Faith? What is the Object of it? Have I a dependency upon my Duties, and Alms, and good Deeds? They will fail me. But if my dependency is upon Chriſt, as a Saviour and a Sanctifyer; and my Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is carryed on gradually: He that hath begun a good work in me, will perfect it: And if the reaſon of my going to Meetings, and going into my Cloſet, and bowing my ſelf before the Lord, is to keep cloſe to him that carries on the Work of Sanctification; he will work all my work in me and for me; I cannot expect to live in this World, but I ſhall meet with Temptations; the Devil will Tempt me; but my Saviour will be nigh me, as nigh to me as the Devil can be; If I Keep cloſe to him he will keep cloſe to me: <hi>My Father,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>is greater than I, and none is able to pluck you out of your Fathers hands.</hi> I muſt expect to be tempted, <hi>For the Adverſary the Devil goes about like a Roaring Lyon, ſeeking whom he may devour.</hi> Alas! ſaith one, though I have made ſome progreſs in the work of Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, yet for all that, he may one day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray me; Am I grown ſtrong enough to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt his Temptations? And wiſe enough to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:65307:13"/> foreſee all his G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns and Traps, which he lays to inſnare me? But I know who can ſee them, and defeat them; I have my Faith fixed upon one that can bind the ſtrong Man, and caſt him out; The Life that I now live, is not in my own Parts, and by my own Underſtanding and Sence: <hi>But the Life that I now live, in the Fleſh, I live by the Faith of the Son of God:</hi> This is that Faith that gives me victory; the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle had a battle for it: <hi>I have fought the good fight; and henceforth is laid up for me a Crown of Righteouſneſs, and not for me on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but for all them that love the appearing of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> And that come to have familiarity with Chriſt, with his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and Truth in their Hearts, with his Grace, and Word; though theſe are ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Expreſſions, they all ſignifie one Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal ſeed of Life, by which men are United to God. It is a Leaven there, to Leaven them into the Divine Nature.</p>
            <p>Whenever ſuch a one his Tempted, he reſiſts not the Tempter in his own power; but he waits to feel the ariſings of that Life and Power, and Vertue, that was in Chriſt Jeſus, and is in him ſtill; he waits for that power that in the name of Chriſt he may ſay, <hi>Get thee behind me Satan:</hi> Being for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifyed
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:65307:14"/> by Chriſts Name, and armed with his power; What is it that a Chriſtian can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not do? What Valiant, Noble, and Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful things have they done, that have been ſhielded with this Faith? See the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Chapter of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews:</hi> All the Repetitions of that Chapter from one end to the other, in all of them the Apoſtle he aſcribes all the Valiantneſs, and Coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſneſs of thoſe noble Acts, to the power of Faith; they looked to Jeſus, before ever the <hi>Virgin Mary</hi> brought him forth of her body. The Prophets did earneſtly ſeek to know thoſe things, which the Spirit of Chriſt that was in them did ſignifie; That there was to be a Prophet, before ever the <hi>Virgin Mary</hi> was born: So that Chriſt was always the Object of a true Believers faith; tho' under the Law they had an high Prieſt, and he was placed at the Altar, and they had Offerings burnt upon it; Yet they had an Eye unto Chriſt; They had an under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valuing of all that their Sacrifices could do for them: <hi>If thou wouldſt have had burnt Offerings,</hi> ſaith <hi>David, I would have given them, I would not have with-held them from thine Altar; thou ſhouldeſt have had enough of them.</hi> He was bold to ſay, in reſpect of Acceptance and Reconciliation; <hi>Burnt Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:65307:14"/> and Sacrifices thou wouldſt not, a Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy haſt thou prepared me; for it is written in the Volume of the Book, I come to do thy Will O God:</hi> He had an Eye unto Jeſus that was to come, upon whom help was laid; there was a Redeemer, that ſhould come from <hi>Sion,</hi> and a Lawgiver from <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> they had an Eye beyond Sacrifices, unto Chriſt: In all Ages, the People of God, they have had the Anſwer of their Souls, which is Reconciliation, and the Favour of God; they that had this Anſwer never had it but by Chriſt: No Man can be accepted with God, can never have the deſire of his Soul Anſwered in Peace, and Reconciliation with God, till his Faith be placed on Chriſt Jeſus: Neither can any man have Faith in Chriſt at a diſtance, and thereby be Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled unto God, but muſt know his Spirit; I muſt have an experimental knowledge of his Power, and Wiſdom, and this I cannot have without his Spirit; Let me believe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo Orthodoxly, except I have the Spirit of Chriſt, it will do me no good, it will be of no Advantage to me.</p>
            <p>This is the Word, that was in my heart as a well wiſher to the Souls of all Men: As God hath done good to my Soul, So I cannot but wiſh well to the Souls of others:
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:65307:15"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:65307:15"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:65307:16"/> That as he hath found out a way for my Redemption, and Salvation, ſo likewiſe I wiſh the ſame for others that are bond-men and bond-women, and under the Power of their Corruption: Gods work hath been to deſtroy the Bondage and the Oppreſſion, and to deſtroy the Tyrant that Reigns over the Souls of his People, God having made them for his Glory; and the Devil hath Stolen them away, that they do not that which pleaſeth God: But God's good pleaſure is, that all may be Saved, and come to the Knowledge of the Truth: <hi>And God ſo loved the World, that he gave his only begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Son, that whoſoever believeth in him ſhould not Periſh but have Everlaſting Life:</hi> And he is called <hi>The Lamb of God, which takes away the Sins of the World.</hi> He can take away Sin, if my Sin do not obſtruct my Faith, and Confidence in him, he will take it away; and if he takes that away, then he makes the Tree good. Nothing hinders us from the injoyment of God, but Sin; and if Chriſt will take it away by the blood of his Croſs, no matter for all the Scorn, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, Hardſhip, Reproach and Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this World; no matter, for he hath not deceived us, but told us before hand; If we will be followers of him, and be led by
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:65307:16"/> him, we muſt expect theſe things, ſuffering Reproaches, Perſecutions, Diſdain, Envy, theſe things come not uncertainly upon us; the World loves its own, and cannot love them that are not of it; but they that are now of the World may be brought to the terms of God, and they may not be any longer of the World: Chriſt Prayeth not that his Diſciples may be taken out of the World, but kept from the evil; he prayed for them that did not believe: So that Chriſt is a Mediator for all men, and a Propitiation for all men, and he is working by his Spirit for the Redemption of all men, <hi>That to as many as believe in him, to them he gives Power to become the Sons of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſum of all is this, that we have an opportunity put into our hands, we cannot deny it, you muſt all upon ſearch confeſs, that the Grace of God doth often work in your hearts, againſt any Corruption, againſt any Evil: Let not this prize be put into our hands in vain, as into the hands of fools: If I knew that this, and that, was a ſin, I would leave it; let us be of that mind, and we ſhall ſoon know it: Then ſay, If I knew ſuch a thing to be a ſin, If I could get a thouſand pounds by it, I would not do it; why ſhould'ſt thou love ſin for profit or plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure?
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:65307:17"/> I am ſure it is an ill bargain when it is done: Whatſoever I am convinced of is a ſin, I will not it.</p>
            <p>Reſolve upon this, and there the Grace of God will be at work; we ſhall ſoon ſee that we muſt leave off ſinning there is ſuch a thing I muſt leave, God hath ſet up a Judgment in my mind againſt it, though it bring profit and pleaſure, away it muſt go; here is a ſtep, a following ſtep, to follow Chriſt, he that will deny himſelf will follow Chriſt: My Redeemer ſhews me this to be an evil; I will not do it, but follow him, and imitate him: Here the Soul is led ſtep by ſtep, even by Chriſt the Captain of our Salvation, till it is gradually cleanſed from ſin, and reconciled unto God; and this can be done by no other means, for Prayer and Alms will not do it: All that can be done by us will not dot it; none can do it but Chriſt alone, that God hath laid help upon, that you may all wait for the Divine Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Grace in your hearts; that is it which we Labour and Travel for, as know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that God hath wrought wonderfully by it for the Redemption of all thoſe that love him, more than they love their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, more than they love their ſins; it muſt be concluded that following of him, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:65307:17"/> leaving Father and Mother, Husband and Wife, Children, Brethren and Siſters, all theſe things as they ſtand in competition with him, and the Obedience of his Spirit; all theſe muſt be looked upon as nothing to him: Then above all things I muſt not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe him; <hi>He can ſpeak Peace, and none can take it away; and if he take it away none can give it:</hi> If we follow Chriſt, when this is done, then all is done according to the Will of God; then the bleſſing of God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcends upon the whole Creation; then every man will ſpeak truth to his Neighbour, and every man will govern his Family with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion; So God is Glorified. and his name comes to be Exalted, who is worthy to be Lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Adored and Exalted above all Bleſſings and Praiſes, to him be Glory, who is God over all, Bleſſed for Ever, and Ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>His Prayer after Sermon.</head>
               <p>MOST Glorious God of Life and Power, and of Everlaſting Kindneſs; a God of Long-ſuffering and Patience, elſe we had not been here at this day: Lord we are Monuments of thy Mercy; thou haſt ſpared us long and haſt called unto us in a day, when we turned away our Ear from thee; thou haſt
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:65307:18"/> ſtretched out thy hand all the day long; and thou haſt gathered a little Remnant of the loſt Sheep of the houſe of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to partake of thy Paſtures of Life; and now all our Souls have been greatly refreſhed, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, ſince we come to underſtand and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend with the reſt of thy Saints, the Height, and Length, and Breadth, and Depth of thy Love, which in the Son of thy Love thou haſt Revealed to us: And bleſſed Father of Life, our Souls do breath and cry unto thee, on the behalf of Strangers which are Aliens from the Common-wealth of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> that are yet brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing and inquiring after thee, <hi>And asking the way to</hi> Sion; O Lord remember them and hear their cry, and let their ſighing and complaining enter into thine Ears; that all they, in whom thou haſt begun to kindle up holy deſires after thee, may have them grow into a flame to burn up all their Enmity to thee, that ſo they may be purified by thy judgments, and receive of thy Heavenly Grace. This is the way which thou haſt uſed with thy Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; thou haſt commanded them to Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip thee in thy dwelling place; thou haſt taken them into thy houſe, and fed them with thy fineſt Wheat, refreſhed them with thy Loving-kindneſs; and filled them with thy Holy Spirit: Deareſt God of Love, this
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:65307:18"/> is the deſign and purpoſe of our Meeting toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; that we may enjoy thy Preſence, and feel the operation of thy Word, and have Communion with thee, and thy Son Jeſus Chriſt, through thy Holy Spirit; the way into Reſt and Life is with thee, thou canſt open, and none can ſhut: Lord open the hearts of this People, to receive of thy goodneſs, and receive of thy bleſſings, that ſo every one may be ſenſible that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u art at the leaſt knocking at the door of their hearts, that thou mighteſt have an entrance, and bow the hearts and wills of all, to receive what thou giveſt and haſt to offer; to receive the word of Life, by which thou art quickning them: And kindle holy deſires after thy ſelf, that every one may receive thy truth in the love of it: That ſo bleſſed God of Life, thy glorious work of Redemption may be carryed on, and we may all feel it carryed on upon our Souls: Hear thy poor People that are crying unto thee, the God of Gods in <hi>Zion,</hi> that are ſenſible of their weakneſs and feebleneſs, and how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able they are to overcome the Enemies of their Soul: Ariſe in thy power O Lord, and theſe Enemies ſhall be ſcattered; Let the Souls of thy People be raiſed from the Duſt, and delivered f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om their Sin, that they may rejoice and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aiſe thy name for their deliverance. Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:65307:19"/> God of Life; our Eyes are unto thee, to ſet forth thy glory, for th u haſt made bare thine Arm for the Salvation of the poor and needy Souls; and thou haſt been ſtretching forth the cords of thy Love to gather them that were ſcattered: and haſt been bringing home to thee thoſe that were hurried away in a dark and cloudy day: Thou haſt made us ſenſible of thy operations; and haſt conſtrained thy Servants to labour in the Word and Doctrine, for the gathering of ſuch home; that ſo they and we may enter into thy holy Covenant and may ſound forth thy praiſes to the Ages and Generations to come: That ſo Holy God of Life, and Love, thou that haſt ſaved us with a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velous ſalvation mayeſt receive for all thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and bleſſings to thy Children, Praiſes, Glory, Honour and Thanksgiving; for thou alone art worthy, who art God over all bleſſed for Ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:65307:19"/>
            <head>Sermon II. Heart Preparation for Receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Goſpel. <hi>Preached at</hi> Devonſhire-Houſe, Feb. 12. 1687.</head>
            <p>IT is in my heart at this time to deſire that every ones heart were prepared to be made partakers of the bleſſings of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel; For there is a certain Preparation that every one muſt witneſs in themſelves, ere they are capable of receiving Divine bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings; For in all Ages of the World the Bleſſings of the Lord have been manifold, and his Arm hath been always ſtretched out in all Ages to the Sons and Daughters of Men ſenſible of the Love he hath unto them, and where theſe tenders of the Love of God have met with prepared hearts, they have received it to their Eternal well-fare: But this hath been the Lamentation that hath
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:65307:20"/> been taken up upon the greateſt part of mankind, that they have not been prepared to receive the Love of God, their hearts and minds have been ſo filled with the Love of viſible things and carnal objects, that they have not been truly ſenſible of the Riches of Grace and Mercy, and Love of God unto them.</p>
            <p>Now it was ſaid of old by the Prophet, <hi>That the Preparation of the Heart is of the Lord;</hi> and there is ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thing that belongs to us on our part, that we might attain to this this Preparation, that we might be brought in to this Spiritual frame of mind, and that is, by returning to the Lord; that Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple might think upon his Name, and have regard to his Appearance: And although this is not the work of Nature, for by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the minds of People are abroad, and they are crying out as the Pſalmiſt ſpeaks, <hi>Who will ſhew us any good?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet to help that defect, the Lord hath been pleaſed to ſend forth his Grace and his Truth and to call unto the Sons and Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Men that they might ſeek after him, that they might <hi>Seek the Lord while he is to be found;</hi> and they that do hearken unto his voice they will readily confeſs that there is nothing doth ſo well ſatisfie an Immortal Soul
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:65307:20"/> as to be gathered into fellowſhip with its Maker: And that at one time or other it is the deſire of all Men and Women that they might attain Peace with the Lord; and they know there is no Peace to the wicked, and they know wickedneſs will remain until it is aboliſhed and deſtroyed; and they know that it is not in their Power to deſtroy it, and therefore of neceſſity there muſt be a waiting upon the Lord who is <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty,</hi> that he may reveal his Power in our weakneſs.</p>
            <p>And they that are thus Prepared in their <hi>Minds,</hi> for them to meet religiouſly toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with expectation unto God that he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his promiſe will appear and will reveal his Arm, and do in them and for them that which they cannot do for themſelves; this is a fit occaſion for People to meet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and thus many times to have their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation to God and ſay, Lord thou knoweſt my weakneſs, and thou knoweſt the enemies I have to deal withal; thou knoweſt I am not able to overcome them; Therefore we are now met together in the Preſence of the Lord to wait to receive at his hands that Power, that Life, that Vertue by which we may be made more than Conquerours. Such a Religious Meeting thus gathered together
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:65307:21"/> hath a Promiſe, <hi>I will be in the midſt of them,</hi> ſaith the Lord; and therefore having a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe we may reaſonably expect that we ſhall be made partakers of the living Virtue and Power, by which we may do that, which of our ſelves we cannot do.</p>
            <p>And I ſay, Friends, it is my Souls deſire that you were all thus qualified, that every one had an evidence in himſelf of this right Preparedneſs; for where the Eye is abroad upon any viſible thing, that it ſeeks ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in any thing below the Lord himſelf, it will wear away and wax old: All thoſe Objects that People fix their minds upon, they will wax old; but they whoſe deſires and the breathings of their Souls is that they may grow into Acquaintance with their <hi>Maker;</hi> this will never wax old. When Peoples minds are fixed as the People of the Lord of old were: When they made a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon between the ſtate of their minds and the minds of others, and ſignified it in theſe words; They are ſaying: They are crying, (that is, they that are of the World) <hi>Who will ſhew us any good?</hi> But we for our parts, our cry is, <hi>Lord lift up the light of thy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance upon us,</hi> and we will be more glad of that than th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y can be with all the increaſe of Corn and Wine, and Oil.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:65307:21"/>
            <p>Now they that feel in themſelves the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their Meeting together is to enjoy the Light of Gods Countenance and to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the bleſſings of God; they have their expectation to God, their minds are retired into God: But knowing right well that if the Tongues of Men and Angels are moved to declare the Heavenly and Divine Myſteries of the Kingdom of God, they cannot be Edified or benefited by them without the Divine help and aſſiſtance of God's Spirit, for there is a <hi>Seal</hi> upon them, and none can open that <hi>Seal,</hi> but <hi>The <hi>Lion</hi> of the Tribe of</hi> Judah, he only is found worthy to unſeal the Myſtery, and unſeal the Divine Bleſſings that are with the Lord, ſo that People muſt come to that retiredneſs of Spirit, to that reſignation of Soul that they are as a little Child waiting upon the Lord, crying out unto the Lord that he will <hi>Prepare</hi> them: <hi>That he will make rhem Hungry, and then Feed them, That he will raiſe a Thirſt in them, and then ſatisfie them with thoſe Divine Springs of Life, which through the Lord Ieſus Chriſt are opened to every one that Believeth.</hi> So far as your minds are ſtayed and ſetled waiting for the Lord, you will feel in your ſelves an openneſs and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:65307:22"/> readineſs, that if the Lord ſpeaks you are ready to hear him; ready to ſubmit to his word; ready to obey him; that ſo there may be ſuch an openneſs in the mind, not to the words of any man, but unto the word of God, to receive that; for where the words of men are received though never ſo excellent, they convert not the <hi>Soul, <hi>But the</hi> Word <hi>of the Lord is pure converting the Soul.</hi>
               </hi> And this word is that which is able to Quicken thoſe that are Dead in Sins and Treſpaſſes, and bring them to be made partakers of Life.</p>
            <p>For it is not an encreaſe of knowledge that will do the turn, but it is the increaſe of Life and Vertue, the increaſe of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, and a Submitting of our Wills unto him that made us: It is this that will do our turn, this will bring Peace to the Soul, and bring us into the Favour of God, through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. Now that all may feel that which Prepares the Heart, for this reſignation, and quietneſs, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, you muſt wait upon the Lord that ye may be made partakers of the bleſſings of of his Everlaſting Goſpel, and of his Divine Preſence: This is that which is moſt profit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, moſt advantagious: And then the Lord will <hi>Open to you the Windows of <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:65307:22"/> and Rain down of thoſe Bleſſings upon you,</hi> whereby you will be comforted and refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, far beyond all the Works that we can do, for it is an <hi>inward Work</hi> that muſt be done upon the Soul to Convert People that have been Alienated and eſtranged from God, and bring them to a Reconciled State through the Lord Jeſus-Chriſt, whereby they may partake of the Divine virtue, which Sanctifies and juſtifies the Soul in the ſight of God.</p>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>His Prayer after Sermon,</head>
               <p>Moſt Glorious and Powerful Father, thy <hi>Arm</hi> of <hi>Power</hi> is made bare in this our Day to bring Salvation to the Poor; O Lord thou haſt lifted up the Light of thy Countenance upon a People, that have waited for thy Glory and thy <hi>Salvation,</hi> a little Rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant whom the good of this World could not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie, but O Lord in an acceptable time thou haſt brought thy Salvation near, and the Light and Brightneſs of thy everlaſting Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel thou haſt commanded to ſhine into the Hearts, and Souls of the Mourners, and bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed down ones, who are ſeeking the living God, not among the outward Forms and ways of Men. But, O Bleſſed Father of Life, thou
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:65307:23"/> haſt now brought us to the Day of thy Power, and bowed our Wills, and made us a willing People therein to ſerve thee, and to do thy Will on Earth, as it is done in Heaven; and for that end O Lord thou haſt put it into the Heart of thy People to wait upon thee in whom all our freſh Springs are, that from thee we might receive the renewing of Power from Day to Day, and in all the hours of our Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and Tryals, our Eyes O Lord have been to thee, and to thy Power; and we acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to the Glory of thy Power and Goodneſs, that thou haſt been a God nigh at hand, when we have been ſeeking thee, and truſting in thee, ſo that we are a People ſenſible of thy Power and preſence with us; for that Eye which thou keepeſt open to thy Children, It brings thy Glory to our view, and ſhews it breaking forth over the Nations, and we have great joy and ſatisfaction in beholding the Progreſs of thy Mighty Power in our Day, how thou haſt broken down and Confounded, and art ſtill breaking down and Confounding all the Dark imaginations and Devices of the Sons and Daughters of Men, that have Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired to hinder the breaking forth of the Glory of thy Son Chriſt Jeſus. O Powerful God of Life ariſe more and more in the greatneſs of thy Power and Love, and make known thy
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:65307:23"/> Counſel, and thy will among the inhabitants of the Earth, and bow their minds O Lord and their Wills, that none may dare to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand thy appearance, leſt they be found fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers againſt God and deſtroyers of themſelves. O Powerfull Father, for this end make bare thine Arm unto the Rulers and Governours of theſe Nations, that they may know thy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, and bow to thy Heavenly Will, and may promote thy Law of Righteouſneſs in their own Hearts, and the Hearts of others, that by thy Power a Bleſſed Reformation may be wrought, and iniquity have a ſtop put to it, that it may not run down in a mighty Stream, as it hath done in time paſt, but that <hi>Truth</hi> and Righteouſneſs, and ſound Judgment may be known in the Earth; that they that hunger and thirſt after Righteouſneſs may have their Souls deſires ſatisfied, and ſo praiſe and thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>givings ſhall ariſe from their Souls to thee. O Powerful Father of Life preſerve and keep thy Children whom thou haſt gathered, and Purged, and Purified, and to whom thou haſt made known the way of Life; and made them a willing People in the Day of thy Power, to do thy will and to wait for the coming of that kingdom that thou haſt promiſed to eſtabliſh under Chriſt Jeſus, the King of Kings and Lord of Lords, that it may grow and increaſe
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:65307:24"/> and be ſpread abroad upon the Earth, and let every one deſire to be the Subject thereof; So Powerful Father of Life, the Arm of thy Power and Invincible ſtrength hath been Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed that nothing hath been able to reſiſt or ſtand againſt and prevail, by which thou art planting <hi>Sion</hi> and building <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhing it; By the ſame Power let thy Work be carryed on and many be brought in to be Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct to Chriſt for the good of their Immortal Souls; as thou haſt multiplied thy Bleſſings among us, ſo from Day to Day thou haſt made us ſenſible of thy Love unto us, owning us to be thy Children, and peculiar People, by thy preſence in the midſt of us when ever we meet in thy Name to wait upon thee that ſo living Father, all thine both here and every where may be encou a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to attend upon thee, and to be faithful to thy Power; that wait for the op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ning of thy Counſels and the enlightning their underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings that they may be able to comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ehend with all Saints, the height, and depth, and length, and breadth of thy Love in Chriſt Jeſus, that in the Senſe of the freeneſs and greatneſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, all thy Children here and every where, that in an everlaſting Covenant of Grace thou haſt gathered to thy ſelf, may have Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with thee and thy Son, and Spirit, and may return thee the honour Glory and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:65307:24"/> Praiſe of all thy Love and Mercy, and Grace, for thou alone art worthy, who art <hi>God over all,</hi> Bleſſed for ever and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="sermon">
            <head>Sermon III. The Firſt and Great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment opened, Or The Heart given up to God. <hi>Preached at</hi> Devonſhire-Houſe, May 27. 1688.</head>
            <p>VVHen God gave forth his Law on <hi>Mount Sinai,</hi> which <hi>Iſrael</hi> was to hear and to obey; The <hi>firſt</hi> great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment was, <hi>Thou ſhalt have no other Gods before me,</hi> here is the ſum and ſubſtance of all the true <hi>Religion</hi> that ever was on the Earth to this day, all the Commandments,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:65307:25"/> all the Precepts, Prophecies, and all the dealings of God with his People from that Day to this, have been all contained in this ſhort Precept, <hi>thou ſhalt have no other Gods but me,</hi> and as long as <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſtood in Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to this Command, their <hi>Bleſſings</hi> were multiplied upon them, their good things were increaſed from Day to Day; The Lord was with them as long as they were willing to be his P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ple; he appeared as their <hi>God,</hi> as their Defe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>der wrought their Deliveran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>ſought all their Battles</hi> for them, gave them Dominion and Strength, Courage and Wiſdom; Miniſtred out of his <hi>Treaſury</hi> all good things unto them; For the great Care of God Almighty was with all his People, he had regard to them, and viſited them at all times to keep them from Idolatry, <hi>I am,</hi> ſaith he, a <hi>Jealous God,</hi> take notice of me to be ſo; I am Jealous of my Name. If thou wilt be mine, <hi>thou ſhalt have no other Gods bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And all the Precepts about Offerings, and Sacrifices, and making attonement for Sinners, and the divers Services and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, the various Offices in the Temple and <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> they were all as outward means appointed of God to keep this outward Church in an inward Conformity to the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:65307:25"/> Command of God. This Command was written in <hi>Tables</hi> of <hi>Stone,</hi> and theſe Tables were laid up in the <hi>Ark of God,</hi> and all this pertained to the <hi>Firſt Covenant,</hi> and all this Typed and Figured out the Diſpenſation of the <hi>New</hi> and <hi>everlaſting Covenant</hi> that God would make with his People, not like unto the old; How not like it? Not like it in the outward Shadows, the Types and Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows of things, but he would bring forth the Suſbtance of all thoſe Shadows and <hi>Types;</hi> and would alter the Form and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward appearance of things, <hi>For as God is unchangeable</hi> ſo his <hi>Law</hi> is unchangea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith the firſt and great Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is, <hi>thou ſhalt have no other Gods but me.</hi> This was put into the Stone Tables. Chriſt Jeſus ſaith, the firſt and great Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is, <hi>thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy Soul, and with all thy Mind,</hi> Mat. 22, 27. This is put into the <hi>Tables of the Heart;</hi> So here is a difference between the firſt Commandment by <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the firſt Commandment by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> they both ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the firſt and great Command to be the ſubjecting of the Creature to him that made him as his God, that he may only ſerve him, that he may love him with his whole
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:65307:26"/> Heart; The <hi>Jew</hi> could prove this by his <hi>Stone Tables,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> proves this by the Fleſhly Tables of the Heart, for there he is bound to love the Lord with his whole Heart, and to ſerve him onely, <hi>him onely ſhalt thou ſerve.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now here is the Jews Law brought over to the Chriſtians in the greateſt Point of Religion that ever was Preached, that ſhuts out all Idolatry, all Superſtition, all variety of Religions, all is ſhut out by this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, and the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> that hath the Law written in his Heart according to the new Covenant, he can go as readily to it and read it, as ever the Jew could go to his <hi>Stone Tables,</hi> and read the Law there; you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny that, if there be a thing written and Graven in my Heart, I can go as readily to it as I can go to any Book or Table, though I have the keeping of it; But the Jews had not the keeping of it (generally,) it was laid up in the <hi>Ark of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now Friends that which lies upon my mind to ſpeak to you at this time, and that out of the great Love that I have to all your precious and Immortal Souls, as God hath had a <hi>Love to mine,</hi> is that you would all conſider and weigh in the fear of the Lord whoſe preſence is among us, which of you,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:65307:26"/> and how many of you are come to the Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of this Commandment I? do not doubt but the moſt of you can ſay, them <hi>all,</hi> but a happy People are you if you can <hi>do one,</hi> I dare pronounce that Soul a bleſſed Soul, that can perform this one Commandment, that can or dare ſtand before his <hi>Maker and ſay, O Lord I love thee with all my Heart, with all my Soul, and with all my Might,</hi> my love is withdrawn from all other things in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of thee, there is nothing in this whole World hath a place in my mind, but as it is in ſubjection to the love of thee.</p>
            <p>Here is the firſt and the great Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the unchangeable Law, the <hi>Law</hi> that was <hi>good</hi> in <hi>Moſes</hi> his Days, and good in <hi>Chriſts</hi> Days, and it holds good in our Days; and indeed it is ſuch a definitive Law that the Breakers of it can neither be good <hi>Jews,</hi> nor good <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> there is an abſolute ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity lies upon us of abſtracting and draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away our minds and Souls from all other Gods, from all Images and other dependen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and truſts that People are naturally liable to truſt to; And to have their whole Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ſet upon the Lord, but alas! with Grief of Heart I ſpeak it, there are but a very few that as yet have known the right giving forth of the <hi>Law,</hi> and there are a
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:65307:27"/> great many fewer that are ſubj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct to it. This Law was not given forth at firſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Thunder and Lightning and a terrible noiſe, and the Mountain ſmoaking, (he that hath an Ear to hear let him hear) in ſo much as <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf ſaid, he feared greatly and he Quaked exceedingly becauſe of the Thunder of the Almighty, and the Mountain that ſmoaked and burned with Fire ſo that <hi>Iſrael</hi> could not draw nigh.</p>
            <p>Now I ſay there are but a few that have come to the Knowledge of the giving forth of this Law, that have certainly known thoſe Thunders, and that Terrible Work that the Lord of the whole Earth makes, when he comes to ſet up his Law; for a great many that have come nigh to it, and might have heard and received the Words of the Law of God, they have gone backward, they have done like unto the <hi>Jews</hi> of old, though they had ſuffered much, and gone through much, and had ſeen the Wonders of the Lord, how be had led them and delivered them, yet when it came to this, that they muſt hear the Voice of God, they ſaid we cannot bear it; We cannot indure it: We have deviſed for our ſelves an eaſier way, for the Voice of Thunder and Dreadful noi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes put them into Terrour and <hi>Quaking,</hi> and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:65307:27"/> Trembling and great Dread came upon them but we have found an eaſier way ſay they, what is that? <hi>Go thou, ſaid they to</hi> Moſes, <hi>and hear thou what the Lord ſaith, and come thou and tell us.</hi> Thou ſhalt be a Mediator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us, let God ſpeak unto thee, and do thou ſpeak the ſame to us, and we will hear thee.</p>
            <p>This was the <hi>Jews</hi> that were not come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Law of God written in <hi>Tables of Stone,</hi> they would not come to receive it in their Hearts as the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> muſt; ſo <hi>Moſes</hi> he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the <hi>Law</hi> from the <hi>Mouth of God,</hi> and he was Faithful as a Servant in the Houſe of God, and he miniſtred forth the Law of God, his Precepts, Statutes and Judgments, and Teſtimonies, and he made them a Book of Laws for all of them to walk by, from the higheſt to the loweſt, how they ſhould act in Criminal matters, and do juſtice between Man and Man, and what they ſhould do in the Worſhip of God, and what they ſhould do towards the Prieſt whoſe Lips ſhould preſerve knowledge for them, and ſo he brought up a Form of Religion, but his Work was according to the Precepts of God, and he brought them into the Form of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Religion, and Government, and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Laws. And ſo <hi>Moyſes,</hi> and the Prieſts
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:65307:28"/> ruled over them, and the Prieſt he offered Sacrifice for them, and made attonement for them, and <hi>Moſes</hi> inquired of the Lord, and asked Counſel for them, and taught, and inſtructed them, and what c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me of all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s at laſt? When this was done, the Prieſt made attonement for Sin; but he could not pluck away the guilt of one Sin, there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained the Conſcience of Sin after he had made his Offering, and <hi>Moſes</hi> taught them the Counſels of God, and the Commands of God, but he could not bind their Hearts to the obedience of them, for he declared o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly againſt them, that they were a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious and ſtiffnecked People; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this they had a Law without them; indeed time would fail me to run through the manifold miſcarriages of the Church of the <hi>Jews</hi> in reſpect of their Idolatry, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of their Contempt and Rebellion, both to God and his ſervant <hi>Moſes,</hi> which was to teach and to guide them: I ſay the time would fail me to mention the manifold miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages that happened among this People, that had a Law and Religion without them, and a Teacher without them.</p>
            <p>Now in the fulneſs of time it pleaſed God in ſending his Son Chriſt Jeſus to raiſe up a Prophet like unto <hi>Moſes</hi> in reſpect of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:65307:28"/> Faithfulneſs, though higher in reſpect of Dignity; for <hi>Moſes</hi> was faithful in all his Houſe as a Servant; but this Man was faithful as a Son in his own Houſe, in the Houſe that he was Heir of, that Houſe wherein he was a King; both a Prieſt, a Prophet and a Ruler in: When the Lord ſignified by the Spirit of Prophecy the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Juſt one;</hi> he ſignified to the People that his Miniſtry, it ſhould not be as that of <hi>Aaron;</hi> the People ſhould not have their Religion without them, and their Laws and Precepts without them, and their Prieſts without them, and their Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Church without them; but that they ſhould have it all within them; <hi>I will write my Law in their Hearts, I will put it into their Inward Parts: then they ſhall be my People, and I will be their God; and they ſhall not forſake me.</hi> Your Fathers brake my old Covenant, but I will make a new Covenant in the Latter days, a New Covenant, not like that your Fathersbroke; they brake the Law without them, <hi>But I will Write my Law in their Hearts: This Prophet that is like to</hi> Moſes, <hi>he ſhall Teach my People, he ſhall be a Leader to them, and guide them in the way they are to go; and ſhall be a Captain for them to lead them to Salvation: And it ſhall come
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:65307:29"/> to paſs, in the Day that I do this, if there be any that will not hear him, he ſhall be cut off from among the People.</hi> That is the Judgment that comes upon the contemners of the Goſpel, upon them that will not hear Chriſt Jeſus; they ſhall be cut off from the People; from what People? From the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God; they ſhall have no part of the Priviledges that are enjoyed through Chriſt; they ſhall be cut off from the Benefits that others reap by their Faith in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>So that now we are to expect the opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and working of a Miniſtry that leads a People to an inward Religion, a Heart Religion, where the Heart is fixed intirely upon the True and Living God, as the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of their Dependance and Truſt, and they have no other; that ſame is a ſtrange Word to Fleſh and Blood; what no other Dependance but on the Inviſible God? Fleſh and Blood can never come to this: Fleſh and Blood and Senſuality can never come to this: This is a Religion that hath been hid from Ages and Generations, and will be hid to all Ages that ever ſhall be in the World where Senſuality prevails: What will you have me to have my whole De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance for the Comfort of my Life here, and of the Life that is to come, the other
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:65307:29"/> Life; to have my Dependance upon an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible God, that Inviſible Power that made me, and Created the World? How is it poſſible for me to ſequeſter my ſelf, and draw my ſelf off from all viſible Objects? I muſt truſt to this, and truſt to that; Fleſh and Blood can never attain to this with all the Wit and Reaſon it hath, it can never ſeparate it ſelf from Idols; they are little Children that keep themſelves frrom Idols: They are Children of another birth, born of another ſeed, that will keep themſelves from Idols.</p>
            <p>Friends, Idolatry is a great deal more common, I find, than moſt are aware of. Am I commanded to Love the Lord with all my Heart, and Soul, and Mind, and Might? What is left when the whole is taken away? If God hath my whole Heart, what have I to beſtow upon the World? What Love, what Affection, what Eager<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, what Fervency can I beſtow upon the World, or any Object in the World; when my whole Heart, and Soul, and Mind is gone before, gone towards the Lord?</p>
            <p>This is the Firſt and Great Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and the Second is like unto it; that is <hi>Thou ſhalt Love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf;</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:65307:30"/> Here it is that the Law and the Prophets Faith, Creeds, Prayer, Religion and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, all that ever was in the World, all Comprehended in this: <hi>Thou ſhalt Love the Lord thy God with all thy Heart, Soul and Strength; and thy Neighbour as thy ſelf:</hi> So what need is there for us to be diſputing about Religion, about this Tenet and the other Tenet, this Text and the other Text? For my part I ſhould only deſire for you to Underſtand this Text, and I ſhould not doubt your going to Heaven: Here is the Sum: Here is all at once: Here is the Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſence of all Religion, of all Types, Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, Figures, Ceremonies, and Prieſthood, and all that ever was or could be Named and Practiſed in the World, all brought to this, <hi>The Heart given up to God;</hi> our Love ſet upon him.</p>
            <p>What, is this ſufficient, will ſome ſay? This will make you a good Moral Man, but what is this to the Chriſtian Religion? You may be led into Error, and become an Heretick for all this.</p>
            <p>How can this be that I ſhould not be of a ſound Faith, but led into Error and Hereſie for all this? When People let in Error, and Hereſie, and Unſoundneſs of Faith, Where do they let it in? Do they not let in the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:65307:30"/> Principles of Errour and Hereſie into their Hearts? I believe this, and that, and the other Error, it comes into the Heart, and hath a ſeat in the Heart; but how can we do that? How can we let it into the Heart; <hi>When the Heart is given up to God?</hi> Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not he keep out Error and Hereſie, if I give up my Heart and Soul to him? Cannot I truſt him with all?</p>
            <p>This kind of talk of Error and Hereſie hath come among Men that have had the keeping of their own Souls; they have taken their own Souls into their own hands, and have ordered their Religion themſelves, or have gotten ſome body to order it for them, and a great many of them have met together to make Creeds, and Catechiſms, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, and Orthodox Doctrines, that might certainly be profeſſed and ſubſcribed. Afterwards ſome have come and found fault with them; then they muſt have a Council to try them, then theſe go off and are laid aſide, and others are given in the room of them; ſo that theſe Men have ſet up for themſelves: Theſe would not be under the Government and Preſcription of God, as Children under the Government of a Father, but they will ſet up Religions themſelves; and ſay to the reſt of the World, if you
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:65307:31"/> own any thing contrary to our Principles, you are an Heretick; and being an Heretick you are to be rooted out and cut off. Do not you read in the Scripture, that whoſoever hears not the Prophet that was to come into the World ſhall be cut off? What will you not hear Chriſt ſpeak in the Church? Will not you hear Chriſt ſpeak? The Church cannot ſpeak without a Head: If you will not hear the Church you ſhall be cut off. Then they have fallen to Hanging, and Burning, and Killing, and Deſtroying People, and Nations not a few: And this comes from their mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Faiths and Creeds, and ordering Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on themſelves; all their Barbarous and Inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Cruelties Martyring and Dungeoning of People comes from their making Faiths themſelves, and of all things nothing is more deſparately wicked, and they did not know it. <hi>The Heart is deceitful above all things and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſparately wicked, who can know it?</hi> Men know not how Proud and Arrogant they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are, and yet they would be ordering the Hearts and Minds and Conſciences of others, and out of this hath Sprung all Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition and Idolatry becauſe men would not give up their Hearts to God; <hi>Thou ſhalt have no other Gods but me.</hi> This Commandment is great in it ſelf, ſtrict in
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:65307:31"/> the terms, <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy Heart, and thy Neighbour as thy ſelf.</hi> Their Neighbour could not ſee with their Eyes; therefore there muſt be Hanging, and Burning, and Deſtroying one another.</p>
            <p>But bleſſed be who is now bringing forth true Chriſtianity upon its old Baſis and Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation whereon it was placed at firſt, for Chriſtianity hath been juſtled off from its firſt Foundation: for inſtead of Loving God with all their Hearts, and Loving their Neighbours as themſelves they Hated them: Now this is the Day, O Friends, the weight of it is great: This I ſay is the Day where<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n God is bringing Chriſtianity upon its old Foundation.</p>
            <p>I would not have you think that I am here judging our Fore-fathers that are fallen aſleep, that therefore they are gone to Hell, becauſe they ſaw not this Day, and Lived not to ſee the benefit of it that we enjoy; I am far from it: This was the thing that they believed and prayed to God for, they did not ſee this Day outwardly but they ſaw it by Faith. I my ſelf when I was a Child I remember the People of God when they got three or four together they would rejoice in the Hope of what they
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:65307:32"/> Foreſaw; they gave Thanks to God for the Bleſſed Days that he would bring forth, though they could not tell when; they did ſay and believe that God would ſcatter the Foggs and Miſts, and bring forth an Happy Day, wherein his People ſhould have the Gift of his Spirit; when they ſaw the Impoſitions and Perſecutions of theſe times, when they that did not Conform and Comply were caſt into Priſons, and thrown into Dungeons, and Goals: Well, it will not always be thus, ſay they, there is a Day a coming wherein the Lord will ſet his People free from all the Yoaks of Oppreſſion and from the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſour.</p>
            <p>Indeed my Soul did rejoyce when I was hearing the Prophetical ſayings of theſe good men, and I thought I might live to ſee that Day; Bleſſed be God that hath Preſerved my Life to this Day, and to this Hour to enjoy what they Prayed for: They Prayed to God to ſcatter the Miſts and Fogs that they might no longer Cloud and Darken Men's Minds and hinder them from enjoying God's Teaching; Bleſſed be God that we are now in the injoyment of the Prayers of the Faithful, that left the World, before we were in it. Now the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:65307:32"/> Day is come that they Prayed for and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired after.</p>
            <p>How ſtrangely doth the Man Talk, will ſome ſay, concerning the Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion? The Chriſtian Religion is all <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land over;</hi> go to any Meeting in <hi>London</hi> except one, and they will tell you they are Chriſtians; I would to God they were, that is the worſt I wiſh them all: But what ſhould we talk of the Chriſtian Religion with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Chriſtian Life? Except we find that amongſt them, What ſignifies the Name and Profeſſion of it? And the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Doctrine is wanting in many places too, There be many in this City urging this very Command of Loving God with all their Hearts, and their Neighbours as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as fervently as I can do, or any body elſe; and yet they will tell you in the next breath, that no man in <hi>London</hi> nor in all the World can do this. No Man can poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly Love God with all his Heart: Never a Man can be found that can perform ſuch an Act, as to Love his Neighbour as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: Not every Neighbour it may be, but ſome one choice Aſſociate he can pick out, that he can Love, and bear with his Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities and Affronts, and Love him as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. Love thy Neighbour, that is, every
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:65307:33"/> body; that there may be a Good-will for all People throughout the whole Race of of Mankind; <hi>Peace on Earth, Good-will towards Men:</hi> This is the Fruit of the Goſpel, Chriſtian Words will not make the Chriſtian Religion, there muſt be a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Life; But where ſhall we find that or ſeek for it?</p>
            <p>I know not, I have nothing to do to Judge any body, but there is one that Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth who it is that Liveth the Chriſtian Life, and who doth not; Who is this? What a one is this? <hi>The</hi> Head <hi>of the Chriſtian Church;</hi> Why, is he here? Yes, the Head of the Chriſtian Church is here, and he ſpeaks and gives Sentence; If you have an Ear you may hear him, and if you will turn your Mind inward, for he is an <hi>Inward Miniſter;</hi> every one of you if you will turn your Minds inward, he will tell you whether you Live a Chriſtian Life, and what a Life it is you Live; If there be a Drunkard here, let him ask whether his Life be a Chriſtian Life, will a man go away Ignorant from this place, and have no Anſwer? If there be a Drunkard here let him ask inwardly in his own Boſom. Lord is my Life a Chriſtian Life? I dare affirm on Gods behalf he will have an Anſwer, No, thy Life is not a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:65307:33"/> Life, but a Shameful Beaſtly Life, a Brutiſh one.</p>
            <p>Who told you that the <hi>Head</hi> of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans Chriſt Jeſus is preſent? Chriſt Jeſus, is he preſent? how came he here? He is Aſcended up into Heaven ſuch a Day, ſay they; How came he here? Let him be Aſcended up into Heaven; yet he is not ſo Aſcended into Heaven as not to be here alſo; how ſhould he fufil his Promiſe if he be Circumſcribed in Heaven or Earth? How ſhould he make good his Promiſe if when Two or Three are met together in his Name, he is not in the midſt of them? Here are now many more than Two or Three met together in the Name of Chriſt, and that hope for Acceptance with God through the <hi>Mediator</hi> Chriſt Jeſus; if you think that here are Two or Three met together in the Name of Chriſt, it follows that Chriſt is in the midſt of them.</p>
            <p>I know not what you may enjoy, ſome may poſſibly ſay, I do not find any ſuch Preſence of Chriſt; I hear of the Preſence of Chriſt in the Sacrament, and I have heard talk of the Preſence of Chriſt at a Meeting; but I have been at many a
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:65307:34"/> Meeting and I never found ſuch a Preſence of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Can you Read the Scripture? Yes, I can Read the Scripture as well as you, but that cannot give me a ſenſe of it; I do Read the Scripture and Believe it, but what ſignifies my Reading the Scripture concerning the Preſence of Chriſt, If I have not the ſenſe of it? I have been at many a Meeting but never had the ſenſe of ſuch a Divine Preſence as you talk of, nor it may be at the Sacrament neither. What is the reaſon thou haſt no ſenſe of it? If thou wilt take my Counſel and turn thy mind inward, and enquire whether the thing I ſpeak of be true, whether there be ſuch a Voice as I ſpeak of? That will tell thee what thy State is, if thou wilt be true to thy ſelf, thou mayeſt know the Divine Preſence, and thou mayeſt hear Chriſt ſpeak.</p>
            <p>The Soul hath got Eyes and Ears as well as the Body? What Eyes doth the Apoſtle mean when he ſaith, <hi>The God of this World hath blinded the Eyes of them that Believe not, leſt the Light of the Glorious Goſpel of Chriſt who is the Image of God ſhould ſhine unto them?</hi> If the Soul hath Eyes and Ears as well as the Body, it can Hear and See as the Body: As the Bodily Eye can See
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:65307:34"/> Viſible things, ſo the Eye of the Soul can See things that are Inviſible and Heavenly; you can hear my Voice outwardly, and you may hear the Voice of Chriſt inwardly; I have known ſome that have been afraid to hear ill of themſelves that they would not enquire; ſome have been ſo guilty in their own Conſciences that they have been afraid of hearing ill, that they would not enquire about themſelves: So it is inwardly, ſome have been Conſciou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that their Life and Converſation is nought, that their Life is a Sinful Life, that they dare not put it to the Queſtion: It would cettainly have been told them, thy Life is not a Chriſtian Life, thou muſt mend thy Life before ever thou comeſt to have Peace with God: If this ſhould be thy Portion and mine, that upon ſearch we ſhould find our condition bad, what harm is it?</p>
            <p>I would put one Queſtion to thee, be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in Conſidering of it: We are all Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Wrath by Nature, none of us differ about that; and that unleſs we be born again we cannot enter into the Kingdom of God: The Queſtion is whether I am one of thoſe or no; Suppoſe upon enquiry it be diſcovered to me that I am not; it is bad enough: This is hard, but not ſo hard as it
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:65307:35"/> is true, this is the thing which I would have you Conſider; Am not I in a better caſe to know that I am in a Natural ſtate, than to go on and periſh to Eternity? As long as there is Life there is Hope; as long as a man is upon the Earth and taking care for his Soul, and enquiring about the State of his Immortal Soul: If my Soul is not in a good condition; Is it not better for one to know it, and to ſeek for a cure? For there is no greater Infirmity and Infelicity can be upon a Man than to have ſome oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult and hidden Diſeaſe that he cannot be made ſenſible of; for this waſts and ſpoils him and he cannot be perſuaded to look out for a Remedy; So it is inwardly, if a Man be Ignorant of his condition and go on to his Dying Day and Hour and not ſeek after a Remedy, this Man periſheth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all peradventure. When you are in this enquiry be content to be controlled, be willing to have the Truth ſpoken though it be againſt your ſelves.</p>
            <p>I might inſtance in divers things that I have ſpoken of: If a man be ſatisfied that his Life is not a Chriſtian Life, I ſay, if the Swearer or Lyar, if the Proud Perſon or the Effeminate, as ſoon as they come to be ſatisfied that their Life is not a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:65307:35"/> Life that they now Live, what will this man expect? What Counſel ſhould we give him, and what Counſel ſhould he take? I will go on in the way that I am in, what! after thou knoweſt thy Life is not a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Life? God forbid. Wilt thou go on and perpetrate Sin upon Sin, and heap up Wrath againſt the day of Wrath? I am a Sinner, my Life is Unchriſtian, I make ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to Live in Sin and die in Sin, Is this good Policy? Conſider another Text which our Lord ſpake; <hi>If ye die in your Sins, whether I go you cannot come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O Friends, lay theſe things to your Hearts, what have I to do but to tell you that the Love I have in my Soul to you all makes me deſire in my Heart that you might be ſaved? This is the Will of God that you might all be ſaved and come to the knowledge of the Truth: Bleſſed are they which know the Truth, the Truth as it is in Jeſus; Truth in the inward parts hath a ſpeaking Voice, and if thou hearken to it, it will tell thee that thy ſtate is nought: Canſt thou believe the Truth when it tells thee ſo? That thy ſtate is nought, and that thou art like to go to Eternal Deſtruction unleſs there be Repentance, and Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to prevent it. Canſt thou believe this
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:65307:36"/> Doctrine, when it ſounds in thy own Heart? If thou canſt not Believe it, Unbelief will be thy Ruine: The Spirit of Truth is come to convince the World of Sin, becauſe they believe not in Chriſt; he tells them their Condition and they will not believe him: The Spirit of Chriſt convinceth men of Sin, and they believe him not; The Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Truth convinceth thee of thy Sin, but thou believeſt him not: Thou Loveſt thy Pleaſure, and thy Profit, and thine Hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; then thou Loveſt not God with all thine Heart, and then thou art not a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, but out of Covenant with God: Art thou ſenſible that thy condition is bad; were it not beſt to get it mended? After we are convinced of our own ſinful ſtate, Is it not our beſt courſe to ſeek to have it mended? Who ſhall mend it? Saith one, I have done all I can to mend my Life, and I cannot mend it.</p>
            <p>I have concluded ſo in my younger years I have Faſted, and Prayed, and ſpent time in Hearing, Reading and Meditation, and did all in my own Power, and all to mend my ſtate, but I could not mend it; and as I grew up in years Sin and Corruption more prevailed, and there was no help; and I came ſo far as to believe there was no
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:65307:36"/> help, and that if God did not help me I was undone to all Eternity. I many times wiſht that I had never been born, I went to Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Meetings, and to all ſorts of ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate People, and to all manner of Ordinance, and to all manner of Means to mend this bad Heart of mine; to ſee if I could get a Power that would give me Victory over my Corruption, but my Arm was never ſo long as to reach thereunto; it was far out of my Power and Reach.</p>
            <p>Many have ſought to get this Power of Reforming their Hearts and Lives, to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it by their own hands, by their own endeavours, but they could never do it; they could never better their condition, nor bring forth fruit worthy of amendment of Life; I wiſh that every one was come to that paſs, that they knew not which way to turn them, that they were come at laſt to their Wits end; they will come to it ſooner or later, the ſooner the better. I have done all I can, I can do no more, I am at my Wits end and know not what to think con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning my Eternal State; I know not what to judge of it, I ſtrive againſt my Luſts and Corruptions; but for all that they prevail upon me, Temptations come before me, but I cannot conquer them. O I am glad
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:65307:37"/> when People are come to that paſs that they know not what to do, but to deſpair of their own Arms, of their own Strength, and their own Wit, and deſpair of all other help in the World; I am glad of that.</p>
            <p>But I am not Preaching up Deſpair of Gods Grace and Mercy, but let me tell you, when Men Deſpair of their own doings, and of all outward means and helps, then they are fit Objects for the mercy of God, and not till then; <hi>When the Lord looked and ſaw that there was none to Save and Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, then his own Arm brought Salvation.</hi> God will not ſave t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll then, God will not reveal his Power till Men have done with their own Power; they will never Truſt God while they think they can do ſomething for themſelves. All the Forms of Religion of the ſeveral People of this Nation will do them little good without the Power; What is the meaning of that Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, that have ſuch Maſſes and Prayers and Performances? What is the meaning of it, let us ſearch to the bottom? They ſay, we are Sinners, when we Pray to God for his Bleſſing, and for Salvation by Chriſt; there is this at the bottom: They think theſe Duties and Performances will be very
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:65307:37"/> helpful to their ſtate, helpful towards the knowledge of it; to ſpeak plain Engliſh, theſe are their Gods: If I ſpeak of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane and Wicked People, I would ſay their Luſts is their Gods: But when I ſpeak of Righteous People that are meer Formaliſts, then I ſay their Duties, as they call them, are their Gods: When they have done all, they can do nothing for them, then they have no Gods at all; they are <hi>Godleſs:</hi> And if God doth not help them they are undone to all Eternity.</p>
            <p>When poor Creatures are <hi>Caſt out as it were into the open Field, to the loathing of their Perſons; not ſalted at all, nor ſwadled at all, but lying in the Guilt of their Blood: When I paſſed by thee, ſaith the Lord, and ſaw thee polluted in thy own Blood; I ſaid unto thee, when thou waſt in thy Blood; yea, when thou waſt in thy Blood, I ſaid unto thee, Live. When I paſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d by thee, and look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon thee; behold thy time was a time of Love, and I ſpread my ſkirt over thee, and covered thy Nakedneſs; yea I ſware unto thee, and entred into Covenant with thee, ſaith the Lord God, and thou becameſt mine.</hi> What was it a time of Love when I was ſuch an Obeject in my own Eyes, that I thought I was the moſt miſerable Creature
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:65307:38"/> in the World? One that could not make a good Prayer, nor Diſpute for Religion, nor Perform any Duty; a Poor Creature <hi>Caſt out into the open Field, to the loathing of my Perſon;</hi> Loſt all that I Gained; my Name was from among the Living, my Days were paſſed over in Sorrow, and I ſaid there is nothing but Darkneſs, and Death, and Miſery for me; I uſed all means, and tryed all things, ſave only a living Truſt in God, a truſt in God alone, and that Fleſh and Blood cannot do; Fleſh and Blood cannot know him, therefore Fleſh and Blood cannot truſt in him: Alas! ſaid I, I cannot truſt in the Lord, I cannot caſt my Soul and all my Concernments, my Fame and Reputation in the World, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not caſt all upon the care of the Almighty, I cannot know him nor truſt in them, how can I do it? No body can do it: They that know my Name, ſaith the Lord, they will put their truſt in me; never a truer word was ſpoken, but how they ſhould know God and truſt in him, I know not.</p>
            <p>When thou comeſt once to this paſs to be at thy Wits end, and not know which way to turn thee, nor to whom to run for help, or to ask Councel for thy Souls well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare; thou art come to the end of all, and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:65307:38"/> without hope, then God reveals himſelf by his Son Jeſus Chriſt; Chriſt the Son of God is known by our coming to him, but none can come unto Chriſt except the Father which hath ſent him draw him: When thou haſt done with thy Gods, and thrown away thy Idols to the Batts and Moles, then thou wilt find the Lord, and thou wilt cry out, O that God would have mercy upon me, and lift up the light of his Countenance upon me, I am a poor miſerabie Creature: There are many that make ſuch a Whining and Complaining that they take a pride in their very Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints; their Hypocriſie is ſo great, I have known ſome that have prided themſelves in wording their Condition and expreſſing their miſerable caſe before the Lord, but ſuppoſe thou canſt not ſpeak at all, but feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thy ſelf miſerable, thou canſt not expreſs thy Condition: At ſuch a time as this God was drawing thy Soul to Chriſt Jeſus the Mediator of it; I have heard of a Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and that there is <hi>Balm in Gilead</hi> for me, that there is a Phyſitian there, that there is one Phyſitian, even Jeſus Chriſt the Mediator of the New Covenant; thou haſt ſinned againſt him and grieved him; yet he ſtands with open Arms for thee, ready
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:65307:39"/> to receive thee and embrace thee; where ſtands he? He ſtands at the Door and Knocks; it is a ſmall matter, one would think, to let him in, Rev. 3.20. Behold, <hi>I ſtand at the Door and knock, and if any man he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r my Voice and open the Door; I will come in to him, and ſup with him, and he with me.</hi> Here is good News for a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry Soul, if any ſuch be here; Chriſt the Mediator ſtands at the Door and Knocks, he will come in and Sup with thee; if thou open to him, then we ſhall meet with the Lords Supper: <hi>This is the Lord, we will wait for him;</hi> he will bring his Bread with him. The Bread of Life and the Wine of his Kingdom: And the Lords Supper will be celebrated without cavilling and jangling.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe we do not pervert the Scripture, I would have you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand Books read what <hi>Commentators</hi> ſay; what thoſe of this and former Ages ſay upon this Text, whether they do not Conſture and Deliver in their Opinions that this Knocking at the Door is Chriſts Calling the Soul by his Grace, and this Door is the Door of the Heart, and Chriſts Calling the Soul by his Grace and Spirit to let him in by Faith: This is their Judgment and
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:65307:39"/> Senſe, and their Senſe is mine, and I believe the Genuin Senſe of the Text, that Chriſt would have People think he is near to them, and that he would have People open their Hearts and Receive him by Faith for to be a Saviour to them.</p>
            <p>No; that, ſaith Fleſh and Blood, I cannot bear, I cannot conſent to have him for my Saviour, I will not let him in, for he is like <hi>Micaiah</hi> to <hi>Ahab; He never ſpeaks good concerning me.</hi> For if I have him for my Saviour I muſt part with my Luſts and Pleaſures; if there be any other Saviour I will try, and not meddle with him; He will ſpoil all our Mirth and good Society, he will tell me of every Idle word that I ſhall ſpeak, I muſt give an Account thereof at the Day of Judgment: What do you think that I can like ſuch a Saviour? That I can live with ſuch a one as will call me to an Account for every word I ſpeak, and that if I ſpeak one idle word Judgment will come upon me. No, I will try one and another, rather than accept of him upon ſuch terms; I am one that am joyned to ſuch a Church, and enjoy ſuch and ſuch Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and ſuch Helps: I am in Covenant with God, and under the Seals of that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant; I am Baptized and do partake of
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:65307:40"/> the Lords Supper, which is another Seal of the Covenant; I hope it will be well with me.</p>
            <p>I will go ſomething farther; another ſaith, we muſt have a Mediator; I will go to the <hi>Virgin Mary,</hi> and offer ſomething to her, and pray to her,: Saith another, I will go to Saint <hi>James,</hi> and Saint <hi>John,</hi> and other Saints, to Intercede with God for me: They muſt have ſome Mediator. This is the Twiſting and Twining of the Sons and Daughters of Men to keep out Chriſt the Great Mediator, who came into the World for this purpoſe to deſtroy the works of the Devil: Alas! I have nothing left but my bare Life and Living in the World; I have nothing left me but ſome <hi>Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tle deſire I had to pleaſe God;</hi> and that he will never Judge and Condemn me for; but my falſe deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and buying and ſelling with Deceit, He will Judge this, and Condemn it. And my Diſcourſing of things without me; all my Carnal Friendſhip and Love of the World, and my vain Faſhions, all that is Corrupt and Defiled; theſe he came on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to deſtroy: He came to deſtroy bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h the Devil and his Works: What can a man Live in the World, and never joyn wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h the Devil? Never Sin at all? Never do
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:65307:40"/> any thing that the Devil would have him do? There is no Perfection in this World; no living without Sin here; then I am ſure there is no Unity with Chriſt here, and if there be no Unity with Chriſt, then there is none with God the Father; What will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of thee now? What will all the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders for that opinion ſay now? There is ſome thing ſtands betwen God and me, and I ſhall never have Peace; and what is that? It is Sin. I would have my Sin taken away, elſe I had better never been born: Canſt thou remove Sin out of thy Heart? I have tryed, but I cannot do it; I have heard of Chriſt the <hi>Mediator</hi> of the New Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant: He ſaith, he came into the World, and that for this purpoſe he was manifeſted that he might deſtroy the works of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil. Now Sin in my Heart is the Devils work, I will ſee if he will deſtroy that for me; I will truſt and rely upon him, and ſee if his great Power can deſtroy it in me.</p>
            <p>Here People come rightly to believe in him that God hath ſent, and truſt in him; and he will take them in, and like a Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion he will rip up their Hearts, and l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t out their Corrruptions, though there hath been never ſo much Rottenneſs, and he will heal them and purifie them and pardon them,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:65307:41"/> though they have been never ſo wicked, if they come to him; when thy Sins are ſet in order before thee, then thou cryeſt out, <hi>O wretched Man that I am, who ſhall deliver me from this body of Death?</hi> Is it God that hath thought of me; and waited to be Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and hath born my Sin long; how wonderful is his patience towards me? All theſe things working in the Soul tend to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get a Love to God, and fervent deſires after being cleanſed and purified from Sin; and earneſt Prayer to the Lord to make that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Fire to kindle that would burn it up: The more the Soul truſteth in Chriſt, the more doth this Heavenly Fire burn up our Luſts and then a Man feels a great change in his mind. The things (ſaith he) that I delighted in are now grievous to me; I hope I ſhall never be found in thoſe things again, my mind is now taken off them; who took it off? Didſt thou not ſtrive be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to take it off? I did, but I could not do it.</p>
            <p>There are many I believe in this Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly before the Lord that are my witneſſes in this matter, that when they came to Chriſt the Mediator he changed their minds, and he untyed the Devils fetters; they were tyed to their Sins and Luſts, but he hath unlooſed
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:65307:41"/> them, and ſet them at liberty; and they now find ſuch a change, that they hate thoſe things they loved; and when they come to think of them, they are aſhamed, they are aſhamed of thoſe things that they formerly took pleaſure in; <hi>What fruit</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>had you in thoſe things, whereof you are now aſhamed?</hi> So I ſay, what pleaſure have you in Sporting, and Gaming, and Drinking, and Company-keeping? What pleaſure have you to think of your Wanton Diſcourſes? What pleaſure in Pride and Vanity? What pleaſure in Wrath and Bitterneſs of mind? And what pleaſure in Malice and Envy? What plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure have you in thoſe things whereof you are now aſhamed? So far as you are convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced you are aſhamed to think of them; I am aſhamed to think that the Devil at ſuch a time, by ſuch a Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation ſhould prevail over me. I would to God you were all come to this to be aſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that you might remember your paſt evil Ways and Actions with ſorrow and ſhame: There is a ſecret Joy in this: Sure it is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be aſhamed than to continue in impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. God hath wrought this change at laſt and who ſhall have the Glory of it? God ſhall have the glory of it, for his own
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:65307:42"/> Works will praiſe him. What men do many times they do for their own praiſe, but when they are at their wits end and know not what to do, they caſt themſelves upon their Maker to ſee if he will have mercy upon them; if not, they muſt Periſh; then for what he doth, he gets the Glory and the Praiſe of it.</p>
            <p>There are ſome here that are bound to praiſe God while they have a Day to live, for what he hath done for them; They could never have loved God with all their Hearts, but they would have continued Strangers to God, and the Devil would have led them Captive at his Will: They would not have loved God with all their Hearts, had not God firſt <hi>ſhed abroad his love upon their hearts,</hi> and conſtrained them to love him; it is he that hath firſt loved them, and <hi>wrought in them both to will and to do, of his own good pleaſure.</hi> Whatſoever we are, we are by the Grace of God; this Grace is magnified in them that believe, and obey the Goſpel: My Friends, we know there is ſo much Peace and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in the ways of God, ſo much Soul-ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in Walking with God, and loving of him with all our Hearts, That I ſhould be glad that every one of you were of the ſame mind and had experience of it. We Labour
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:65307:42"/> diligently for this purpoſe, and we would ſet before you theſe two things.</p>
            <p>Firſt how we may come to know our miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erable State by Nature?</p>
            <p>What a bleſſed and happy S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ate they are in, that have been Converted and Changed; that have been tranſlated out of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Darkneſs into the Kingdom of God's Dear Son?</p>
            <p>Conſider your State by Nature is Evil, we hope that many of you in hearing the Reports of the Goſpel, concerning the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Lord; his great love in ſending his Son into the World to ſeek and ſave you that were loſt, and that you may believe in him. And we are perſwaded that by the Fooliſhneſs of Preaching God will ſave ſome of you, that you may be his Redeemed Ones, and truſt to no other Saviour, for there is not any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Name under Heaven but the Name of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> by which you can be ſaved; He only can take away the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns of the World, his Spirit ſearcheth the Heart, and tryeth the Reins; which he promiſed to ſend into the World when he was leaving it. Now I dare Proclaim that Holy Spirit to be the Spirit of the God of Heaven, that now ſees what Reſolution thou art of, and what thou art now propoſing to do; whether to go
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:65307:43"/> on in Sin, or to return to God: This I can ſpeak without Blaſphemy; it is God's Spirit that ſearcheth thy Heart, and knoweth thy thoughts and purpoſes, and convinceth thee of thy Sin, God hath ſent his Son Chriſt Jeſus into the World to enlighten you, that by his Light you might ſee him, and that by his Grace you migh Receive him, and that by his Grace you might be ſaved.</p>
            <p>To him I commit you all; and theſe words that we have ſpoken are in the Evidence and Demonſtration of the Spirit, according as he hath wrought in us.</p>
            <p>I muſt tell you we were never called of God to Study <hi>Sermons</hi> for you, nor to Preach things that are made Ready to our hands; but as the Lord our God hath wrought in us, and as God hath been pleaſed to make known his mind to us, and by his <hi>Spirit</hi> given us utterance: So we ſpeak, and ſo we Preach: You that are come to believe and receive the things of the Spirit, you will Judge what I ſay: I ſpeak unto you that are Spiritual, Judge ye what I ſay, ſaith the Apoſtle; ſo when I ſpeak of Divine and Heavenly things, you that are Spiritual Judge what I ſay, and as you come to Judge and Determine in your ſelves that theſe things are true; you will feel the Power of them in your own Spirits:
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:65307:43"/> And we ſhall all be of the ſame mind, and as we have <hi>One God,</hi> we ſhall ſerve him in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity, and Worſhip him with Reverence; then his Name ſhall be Exalted in the midſt of us, and we ſhall Edifie one another in Love, and we ſhall inſtruct one another, and call upon one another: Come let us go to the Houſe of the God of <hi>Jacob,</hi> He will Teach us and Preſerve us in his way, and do us good and keep us from all Evil.</p>
            <p>Turn your minds inward, and conſider that God is a God at hand ready to help you, and he requires no more of you than of other People in former times, to love the Lord with all your Hearts, and to abſtract and withdraw your minds from all other things that do come in Competition with him, and be ſure to have no Truſt or Dependance but upon him: Then ſee what God will do for you, no Tongue can expreſs, nor Pen Write; neither hath it entred into the Heart of Man to conceive the things that God hath prepared for thoſe that love him. That Wiſdom, and Knowledge, that Joy, and Peace, and Conſolation that paſſeth all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding: He will reveal and Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate by his Spirit to them that love him, and truſt in him and rely upon him, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive teaching from him; he will feed them
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:65307:44"/> with Food in due ſeaſon, he will bring the former and the latter Rain, and they ſhall be as Trees planted by the River of Water, and bring forth Fruit in due ſeaſon, and their Leaf ſhall not Fade, or wither. This hath been <hi>Londons</hi> wonder, and <hi>Englands</hi> wonder; How comes it to paſs that ſuch a Peoples Leaf hath not Withered nor Faded, as many have done? Our Root was by a River. If we had ſtood in our ſelves, if our depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance and ſupport had been upon Doctrines, Tenets and Commandments of Men, then our Leaf would have been upon the Ground as well as others; but becauſe we have been upon Our Root Chriſt <hi>Jeſus,</hi> that is, always Green both in Summer and Winter, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Leaf hath not withered, to the Praiſe of God and the Honour of his Name be it ſpoken: He hath preſerved us, for we have no Power of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſelves no more than others; but we truſt in God, and have received Power from God to ſtand as witneſſes for him; We have truſted in the Lord, and he hath ſtood by us; and delivered us when we were compaſſed about with Dangers and Diſtreſſes. If we continue to truſt in him ſtill, he will bring us through all our Tryals and Troubles, and he will be with us, and never leave us nor forſake us, if we take him for our God we ſhall never need any other.</p>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:65307:44"/>
            <p>We read that <hi>Senacherib</hi> King of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> ſent <hi>Rabſhekah</hi> to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kiah</hi> with a great Army; ſaying, <hi>What Confidence is this wherein thou truſteſt, and he ſpake alſo to the People, and cryed with a loud Voice, hear you the Words of the Great King of</hi> Aſſyria, <hi>let not</hi> Hezekiah <hi>deceive you, for he ſhall not be able to deliver you; neither let</hi> Hez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kiah <hi>make you truſt in the Lord, ſaying, the Lord will deliver us,</hi> Hezekiah <hi>he went and prayed to the Lord, ſaying, O Lord of Hoſts, God of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>that dwelleſt between the Cherubims, thou art the God, the God alone of all the Kingdoms of the Earth, thou haſt made</hi> Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>and Earth, incline thine Ear O Lord, and hear, open thine Eyes O Lord and See, and hear all the words of</hi> Senacherib, <hi>which hath ſent to Reproach the living God &amp;c.</hi> And we Read that after he had preſented his ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before the Lord: <hi>The Angel of the Lord went forth and ſmote in the Camp of the</hi> Aſſyrians, <hi>one hund<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed fourſcore and five thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, and when they a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſe ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing behold they were all Dead Corps.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you ſee what came of it a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> laſt, and thus it hath been in our Day; they th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t truſt in the Lord he will deliver them, and they ſhall never be aſhamed nor Confounded, but as for all other Gods, they that truſt in them
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:65307:45"/> ſhall be confounded and covered with ſhame, and they and their Gods will periſh to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
            <p>And now my Friends, I beſeech you all to have reſpect to this great duty of putting your whole truſt in the Lord, who is the Living God and he will be always preſent with you, and work in you both to will and to do of his good pleaſure; he will ſupport and preſerve you in all your Tryals, and ſufferings, that you may be Veſſels of Hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to bear his Name in the Earth, and to ſound forth his Praiſe to the following Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations.</p>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>His Prayer after Sermon.</head>
               <p>MOST Glorious, infinite, Powerful Father who haſt Created us and given us Life and Breath, and lengthened out our time to this Day, and haſt long waited to be Gracious to us, and art ſtill waiting upon the Sons and Daughters of Men; holding forth the hand of thy love, and offering thy Grace, and tendering Salvation unto them, and haſt brought a Day of Viſitation upon the Inhabitants of this City and Nation: Glory, Praiſe and Thanksgiving be to thee, O Lord that by thy Power haſt inclined the Hearts and Conſciences of the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:65307:45"/> Sons and Daughters of Men to ſubmit to thee, and bowed their Necks to the Bleſſed and eaſie Yoke of thy Son Jeſus Chriſt, that they may do thy will on Earth as it is done in Heaven: They that are Traveling, and diſtreſſed, and Afflicted in their Souls becauſe of their bondage, do thou ariſe living Father, and reveal, and diſcover thy Power to them, ſhew them the exceeding greatneſs of thy Power that they may truſt therein, and be ſafe; make bare thine Arm for their Salvation: Thoſe that are ſlumbering in their Profeſſion, let them be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakened, and bring to thine Heavenly King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom thoſe that have paſſed through thy Refi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Fire; and whom thou haſt Cleanſed and Sanctified: Powerful Father of Life carry on thy work among thy People every where, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther them that are ſcattered; and bring back to thy ſelf thoſe that are wandering and out of the way, and ſeeking the living among the Dead; Lord teach them and let them hear a Voice behind them, and guide them to thy Holy Mountain, that they may be brought to the path of Life, and to the place which thou haſt provided for thy little Flock to meet and Feed together; Offering unanimoſly the Sacrifices of Praiſe and Thanksgiving, which thou haſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained and appointed in thine Houſe. Bleſſed and Powerful Father, all thy little ones be
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:65307:46"/> pleaſed to ſurround with thine Almighty Power; and where ever they are let them feel thy preſerving Hand, delivering them from the Evil of the World: We pray not that thou ſhould'ſt take them out of the World, but to preſerve them from the Defilements and Pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of it: That a Holy People may ſerve thee the <hi>Holy</hi> God; and bear thy Holy Name upon their Hearts, That, that above all may be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted and magnified, and humble Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>givings and Praiſes may be given unto thee, through Jeſus Chriſt, for all thy love thou haſt manifeſted, and for thy abounding mercies, and renewed favours which we have received at thy hands; to thee living Father through Chriſt Jeſus thy well beloved Son in whom thou art well pleaſed, be all Honour, Praiſe and Dominion rendred by us and all thy People, from henceforth, and for Ever, and Ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="sermon">
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:65307:46"/>
            <head>Sermon IV. The Standard of Truth. <hi>Preached at</hi> Grace-Church-Street, May 29. 1692.</head>
            <p>THERE is an Univerſal <hi>Standard</hi> of Truth that God hath ſet up over all the Sons and Daughters of Men; he hath given the Knowledge of it in and through Jeſus Chriſt, he hath dealt it out to them, that they may be capable of joyning and adhering to the Truth, and to be delivered from Eternal Condemnation. This <hi>Standard and Meaſuring Rule</hi> is revealed, and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted in every Man and Woman, by the Light that ſhines in their Hearts; by which they are able to diſcern, and to give a ſound and true Judgment (if they are but willing) upon <hi>all their own Ways.</hi> A Man or Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man may know, in every word they ſpeak, in every Action they do, whether they ſpeak and do according to the Truth, or whether
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:65307:47"/> they are juſtified by the Truth in what they ſpeak and do.</p>
            <p>I tell you my Friends this is no ſmall mercy that Mankind hath obtained at the Hands of his Maker, that he is brought into a Capacity of not acting blind-fold: but that he may ſee his way and his own Inclinations, and paſs Judgment upon them whether they are good or evil, whether they will ſtand juſtified in the ſight of his Maker, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they will be Condemned.</p>
            <p>I Confeſs the vail of Ignorance that is come over the Sons and Daughters of Men, through Sin, Transgreſſion, and Rebellion, is very great. And I may ſay as the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>ſometime you were darkneſs;</hi> and what can Darkneſs ſee? What can darkneſs diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover? The Lord our God that made us hath not left us in that State of Darkneſs, Blindneſs, and Ignorance; but through the Riches of his Mercy and goodneſs, hath found out a way to command that Light ſhould ſhine out of Darkneſs into Peoples Hearts for all that the Devil did to darken Man, to alienate and eſtrange him from his Maker.</p>
            <p>The ſame Almighty Power that ſaid in the Creation. <hi>Let there be Light and it was ſo,</hi> he hath ſhined into our Hearts, and the way
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:65307:47"/> by which he hath done ſo, is through the Mediator, through Jeſus Chriſt the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, <hi>in whom the fulneſs of the Godhead dwells.</hi> He hath received Power from his Father, not only to be Light and Salvation, but to impart and Communicate of that Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Light unto them, even unto every one that cometh into the World, that ſo by means thereof they may be delivered from their Darkneſs, and Ignorance of the mind of God, that they were lyable to in the Fall; and might be reſtored through the Mediator to a Capacity of Judging of their own ſtate as the Lord Judgeth, and of their own Actions, and of their own words, and ways and Inclinations.</p>
            <p>This is the <hi>Standard</hi> which God hath pitched in every one of your Boſoms for the Tryal of your ſelves; either for Juſtification or Condemnation of every Word and Action.</p>
            <p>Now to make every one ſenſible of the greatneſs of this bleſſing: Conſider it is not only given to augment, and to encreaſe Knowledge; but it is given on purpoſe to allure and perſwade Men into a likeing of Truth, into a Love of Truth: The Apoſtle eſteemed it a wonderful mercy that came by Chriſt, he hath ſent him to bleſs us, in turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:65307:48"/> every one of us from the Evil of his ways, ſo that here is a Capacity that the Sons and Daughters of Men have, through the Mediator, of being turned from the Evil of their ways and doings to that which is well pleaſing to God.</p>
            <p>The next work after God hath wrought thu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mercifully for the Sons and Daughters of Men, is that they would be good to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and merciful to themſelves, and take pity of themſelves; by a due Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of the Grace and Mercy, and kindneſs of God, that he hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed freely upon them, and in bringing all their D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eds to that Standard; all their words and Actions to that Rule, that ſo whatſoever they be, or how many ſo ever, if they do not anſwer that Standard and Rule, they may deny, withſtand and reſiſt them; that ſo they may keep out of Condemnation: For the Apoſtle declares it plainly without ſcruple: <hi>There is no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> If he had ſaid, to them that profeſs Chriſt Jeſus, there had been a large Latitude, eſpecially for theſe Nations, but the Words are limitted, and you will find them ſo; that is, <hi>to them that are in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> and (as if he ſhould ſay) that you may know rightly whom I mean; I
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:65307:48"/> mean <hi>ſuch as walk not after the Fleſh, but after the Spirit:</hi> They that are in Chriſt walk after his Spirit, for, <hi>they that have not the Spirit of Chriſt are none of his;</hi> but they that are his, walk after the Spirit, the Spirit of Truth; and there is no Condemnation to them.</p>
            <p>It is not only the Scriptures that Ratify and confirm this Doctrine, but you your ſelves are all living witneſſes of the Truth of this; that ſo far as you do act and ſpeak in Obedience to the Principle of Truth, that God hath Planted in you; you feel no Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation upon you: Such a thing I did at ſuch a time, and I had no Condemnation, Why ſo? Becauſe I did it in Obedience, and Subjection to that meaſure of Grace that God ſet up in me; and ſuch a thing I did, for which I was Condemned, why ſo? B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cauſe I did it according to the Inclination of my own Corrupt mind, and in Contradiction to the truth that opened in me.</p>
            <p>My Friends, I would have you in point of the Doctrine of Chriſtianity to be the better for what you Read and hear; it is poſſible for me to Preach the Truth, and you may believe what I ſay, and you may Read the Holy Scriptures, and have the belief of what you Read, but if you come to a ſenſible feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:65307:49"/> of the fulfilling of the things you hear, you will give a greater Seal to the Truth of the Doctrine, than by all you have Read and heard; and you will <hi>grow wiſe to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> by trying and experiencing the effect of every thing you underſtand: And not like the Carnal Men of this World, that have not Faith, that mind only their Worldly Profits and Pleaſures; ſuch are <hi>Earthly, Senſual, Deviliſh;</hi> but I would judge of Actions and Words, according to truth, and according to the eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct I find in me: I did ſuch a thing, and I had peace in the doing of it, I feel no Reproach, no Condemnation upon me; here is a way for People to grow up in the Life of Chriſtianity, to keep to the Standard of Truth; for whether Men will or no, they muſt do it at laſt, and may now if they pleaſe, make a Tryal of their Words and Actions.</p>
            <p>As for the moſt part of you, you are got paſt <hi>Pilate, Pilate</hi> could make that enquiry, <hi>What is Truth?</hi> ſaith he; And I confeſs it is not long ago, it is within the Memory of Man that a more ſerious and better ſort of People were confounded with the Darkneſs and Ignorance of thoſe times that they were ready to cry out, What is Truth? And where is Truth? Their Eyes were ſo blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:65307:49"/> and things were ſo jumbled and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed by the Diſputations that Men Raiſed; they made things ſo dark that People could not ſee their way: but God who hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Light to ſhine out of Darkneſs, hath brought a <hi>Glorious Day,</hi> that hath diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pated, and ſcattered, and driven away a great deal of that Fogg, and Miſt, that did over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread Mens minds: As many as have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely ſought the Truth in the inward parts, they have found a Divine Principle of Truth, that hath a ſelf evidencing quality in it ſelf; to convince the Minds and Conſciences of the Sons and Daughters of Men, that it is the Truth: And to this the Lord hath brought moſt of you, to be ſenſible of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that is Truth in it ſelf; There are many things that are true in the Words of them, many true Expreſſions; but there is Truth in it ſelf, the Eſſential Truth of God, which as it is in God is Everlaſting and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal, and will ſtand over all Errour, Falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and Deceit; as the Truth is in Chriſt Jeſus, it is a Standard and Rule for Men to act by: He hath given it to the Sons and Daughters of M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, and as it appears in them, it is either a Judge to Condemn them, or a Saviour to ſave them from their Sins, and ſo to juſtifie them.</p>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:65307:50"/>
            <p>Now that which concerns us, is to find out that meaſure of Truth, or manifeſtation of Truth, or Principle of Truth; which it hath pleaſed God to reveal in our ſelves: And whoſoever will turn their minds a little while inward, into the ſerious ſearch and Conſideration, how the Lord hath dealt with them; they will find they are not quite deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of Truth. One that makes it his practice to Lye, Cheat, and Cozen, or one that is a <hi>Lyar,</hi> is not utterly deſtitute of Truth; for there is a Principle of Truth in him, that doth Check him, and Reprove him for his Theft, Lying, and Falſhood; and he lives under Condemnation in himſelf: He cannot draw near to the God of Truth upon any oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, but his Lying and Falſhood ſtands in his way. Now if ſo be that this Lyar be made ſenſible of a Principle of Truth in him; do but bring his Words and actions to the Truth, ſo much of it as he knows will make him leave <hi>Lying,</hi> and D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ceiving, and he muſt Practiſe Truth to eſcape Condemnation, and if he will but l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave Lying and Falſhood, and live in the Truth, and ſpeak the Truth to his Neighbour; he will find another State, Condition, and frame in his Soul than there was before. He is now more at Peace, and hath a Clear and Serene way to come to God
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:65307:50"/> by Prayer, and for pouring out his Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, which he had not before; for he had barred up his own way by his Sin, which lay continually at the Door; <hi>If thou doſt not well Sin lies at the Door,</hi> ſaith God to <hi>Cain;</hi> ſo when you do Evil, you cannot but know it; when you are Drunk, or Swear, or tell a Lye, and deceive your Neighbour, and carry on the deſign of ſinful profit, thou knoweſt it, whether Men know it or no, and God that made thee knoweth it, and there thy Sin lies at the door, and blocks and bars thee out, that thou canſt not offer thy Prayers to God with that clearneſs, as if thou hadſt ſpoken the Truth; ſo that it highly concerns every one of us to be wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon God for the diſcovery of his Truth to us; and then we muſt Embrace, Adhere, and join to the Truth as our chiefeſt good.</p>
            <p>But ſome will ſay, this Adhering and joining to the Truth is a hard Leſſon: It is pretty eaſie to find out a Principle of Truth, that ſtandeth againſt and oppoſeth all manner of Evil. Very few now a days will deny a ſetled Principle of Truth in every Man, that judgeth Falſhood and Condemneth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it, and witneſſeth againſt it in others, and in themſelves: But this ſame joining, and
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:65307:51"/> Adhering to it, that cannot be done without a Croſs to a Carnal mind.</p>
            <p>Now if the Croſs of Chriſt be not taken up, there is no good Chriſtianity among us; where this is neglected, it ſpots and ſtains the Profeſſion of Chriſtianity; becauſe it is ſo directly oppoſite to the Doctrine of Chriſt; <hi>He that will be my Diſciple muſt,</hi> it is not, he may if he will; but <hi>He muſt take up the Croſs of</hi> Chriſt <hi>and follow</hi> Him. There were a ſort of People that were never like to be made Chriſtians, that would be exempt from taking up a daily Croſs; therefore he preſſeth it upon them to deny themſelves and take up his Croſs and follow him. No man is like to live a Chriſtian Life without taking up a Daily Croſs.</p>
            <p>This I cannot do, ſaith one, I know how to carry my ſelf among Chriſtians with Seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, Sobriety and Watchfulneſs without ſhaming my Profeſſion; but I cannot deny my ſelf, I cannot contradict my own Will: This is that which keeps a man from leading a Chriſtian Life, Then he cannot deny him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and take up his daily Croſs.</p>
            <p>Now it is come to this, now a days when a Light is broke forth, and Men have a Principle of Truth in their own Hearts: It comes to this; ſaith one, I ought to be
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:65307:51"/> Holy in all manner of Converſation, and to be Watchful over my Words; and have my Converſation Honeſt and Juſt without Deceit. See what a deal I know, yet I can never Live this Life for all I know it ſo well; I cannot take up a daily Croſs which is ſo much againſt the contrary inclinations working in me. Then the Queſtion I put to my ſelf is, Shall I take up a Croſs or no?</p>
            <p>Here it comes to the point with every Man or Woman after they come to the knowledge of this <hi>Standard</hi> of Truth: If the World would but come to this Rule and Standard, there would be no more Cheating, Couzening; no more Fraud, Deceit nor Emulation; nor War and Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, if Men would but in every thing they do, anſwer the Principle of Truth in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; they would put the Queſtion to themſelves: Shall I take up a daily Croſs or no? Shall I deny my ſelf thoſe Pleaſures that my Conſcience doth condemn? And thoſe ungodly gains that I ſeek after by Falſhood, by Lying, Prevaricating and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting from the Truth, ſhall I do this, that I may be Rich and Great in the World?</p>
            <p>You know what I ſay, many of you, and
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:65307:52"/> have put this Queſtion to your ſelves, and ſome have made a good Anſwer to it: I will take up my daily Croſs by the Grace of God; this Standard of Truth ſhall be the Rule of my Words and actions to my Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-day.</p>
            <p>They that have learned this Leſſon and obtained peace with God through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that have not only made a Reſolution but performed it in Act and Deed, by the Power of Chriſts Croſs they will be Purified and Sanctified and Waſhed from their Old Converſations, and <hi>Have their Converſation in Heaven;</hi> that is, Live after a Heavenly manner; Live a Godly Life here upon Earth, when they have come to this Reſolution, and alſo to the Practice of it.</p>
            <p>I would deſire and it is my Labour that you that hear me this Day; that are aware of what I am ſpeaking, <hi>viz. The Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard of Truth.</hi> The Principle of Truth, that unerring Guide, which is placed in the Conſcience of every Man, that Juſtifieth or Condemneth his Actions and Words: You that come to be aware of this, that you may all come to this Godly Reſolution in your ſelves I would have this Diſpute carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on in every ones Boſom; when the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:65307:52"/> Queſtion is ſtated, I would have you real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Anſwer it: Shall I guide my Actions and Words according to this unerring Rule or no? I cannot tell what to ſay, ſay ſome, there is danger in it: What danger can there be to anſwer that which a Man knows to be Truth? I will tell you what danger: The World is Perverſe, the moſt men Live out of Truth; and the Devil is a Cunning Adverſary, and he would have none Live in it: <hi>He abode not in the Truth;</hi> and he would not have us live in it, nor regulate our Words and Actions by the Truth in our own Souls: What if moſt Men in the World pervert the Truth? What if ſo few walk in the <hi>Narrow Way,</hi> and ſo few come to Life Eternal; therefore is that an Argument, I muſt not come there? ſhould it not ſtir me up to greater diligence, that by any means I may be of the number of that few that ſhall obtain Salvation, and not go with a agreat company in the Way that leads to Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; If we improve our Times and Seaſons, and Opportunities, and Mercies, and Bleſſings that are vouchſafed to us; we at laſt may obtain Life Eternal.</p>
            <p>But ſome may ſay, I muſt ſit down in Deſpair, for I cannot come thither of my ſelf, though I do what I can to <hi>Work out my
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:65307:53"/> own Salvation:</hi> There is a Decree againſt me, what though I ſhould Pray never ſo much, and ſpend my Nights in Grief and Sorrow? If I be Decreed to Eternal Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; there is no help for me, no hope that I ſhould eſcape it: And if I be Decreed to Salvation, though I take my Liberty to Sin and be Looſe and Wanton as others; it cannot hinder me from attaining Salvation at laſt.</p>
            <p>For this Reaſon many have laid aſide the Spiritual Warfare againſt Corruption, and their Spiritual Travel, that they will do do nothing in order to their Everlaſting Happineſs; therefore they think they had as good take their Pleaſure: But my Friends, the caſe is not now ſo with us; Let every Soul among us praiſe the Lord for his mercy in expelling that thick Cloud of Darkneſs, which is vaniſhed and gone: This I know, and I hope you do all believe that God doth every where, and in every Nation call Sinners to Repentance, and that <hi>He delighteth not in the Death of him that Dyeth, but rather that they would turn and Live;</hi> and in order thereunto he hath given his Son Jeſus Chriſt to be a Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and a Mediator, and he hath ſent forth the Spirit of his Son into our Hearts to give
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:65307:53"/> direction to us in our Way: Now our Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is to make improvement of thoſe Viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Mercy that God hath beſtowed upon us in order to our Salvation; and not Live in <hi>Rioting and Drunkenneſs, Chambering and Wantonneſs, Strife and Envying,</hi> and following the Faſhons of the World: But we muſt <hi>Work out our own Salvation with Fear and Trembling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſome will ſay, Is not this done alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy? Is it not already wrought by our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and Mediator? <hi>Chriſt hath taſted Death for every Man,</hi> and laid down a Price for the Soul of every Man.</p>
            <p>But there muſt be a change wrought in us: There is a Tranſlation of our Souls from one ſtate to another: This is called in the Scriptute Regeneration, and being born again, this is called a being baptized into Chriſt, and deſcribed alſo by other expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions: But the matter is to Change thy Life, for there is a ſinful Source of Wickedneſs that is ſtirred up by the Motions of the Powers of Darkneſs and our own concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence, but God is always ready to bring us under the Government of his Holy Spirit that will lead us into into all Truth; and this cannot be done without a Croſs; but the Queſtion lies here, Shall I take up this
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:65307:54"/> Croſs or no? if I do, it will <hi>Crucifie me to the World.</hi> Let me ſee; How much do I Love the World? A great deal: But do I Love the World better than my own Soul? <hi>What will it profit me to gain the whole World, and loſe my own Soul? Or what ſhall I give in Exchange for my Soul?</hi> I cannot get to Heaven without denying my ſelf; let me take care of my Immortal Soul; I am a poor Creature, I will ſerve the Lord my Maker, and make it my buſineſs to Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie and Pleaſe him: He can ſnatch me away by Death when he pleaſeth, therefore I will labour that my Thoughts, Words, and Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Converſation may anſwer to that rule, that he hath ſet before me, as a Standard of Truth to ſquare and regulate my actions by. I will not live any longer in vanity as many do, I do not know but my Breath may be ſtopt to Day before to Morrow; therefore <hi>To Day while it is called to Day, I will hear</hi> Gods Voice and <hi>not harden my Heart,</hi> but receive that Counſel that is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to me for the benefit of my Soul; I am bought with a Price, I am none of my own, I will live to him that died for me, I have more Reaſon to live to Chriſt and ſerve him that ſhed his precious Blood for the Redemption of my Soul, and to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:65307:54"/> to him; then to be ſubject to Chriſts Enemy, to the Prince of the Power of the Air that Rules in the Children of Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; I will take up a Reſolution to ſerve God, but I can do nothing of my ſelf, but <hi>The Grace of God which brings Salvation, will teach me to deny Ungodlineſs and World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Luſts; and to live Righteouſly, Soberly and Godly in this preſent World.</hi> Take heed of being deceived and beguiled for there is no way will bring you to Heaven, but an Holy and Undefiled way.</p>
            <p>Therefore come and take this Standard of Truth in your hands to guide you in your way, that you may neither turn to the Right hand nor to the Left; this will ſhew you the way you ſhould walk in, and be like the Cloud and Pillar of Fire to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in their journey to <hi>Canaan</hi> which was a Type of Heaven; the Cloud they could ſee by Day, and the Pillar of Fire by Night; ſo this Standard of Truth will direct you in your Travel to the Heavenly <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an:</hi> Let this be the Rule and Meaſure of your Thoughts, Words and Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>If a workman that is a Builder hath a
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:65307:55"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:65307:55"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:65307:56"/> Rule to work by, if he goes on and never examines his Work by his Rule, but makes his Eye his Rule; if he doth not bring his Rule to his work every little while, to ſee whether his work be right, if he worketh on and never mind his Rule; What ſad work willl he make? But a Prudent Skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful workman will ſay, I will not truſt mine Eye too much, but I will look to my Rule, my Rule will not fail me; if there be bad work, it will diſcover it to me, that I may mend it before I go any further: Thus a diſcreet Workman will bring his Rule to his Work, and uſe his Line and Plummet that he may make it Workman like; He will ſay, if I let my Rule alone and not make uſe of it, but work as I pleaſe and truſt to mine Eye, no wonder if I make bad work, and what I build fall down again, and tumble about mine Ears.</p>
            <p>You to whom God hath given the Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard of Truth as a rule and meaſure to Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern your Thoughts, Words and Actions by: Let every thing be tryed with it before you Die and leave this World: If you do ſo and make this your daily practice; then ask your ſelves, and you will be able to tell your ſelves, and tell me, and ſay, I have now ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained more hopes of Gods Favour and a
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:65307:56"/> greater ſenſe of his Love, and goodneſs to me than ever I had before. The Apoſtle doth exhort us to <hi>Walk Circumſpectly not as Fools, but as Wiſe Redeeming the time.</hi> We have ſpent a great deal of time in vain; let us now be Wiſe, and Improve our time for our Eternal Advantage; let us walk Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumpectly, that is, look round about us, Conſider our ways, and try all our Thoughts Words and Actions, by the Standard of Truth; <hi>To Day</hi> (My Friends) <hi>while it is called to Day,</hi> hear the Voice of God, and <hi>harden not your Hearts,</hi> and receive that Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Counſel, that is tendered to you, that you may be <hi>partakers of the Inheritance,</hi> among the Saints in Light.</p>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>His Prayer after Sermon.</head>
               <p>BLeſſed and Eternal Father, Thou haſt brought forth thy Glorious Name, and Revealed thy Power, and thy Mighty Arm; and thou haſt cauſed a Remnant to bow, and Worſhip at thy Appearance: Thou art <hi>Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful, Thy Majeſty is Great,</hi> they that do behold thee, will with Reverence Worſhip be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee. Thy Power is gone forth, and hath reached the Hearts of thy People; Thou haſt humbled them, and ſubjected them to thy Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:65307:57"/> Almighty Power; that they might ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in the Earth to the Praiſe and Glory of thy great Name: And O Lord as thou haſt begun a great Work in the Earth, ſo thou haſt committed this Work to thy Servants, and Children, that bear thy Name among the Sons of Men; that they ſhould ſhew forth thy Right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, among the Inhabitants of the Earth; and our Souls have ſaid many a time, Who is ſufficient for theſe things? All our fitneſs and ſufficiency, our meetneſs and preparation is from thee: Do thou Reveal thy Power, and make <hi>bare thy Almighty Arm.</hi> We have found thy Preſence from day to day, and thou haſt upheld them that know thy Love. O Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous God of Life, herein we have encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to go on in the Work which thou haſt called us to; hereby we are enabled to Worſhip before thee, and to offer up living Praiſes unto thy great Name, for that Refreſhment and conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, which thou haſt Miniſtred unto thy People: And, O living Father, We have never waited on the in vain; whenſoever we have met together in thy Name, We have found thy Divine Preſence, and the opening of the Treaſures of thy Love; of thy Wiſdom, and of thy Favour to thy Children: So that from day to day, and even at this day, thou remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bereſt thy People, and thou giveſt them freſh
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:65307:57"/> occaſion to draw nigh to thee, and receive their daily nouriſhment and ſtrength from the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of thy Power: O living God of Life, gather up the Hearts of thy People more and more, and draw them into a nearneſs to thy ſelf; that their Underſtandings may be mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e and more opened to diſcern thy Will, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject themſelves to thy Wiſdom; that every Thought that is exalted againſt thy Divine Power, and living Voice in their own Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences may be brought down; that ſo all the Nations of the Earth may bow before thee; that ſo thy Truth may Reign, and thy Power may be exalted, and the Righteouſneſs which thou haſt Revealed, may ſhine forth more and more, in the Brightneſs and Glory of it; and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten thoſe that are afar off that they may be brought to ſeek after God. And <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng God of Life,</hi> let th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe that are bowed down under the Weight of Sin, be ſupported and raiſed up; and thoſe that are weary, and Heavy Laden, let them have reſt to their Souls. <hi>Powerful God of Life,</hi> keep thy People in a freſh and living Sence of thy love, and of thy Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Vertue, by which thou nouriſheſt thy Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and ſatisfieſt them from day to day; Not only when they are met together, but when they are ſeparated from one another: let thy People be preſerved from the Evil of
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:65307:58"/> the World, while they are in it, and let thy Wiſdom and Power give them Victory over it, that thou mayeſt have the Glory of all thy Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and Bleſſings, vouchſafed to them: For thou alone art worthy, who art God over all Bleſſed for Ever, and Ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="sermon">
            <head>Sermon V. The great Duty of Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring our Creatour. <hi>Preached at</hi> Devonſhire-Houſe, April, 6. 1692.</head>
            <p>THERE is only <hi>One Living and True God,</hi> Creatour of Heaven and Earth, whom we are obliged to ſerve and Worſhip; I have ſo much Charity as to believe, there are none among us but will own and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge this: And my Soul wiſheth that this Obligation did always reſt upon every
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:65307:58"/> ones mind, that they might <q>Remember their Creatour, that hath given us all Life and Breath; and continued all our bleſſings to us, that ſo every one might apply their Hearts unto that Univerſal Duty, that we are all convinced of.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>And they that are thus imployed, and exerciſed; they are conſidering, how, and after what manner they may quit and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge their Duty, and perform the Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation that lies upon them, ſo that it may be accepted at the hands of God; I ſpeak now of thoſe that are conſiderate, not of thoſe that go on in a Form of Religion, and matter not nor Regard whether they are accepted of God or no; but all that are Conſcientious towards God, they are deſirous to ſerve God, and Worſhip him, (ſo as they may be acceptable to him) ſo to perform duties that they may receive their reward, and that Encouragement, that God in all Ages, hath diſcovered and made manifeſt to be in his Purpoſe towards them that truly ſerve him.</q>
            </p>
            <p>When People come to this Conſideration how they may ſerve God aright, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him acceptably, the Lord is nigh unto them to inſtruct them, to teach them, and guide them in that way that is Everlaſting:
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:65307:59"/> And bleſſed be his Holy Name, a great many in our days have met with this Divine Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and Inſtruction; and are taught in this Age, as in former Ages, to Underſtand the Worſhip of God that he requires, that is in Spirit and Truth; and do find that the Father doth ſeek ſuch Worſhippers, and where he finds them, he rewards them: And they have an Anſwer of Peace in their Boſoms, and they are encouraged to go on in the Worſhip, and ſervice of God to the end of their days.</p>
            <p>And it is a great mercy, and benefit, a great bleſſing that God hath beſtowed upon a Remnant; ſo opened their Underſtandings to let them ſee, and know the way of being near to God, that ſo People may know whom they Worſhip; for you have Read, there have been Worſhipers that do worſhip they know not what: As our Saviour ſaid to the Woman of <hi>Samaria, You worſhip, you know not what:</hi> We know what we worſhip, ſo all that are taught of God do know which is the Firſt Leſſon of Chriſtianity, as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>He that cometh to God muſt firſt know and believe, That he is,</hi> That is, People muſt firſt be ſenſible, that there is a God, and that he is a Rewarder of them
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:65307:59"/> that diligently ſeek him, before they can rightly Worſhip him.</p>
            <p>Now for want of this knowledge, the World is ſcattered, and People are divided into a great many ſorts of Worſhips, and Faſhions, and ways of Religions, for want of the Knowledge of the true Worſhip, of the True and Living God; ſo that though Men are Univerſally Convinced, that there is a God; and that a worſhip is due to him from every one of us, yet People are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, ſcattered, and divided about the performance of their great Duty: And in the Day that the Lord hath viſited his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple he hath come to Anſwer this doubt, and Queſtion for them; it hath been the great Queſtion of the World, and is ſtill of many Thouſands: I know we ſhould Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God, but I know not the way and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner wherein to find acceptance; The Lord hath Anſwered that Queſtion in abundance, They that have Ears to hear, let them hear what the Spirit ſaith; there is a ſhort Anſwer to it all.</p>
            <p>Let People profeſs what Religion they will, there is no acceptance with God, but through Chriſt; ſo that if People come to be of this, and that, and the other Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and change their Religion never ſo often,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:65307:60"/> and go from one Religion to another: If they come not to Chriſt, they come not to him, in whom they may find acceptance; in him God is well pleaſed with every one, but out of him, he is pleaſed with never a one: The great Miſtery of Religion, it lies in Chriſt; People muſt come to God, by Faith in him; for without Faith it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to pleaſe God; let People perform never ſo much ſervice, and duties, all muſt paſs through the hands of the Mediatour, before ever their performance will reach un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, or before Peace and Comfort will reach to any Mans Soul. Therefore, it is the wiſeſt way for every one that would have acceptance with God to come to him, in the Name of the great Mediatour: Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple would be glad to have acceptance with God, and not to have their ſervices turned back upon them, as <hi>Cains</hi> was; every one that will have acceptance with God, muſt come this way, there is but one way.</p>
            <p>It is not the way that Men have invented, ſome by their Works and Merits; ſome by their made Faiths, and made Beliefs; and by divers Articles, and Principles, holding this Principle, and the other Principle; but our Lord and Creatour, he hath found out one way in his Infinite Wiſdom, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:65307:60"/> Mercy to Mankind, that was for ever loſt, and could never return to God by all his Sacrifices, Offerings, and perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances; he was never able to return into Unity with his Maker: If God had not found out a way; and the way that God hath found out, is by his Beloved Son Jeſus Chriſt; God ſpared not, He ſpared not What? <hi>He ſpared not his only begotten Son,</hi> Why, what did he do with him? <hi>He gave him for the Life of the World;</hi> in him that God gave, there is Life: It pleaſed the Lord that his Son ſhould have Life in him, as the Father had Life in himſelf; for Chriſt was with the Father, before the World began; in him was Life and the Life was the Light of Men. <hi>John,</hi> 11 4. It was no Created Life, that Life, that is in his Son is not a Created Life; but it is Eternal Life, and it was given for the Life of the World, and that Life is the Light of Men: <hi>This is the true Light, which lighteth every Man that cometh into the World;</hi> ſo that here is the Dignity of that Life which God hath beſtowed upon us; we are indued with that Life, which was with the Father through Jeſus Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the World was: Let us Conſider the Dignity of that Light, that we are lighted with.</p>
            <pb n="110" facs="tcp:65307:61"/>
            <p>The Queſtion is, whether we ſhould obey this Light or no: It is the Queſtion of every one; I am enlightned, ſaith a Man, ſhall I obey it or no? If I obey, I muſt take up a Croſs, and part with my beloved Luſt, and Corruption: No doubt of that, we muſt perſwade People to do that, before we can bring them to Heaven, and happineſs and Fellowſhip with God; it muſt not be by that way they loſt it, but by the contrary way, by which God will bring Men to Happineſs again: They loſt it by Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, and Sinning againſt God, by this way and means Men came out of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and Favour of God, by what way ſhall they obtain it again? Shall it be by committing Iniquity, and breaking Gods Law? No, here is the way that God hath found out to bring poor Man back again to himſelf; by the Suffering and Obedience of his Son Jeſus Chriſt: He hath given to him all Power in Heaven and Earth, that all ſhould be Subject to him; here is a Dignity which Chriſt hath obtained.</p>
            <p>It comes to the Queſtion with us whether we are inlightned, (Now we know we are Enlightned) God hath beſtowed ſomething upon us, that Wars and Fights againſt Sin and Iniquity: How came we by it? Is it
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:65307:61"/> any faculty in Nature? No Nature is Corrupted and Defiled; becauſe <hi>the Carnal mind is enmity againſt God, for it is not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the Law of God, neither indeed can be;</hi> yet there is ſomething in me that Anſwers the pure Law of God, that which makes me to hate things that are Reproveable; that is Light: How came I by it? It is not Natural, for then it would run Parallel with that Natural Inclination, that is in my Soul to lead me, further, and further from God. Theſe are ſet in oppoſition one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another, the Fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh and the Spirit; <hi>The Fleſh Luſteth againſt the Spirit, and the Spirit againſt the Fleſh.</hi> Here is part of an inward War, that you may be all ſenſible of. Now theſe two Warriors, the Fleſh and the Spirit make War one againſt another, and one of them is over come: It is true, there is ſuch a Principle in me that ſtrives againſt Sin, and Corruption; How came you by it? If you believe the Scriptures, I ſay, it is the Life of the Son of God, that lighteth every Man that cometh into the World. Now many that have rejected and deſpiſed the Light, I believe they did not think at the ſame time to mock, and make a ſcorn of the Life of Jeſus, though it was really ſo; but if People came to a true eſteem and
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:65307:62"/> value of that Light, that God hath planted in the Soul; they would give more reverence and reſpect to it: It is this that brings thoſe that Preach Chriſt, to Preach him in thoſe terms, and under thoſe Denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that he is nigh them.</p>
            <p>We do not doubt of Chriſts being born of a Virgin in the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and that he wrought Miracles; and Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed many Godly Sermons; and that he was Crucified, Dead and Buried, and Roſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain from the Dead, for theſe things are certainly true; we would have him our Saviour in this Age, we would have a nearer knowledge of him, and a ſenſe and feeling of the virtue of that Power by which he ſaved them that lived in former Ages: He is not a Chriſt and a Saviour of one Age only, but of all Ages to this Day, from <hi>Adam</hi> to the laſt Man that ſhall live upon the Earth: That Age and Generation that knoweth not Chriſt will not be ſaved by him; if there be any Age wherein he is not known: There is no other Name under Heaven by which you can be ſaved; if you ask where is this Saviour? <hi>Say not in thy Heart who ſhall Aſcend into Heaven, that is, to bring down Chriſt from above; or who ſhall Deſcend into the deep, that is,</hi>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:65307:62"/> (to bring up Chriſt again from the Dead?) <hi>The word is nigh thee, even in thy mouth; and in thy Heart; that is, the Word of Faith which we Preach.</hi> He is nigh thy Soul, he is the Lord of Life and a Quicken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Spirit: If I know that Quickening Spirit, after this I know the Lord Chriſt, when he comes to work in me by his Power changing my Heart, and tranſlating me from Death to Life; then I know the true Chriſt: God hath manifeſted in all Ages that it is the Duty of People to come to the knowledge of the Son of God, for he hath ſent forth his Spirit for to teach us, and to lead us into all truth.</p>
            <p>For when Chriſt was with his Diſciples he told them that he would pray the Father, and he ſhould ſend the Spirit the Comforter; and when he came he would be known by his Divine and Inward Teachings and Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, guiding and leading them into all Truth; that was his work to them: But what ſhall other Folks do? He will be made known to others too: When he comes <hi>He ſhall convince the World of Sin.</hi> So that his work to his Diſciples was, to lead them into all Truth; and his work to the Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld is, to convince the World of Sin. Who will deny but that there is a Spirit in our
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:65307:63"/> Age, as well as in other Ages that will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince men of Sin? Is this the Spirit of God that convinceth the World of Sin, or is it <hi>the Spirit of the QUAKERS only?</hi> When People come to conſider really and truly how they may ſerve God aright, they will find there is no ſerving God aright un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they come to Chriſt the Mediator, that in and by him they may put up ſuppplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to God, and through him they may expect at the hands of God Peace and comfort; and there is no other way, nor never will be.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jews</hi> they had another way, they had an outward way of ſerving God, this ſtood in divers Offerings, Sacrifices, Waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and Obſervations; this was a way of worſhip of Gods own inſtitution to that Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but what came of it? When the Apoſtle came to graſp it, he ſaid, <hi>The commers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto were not made perfect:</hi> What were the tranſgreſſors of it then? They that would ſin on, and continue in ſin; and not bring a Goat or a Ram or other Oblation; they that did obſerve it and came up to the point of the Law, they did bring their Offering when they were convinced of their Sin: If a man ſinned he was to bring a Hee Goat, and to bring it to the Door of the Tabernacle; but when he ſinned, the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:65307:63"/> of ſin, the guilt of ſin remained upon him. <hi>For it was impoſſible,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>that the Blood of Bulls and Goats ſhould take away the Sin: For if the Blood of Bulls and Goats, and the Aſhes of an Heifer ſprinkling the Unclean Sanctifieth to the Purifying of the Fleſh; how much more ſhall the Blood of Chriſt who through the Eternal Spirit Offered himſelf without ſpot to God, Purge your Conſciences from Dead works to ſerve the Living God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When there is no hope of attonement and reconciliation with God by all thoſe offerings under the Law, he tells you of one offering of the Son of God himſelf through the Eternal Spirit by which he became a a Propitiation; for thus will it do: If I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that Chriſt offered an Holy Offering to the Father for my ſins, I believe he offered his Body and that through the Eternal Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that he might be a propitiation for ſin, and take away ſin; and have Power over Sin and Death, and conquer Death and Darkneſs: the Apoſtle drives the matter far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, you muſt come to the inward Work of this outward Offering, this Eternal Offering that was in due time Offered to God; you muſt come to know the Operation of it by the ſprinkling of the Heart from an evil
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:65307:64"/> Conſcience, ſo that there was to be an Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catory Faith for the offering of that: The way to a Saviour was not made by Man, no more than the way of Salvation by Chriſt was found out by Man: No more than the Application of the benefits is effected by man.</p>
            <p>Where it pleaſeth God to call a People by his Grace, he calleth them to his Son, not by this and the other Form: <hi>No man cometh to me,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>except the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which hath ſent me draw him.</hi> The firſt thing that a Man or Woman comes to be aware of, is the ſecret ſenſe and feeling of the Lords Divine Power upon the Heart, to ſeek Chriſt Jeſus: As ſoon as they feel this and embrace it, this will be a Token of the Love of God; I hope all this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation will acknowledge that they have ſometimes felt his drawings, and that they have not embraced and cloſed with them ſo well as they ought.</p>
            <p>When the People are aware of theſe drawings Inwardly to Holineſs and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and are ſenſible that they ſhould with care and intention cloſe with them for the good of their Poor Souls; and that it concerns them to be happy in the other World, that World that is to come? and
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:65307:64"/> therefore reſolve to be led by theſe drawings of the Spirit of God; theſe are not weeds that grow in the Field Naturally: Theſe are ſparks of Divine Fire kindled in the Hearts of Men by God himſelf; No Man comes unto God, till God cometh to him and touches him, and gives him ſenſe and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; theſe are the motions and ſtirrings of Gods Holy Power in the hearts of many that are wicked and Abominable. Yet the Lord doth not deſpiſe the work of his own hands, but reacheth to ſuch.</p>
            <p>When the Lord meets with theſe that Deſpiſe not but highly Prize this wonderful Grace, and Cloſe with it, and are Glad of it; ſuch a one ſaith, I feared that the Lord had forgotten me, and had paſſed me by and had done with me; but I ſee he Viſits me again, and he hath Viſited my Soul this Day, inclining me to walk more anſwerably and ſuitably to his Love, he hath doubled his Power upon me and hath kindled a holy Fire in my Heart, and cauſed me to ſeek after him: He hath touched my Heart, and I will Pour out my Soul in Supplication, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he hath touched me: He will take hold of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e by his Power and he will keep me from being any more drawn away, I will live in the ſenſe of his Power and mercy
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:65307:65"/> that keeps me Night and Day, that I may encreaſe in it, and grow in Grace.</p>
            <p>When the Lord meets with ſuch a one he will draw him to the way that he hath appointed, <hi>none can come unto me, ſaith Chriſt, except the Father which hath ſent me draw him.</hi> If I am drawn, into what form ſhall I go now? And what Ordinance ſhall I take up now? This is all under Feet: This is none of my Work, I will come to Chriſt the Mediatour, and he will take the Government and Rule of me; It is not my beſt way to ſtudy for a form and an outſide Religion. I will wait upon that Power that hath thus touched my Heart, that he may by degrees bring me to the Obedience of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But ſome are ready to ſay, Who and What is this Chriſt Jeſus that you are ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of, that Immediate Chriſt Jeſus that is extant and preſent; that I am to have to be the Object of my Faith? That I may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in him, and come to Acquaintance of him; that I may partake of the Life of Chriſt Jeſus and have it Communicated to my Soul.</p>
            <p>It is true we have not a thought, or a word to ſpeak, that may Derogate from the wonderful Grace of Chriſt, who died in his
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:65307:65"/> perſon on Earth for the ſalvation of our Souls: Yet we muſt know that the Lord Jeſus Chriſt may be Spiritually preſent with us, and take the Government of us, and we are to be ſubject to him. How ſhall this be? I am ſpeaking of one that hath felt the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Drawings when he draws them to his Son, and draws them to ſomething that is Holy and Pure: This God the Father hath begotten; we read in Scripture; <hi>that God hath begotten Chriſt who is the only begotten of the Father.</hi> It is ſtrange, you will ſay, to ſpeak of begetting Chriſt again, God begets Chriſt again, that is, ſpiritually, he being the firſt born in many Brethren, in every true Believer, and there is a travel of Soul that Chriſt may be Formed in him.</p>
            <p>See what Travel of Soul the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> falls into the ſecond time, for the Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians: They were a brave People, they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiped God in the Spirit and believed in Chriſt Jeſus, and afterwards they came to be ſeduced by falſe Prophets, and falſe Teachers; that ſet them about their Works, and told them that they could not be Juſtified and ſaved without their own Works: Theſe falſe Teachers that came among them, were as bad as Popiſh Prieſts and Friers. It is not your Obedience to Chriſt, and the Spirit
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:65307:66"/> will ſave you, you muſt be doing: So theſe Poor People were deluded and bewitched, to give you the Apoſtles own Words, and ſo they were Infatuated, and <hi>drawn away from the Simplicity of the Goſpel,</hi> and they thought by the works of the Law to obtain Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The Apoſtle writes a Letter to them, and tells them that he <hi>traveled in birth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain till Chriſt was formed in them.</hi> If this was not Scripture it would look like a ſtrange work, there muſt be a forming of Chriſt, a Birth there muſt be, and a begetting; Who muſt beget in this and that moment? But the ſame that begat from the beginning, the ſame is the Father, he begets Chriſt in all that believe and obey the Goſpel. He is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting ſomething in me that is Holy, though I be unholy; the Father by the Operation of his Divine hand begets ſomething in me that is Holy: This I find though I am not ſo good as I ſhould be, I have that given me that will tell me, that the more I adhere and joyne my ſelf in my deſires and Affections to this good Principle, the more I ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the Quality of it; this good Principle, though it be like <hi>a little Grain of Muſtard-ſeed,</hi> I cannot tell what to compare it to for Littleneſs, in compariſon of the Great Lump and Maſs of Sin, Corruption and Filthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:65307:66"/> that Wars againſt it. This will Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread all that is bad and make me <hi>Holy,</hi> as that is Holy, Pure as that is Pure, and to have a Love to Him from whence it came, even to God and Chriſt. It will gather the Affections from Corruptible things, and place them upon things above.</p>
            <p>This Faith tells People that it is <hi>the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of things hoped for; and the evidence of things not ſeen,</hi> ſuch a one lives by Faith, ſuch a one that comes to be joyned to that, that is begotten of the Father: He lives by the Faith of the Son of God, and can do nothing of himſelf but through Chriſt that ſtrengthens him. They ſay unto God, I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive I can do nothing without thee, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not Pray unto thee, nor ſerve thee, of my ſelf I can do nothing acceptably, but through Chriſt the Mediator; ſuch a one becomes like a little Child, and he muſt be Led, and who muſt Lead him but the Spirit of Chriſt?</p>
            <p>You cannot Preach, ſaith one to him, unleſs you be moved by the Spirit: You cannot Pray till you be moved by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; How ſhould I? No, without him I can do nothing, I cannot Preach, nor Pray, nor do any thing Acceptable to God the Father but by Chriſt, and he hath Revealed him in me.</p>
            <pb n="122" facs="tcp:65307:67"/>
            <p>This is no new Doctrine, we ſee the new and Living way: It was an old way to old Chriſtians, and a new way to the new; and ſo a Thouſand Years hence, if the World laſt ſo long, Men will ſee that they cannot do any thing pleaſing to God, but as they are gathered into Chriſt, they will ſee their own Righteouſneſs, works and doings will avail them nothing at all. This is all laid at the feet of Jeſus whom God hath exalted to be a Prince and a Saviour, to be Lord and King.</p>
            <p>Now my Friends, we are engaged in this Age, abundantly engaged to offer thanks to God, through Jeſus Chriſt, that he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided and opened a way for the ſending forth the Spirit of his Son: And that God hath gathered a People, and hath made known to them the way of Life, that they might walk in it; but there is no walking in it but through a Daily Croſs, and ſelf-denial: It is not likely that a Man ſhould be brought back to God the ſame way that he went out from God, and the Prophets and Apoſtles do allude to this turning to God, <hi>When thou turneſt aſide to the right Hand or to the left, thou ſhalt hear a Voice behind thee ſaying, this is the way, walk in it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is a Voice that calls to People in
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:65307:67"/> our Days to look behind them, for they are out of the way: This Prophecy is fulfilled in our Days; we cannot turn away from the good ways of God, but we may hear a Voice behind us ſaying, thou art ſinning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, and breaking the Holy Law of God. Now if People return, it muſt be by the Croſs; I will not return to God, ſaith one, I have Pleaſure, Profit and Honour, and whatſoever my Heart can deſire in this evil way that I am walking in, if I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn I ſhall have nothing but ſhame and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, I ſhall be undone and ruined; and I ſhall loſe the Favour and Friendſhip of my Friends and Relations! I cannot return to God but through a Daily Croſs, and ſelf Denial; What then? It's likelier to be the right way, this bearing the Croſs.</p>
            <p>Chriſt tells us <hi>If any will come after me let him deny himſelf and take up his Croſs and follow Me.</hi> This Voice of Chriſt calls me to repent and turn from Sin, and giveth me a ſtrong Argument, that it is true, that it is the ſame way that will bring me back to God by the Mediator. It brings its own Evidence with it: We need no Argument to prove that it is a right way: It is a right way becauſe it is the <hi>narrow way.</hi> It is the right Gate, becauſe it is the <hi>ſtrait Gate:</hi>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:65307:68"/> Every body can walk in the broad way with eaſe, without any Croſs.</p>
            <p>When People are come thus far that they are convinced of their Duty, when they are called to amend their Lives and Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to forſake their Sins and turn to the Lord: This is the great Queſtion now; Have I Power to do this? This Queſtion hath ſtumbled a great many; when they have ſome beginning thoughts of turning to the Lord, and at laſt they have ſetled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in a belief that they cannot do it; it is true, and nothing truer, that Men Convinced of their Sins, have not Power to leave their Sins of themſelves: This is true, but not all the Truth; to Men that God convinceth of Sin, He gives them Power to be made willing to forſake their Sins. He hath given Power to all that <hi>are in Chriſt Jeſus to believe and become the Sons of God; then they have denied ungodlineſs and Worldly Luſts:</hi> If they be the Sons of God, and <hi>live. Righteouſly, Soberly and Godly, in the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what ſhall they do that are ſenſible they have not Power to forſake their Sin, till God is pleaſed to give them Power? Such have nothing to do but to wait upon the Lord, for the giving of this Power, and
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:65307:68"/> then I have a Duty Incumbent to me to Anſwer this Power. The Apoſtle upon this ſubject tells us what People are to do for their own Converſion: He aſcribes the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Converſion to Chriſt Jeſus. The Prophets and Apoſtles they tell us, there is ſomething for Man to do, that is, if he hath not Power, he is to be willing to receive it. The Apoſtle hath a notable Expreſſion to this purpoſe: He puts them in mind, how they uſed to do by the Devil, when they were the Devils ſervants, they did obey his Commands and yielded their Members ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to Unrighteouſneſs; How did they yeild? They did it Heartily with pleaſure and delight; thus you did when you did not know the Power of God, but now you are come to the knowledge of the Power of God. <hi>Yield not your Members as Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of unrighteouſneſs unto Sin, but yield your ſelves unto God, as thoſe that are alive from the dead, and your Members as Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Righteouſneſs unto God.</hi> Rom. 6.13. Let your Minds and wills and Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, be joyned to that Power which God Viſited you with; in Love to God, give up your Members as Servants unto Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>Here is ſomething for Man to do in the
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:65307:69"/> Day of Gods Viſitation; <hi>Thy People ſhall be willing in the Day of thy Power,</hi> That they may come to that, and experience that; this ſhews that they are the People of God: But they that are not a willing People, are none of Gods People; but Gods People are ſo: And I pray God make you all ſo, to be a People willing to be Gods People, when he gives you Power, and it will not be long before he gives you Power to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake your Sins, to forſake this, and the other Fooliſh Proud and vain Action, and faſhion; he hath made Chriſt Jeſus to be Lord and King, and he ſhall Reign over Death, he hath made all things by Chriſt; and he is become the Saviour of all Men, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of them that believe; ſo that I would have a ſpecial Salvation, and thou wouldeſt have it too; Chriſt hath made a way, and opened a door for us to be ſaved, that we might have an abundant entrance into his Everlaſting Kingdom. But I would have a ſpecial Salvation, that will inveſt me with the Love of God in my Heart before I die. It is to be had only through Chriſt, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to him will I come; to him muſt every one come, and every Knee bow to his Name, and every one muſt wait to his appearing in the Spirit. When Chriſt appears, Truth
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:65307:69"/> ſtirs: Now if a Holy Divine Life is in thee, it is He; if a Principle of Truth ſtir in thee, it is He: The ſame Jeſus, only in a ſmaller Manifeſtation; He that is Faithful in a little, He will make him Ruler over much. This is he that God hath ordained to be the Captain of our Salvation; this is that which we Preach in his Name, and teſtifie and declare to all People, that there is no other Saviour: No deliverance from Death and Hell, but by, and through him; <hi>In him there is Reconciliation, and that Peace, which paſſeth all Underſtanding;</hi> and Power over all thoſe things, which have Captivated us; and made us diſobey our great Lord and Maker: Let us wait for the coming of Chriſt. <hi>He is our King, our Lord and Lawgiver, and he will ſave us:</hi> This was the cry of his People of Old, for the glorious and great Salvation he hath given, and the Work he hath wrought. Let the Prayers and Supplications of all People that deſire Salvation, be put up more and more; that he will viſit the Earth, and give Power from above, and bring us into that New and Living Way, which he hath conſecrated for us, through the Vail; that is to ſay, his Fleſh; to whom be Glory for Ever, and Ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:65307:70"/>
               <head>His Prayer after Sermon.</head>
               <p>BLeſſed and Eternal Father, thou haſt brought forth thy Glorious Name; and revealed thy Powerful and mighty Arm: Thou haſt cauſed a Remnant to bow and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip at thy appearance; thou art wonderful O Lord, thy Majeſty is great, and they that behold thy Glorious appearance will bow, and with humble Reverence Worſhip before thee: Thy Power is gone forth, and hath reached the Hearts of thy People; thou haſt humbled them, and ſubjected them to thy Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Almighty Power, that they might ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in the Earth; to the Praiſe and Glory of thy great Name. And O Lord as thou haſt begun a great Work in the Earth, ſo thou haſt committed this great Work to thy Servants, and Children that bear thy Name among the Sons of Men; that they ſhould ſhew forth thy Righteouſneſs among the Inhabitants of the Earth: And our Souls have ſaid many times, who is fit and ſufficient for theſe things? All our ſufficiency and Preparation is from thee; do thou make bare thine Arm, and Reveal and make known thy Power: We have found thy Preſence with us, from day to day, and thou haſt upheld them that know thy
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:65307:70"/> Love. O Glorious God of Life, herein we have Encouragement to go on, in the work that thou haſt called us to: Hereby we are enabled to Worſhip before thee, and to offer up Living Praiſes to thy great Name, for that Conſolation; that thou haſt Miniſtred unto thy People. And O living Father, we have never waited upon on thee in Vain; when ever we have met together in thy Name, we have found thy Divine preſence, and the opening of the Treaſures of thy Love, of thy Wiſdom, and of thy Favour unto thy Children; ſo that from day to day, and even at this day thou remembreſt thy People, and giveſt them freſh occaſions to draw nigh to thee; and to receive their daily nouriſhment, and ſtrength from the Operation of thy Power. O living God of Life, gather up the Hearts of thy People more and more unto thy ſelf, and draw them into a nearneſs to thy ſelf; that their Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings may be more opened, to diſcern thy will, and ſubject themſelves to thy Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: that every thought that is exalted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy Divine Power, and living Voice in their own Conſciences, may be brought down; That ſo all the Nations of the Earth may bow before thee, that ſo thy truth may Reign, and thy Power may be exalted, and the Righteouſneſs which thou haſt revealed,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:65307:71"/> may ſhine out more and more, in the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and glory of it; and inlighten thoſe that are afar off, that they may be brought to ſeek after thee. And O thou living God of life, and power, let thoſe that are bowed down under the weight of Sin, be ſupported and raiſed up: And let thoſe that are weary and heavy laden, have reſt to their Souls. Powerful God of life, keep thy People in the freſh and living ſenſe of thy love; and of thy Heavenly Vertue, by which thou nouriſheſt thy Children, and ſatisfieſt them from Day to Day, not only when they are met together, but when they are ſeparated from one another; let thy People be preſerved from the World, while they are in it, and let thy Wiſdom and Power give them Victory over it: That thou mayeſt have the Glory of all thy Mercies, and Bleſſings vouchſafed to them, for thou alone art worthy, who art God over all Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for Ever, and Ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="sermon">
            <pb n="131" facs="tcp:65307:71"/>
            <head>Sermon VI. The Divine Monitor: OR, Light from Heaven. <hi>Preached at</hi> Grace-Church-Street. June, 19. 1692.</head>
            <p>IT is a great Priviledge to the Sons and Daughters of Men; that it hath pleaſed God Almighty to open a way, how they may come to the true Knowledge of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: And O that there was a Heart in every one of us that could rightly prize this Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge, as they ought to do: for in the Knowledge of the true God, conſiſts our true Happineſs; and without this, the mind of no Man or Woman can be be good: there is nothing ſeaſons the mind and Soul of Man, and prepares, and fits it for an everlaſting well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>being;
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:65307:72"/> but the Divine Knowledge of the living God that made him: And there is a Propenſity in the Soul of Man, even ſince the Fall, to return again to God; and to have that acquaintance, and Communion with the Lord that Man had before he fell; and they that have regard to that inward ſpark of Divine Love, that they find in their own Souls towards God, they will experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence that the Lord is merciful and Gracious, and Propitious to that which is of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
            <p>For though the Soul is loſt, and Man is loſt through transgreſſion, and a great Alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is happened between him and his Maker; yet the Mercy of the Lord endureth for ever. And his kindneſs and favour to loſt Man is ſuch, that he ſtretcheth out his hand all the day long; and preſents, and offers to the Children of Men, a Friendſhip and Acquaintance, and a Communion again with him; and though by Sin and Tranſgreſſion there is a rebellous Nature grown up in the Sons and Daughters of Men; yet the Soul of Man is not wholly ſo, there is ſomething that ſtrives and labours in a contrary way, and perſuades the Soul to turn again unto the Lord, and to wait for the knowledge of God, and whoſoever hearkens with care and
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:65307:72"/> diligence to that Divine Monitor that is daily drawing and perſuading People to ſeek af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter God, they come to underſtand that the Lord is not ſo Angry with Mankind, but his Love and Mercy and Good-will reaches towards all the Sons and Daughters of Men; and the Bar that hinders their Communion with God, and Peace with God; it is not in the Lord, but it is in themſelves; and therefore the remedy muſt be wrought in themſelves.</p>
            <p>This is evident to every Eye, that there is ſomething gotten into Mankind, which the Holy God cannot own, and can never have fellowſhip with: That is, another con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Spirit hath wrought upon the Souls of People; and hath ſeduced and drawn them out to that which is unholy and contrary to God, and the terms of Gods Covenant with Mankind; which is, that he ſhould forſake that which the contrary Spirit hath wrought: <hi>Let the wicked forſake his way, and the unrighteous Man his thoughts.</hi> Why ſhould he forſake his ways? Becauſe the Lord never led him to thoſe ways: He that made him never led him into them, but the Devil the Enemy of Mankind ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced him into thoſe ways; therefore the Creatour cries out to him; <hi>Let the wicked
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:65307:73"/> forſake his Ways and the unrighteous Man his Thoughts.</hi> I cannot have union with him as long as he walks in his evil ways, I cannot dwell in his mind ſo long as evil thoughts are in it; ſo may the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of the works which the Devil hath wrought, that Man is carryed away from God by his evil thoughts, and the works of the Devil.</p>
            <p>Why doth not God deſtroy thoſe works when he is Almighty and able to do it? Very true, God is ſo; but he hath offered to Mankind through the Son of his Love a way and means, how Man may come to be purged and cleanſed, from the evil that the Devil hath wrought in him; and how he may come to be reconciled to God: God hath not choſen the way of Coertion and Force, and to work altogether by irreſiſtible Power, that Man ſhall go to Heaven whether he will or no; there was no force uſed for his going to Hell and Darkneſs, but it was the choice of his Will: The Devil could not have forced Man and Led him away out of Covenant with God, he could nor compel him to break the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Command of God, but the Devil tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, and he yielded to the Temptation, and now Man is driven out of the preſence
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:65307:73"/> of God; yet God hath found out a way for the Sons and Daughters of Men to return again to him; what, by Force and Coertion and Irreſiſtible Power? No, but the Scripture ſaith, he hath offered Faith and Salvation to all Men: He hath freely given the Son of his Love out of his own boſom, who making himſelf an Offering for ſin, hath preſented a way and means for Mans returning again to God.</p>
            <p>How doth God preſent Chriſt to us? he preſents him to the view of every ones mind, to the underſtanding of every Soul. He Offers and preſents him for Salvation to the ends of the Earth. There is Damnation come in by Man's being ſubject to Satan: But Salvation comes in by his being ſubj ct to Chriſt; as Damnation came in by his being defiled; ſo Salvation came in by his being cleanſed: As the Devil is the Defiler, ſo Chriſt is the Cleanſer, and Man is the object upon which both do work; and they that have been defiled and corrupted (as we all have) by the unclean Spirit: Can any of us give a reaſon why we ſhould not be cleanſed by the holy Spirit: we have loſt our Right to Heaven by Sin and Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion in the firſt <hi>Adam:</hi> And can any give a reaſon why we ſhould not be Reſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:65307:74"/> and Redeemed by Jeſus Chriſt the ſecond <hi>Adam?</hi> No reaſon can be given of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, but that God is free in his Love, and Chriſt in his Offering: <hi>He hath Offered himſelf a Sacrifice for Sin:</hi> Every Prieſt hath ſomething to Offer. This Man, the Man Chriſt Jeſus offered himſelf through the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Spirit, a Sacrifice for Sin: And now the Sacrifice is Offered, and a Door is opened, and a new and living way conſecrat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed through the Vail, that is to ſay his Fleſh,</p>
            <p>Now who can be wiſe enough to find out a reaſon why all men enter not in at this Door? for all Men Run in at the other Door which the Devil and <hi>Adam</hi> opened to run from God; all could run in at that Door; what is the reaſon that all run not in at that Door which Chriſt hath opened and God hath Revealed, and which coſt Chriſt ſo dear to work our way back again for Mankind to return to God? If we go about to enquire into the reaſon we ſhall find it very little; for there is all the reaſon in the World we ſhould ſerve God, and ſeek our own Happineſs. There is all the reaſon in the World we ſhould part with Sin and Iniquity, and with the Devils Work which he wrought if we knew but how: now this I ſay is a great Priviledge that God hath
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:65307:74"/> afforded to the Sons and Daughters of Men, that they may know; for here is the terms of the Goſpel and of Salvation brought to a narrow compaſs, to a ſhort ſum, there needs no Catalogue of them, they that will be ruled by the Wicked one muſt have their part with him, and they that will be ruled and Governed by the Holy one, ſhall have their part with him, that where he is, there they may be alſo.</p>
            <p>Is this in the Power of Man's? Will no, there lies the miſchief in the will of Man, for you cannot but know by Experience, if a Man may have his own will, he will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies run headlong to Deſtruction, and run in the way of Wickedneſs: And if ever he comes to turn out of that way into the way of Righteouſneſs, he muſt do it in a way that is Croſs to his own will. Some have ſaid becauſe we have ſpoken of the Free Grace of God in a way that is univerſal, of his kindneſs to Mankind through Jeſus Chriſt, they have ſaid that we hold Free Will, that Men might be ſaved if they would; but alas! We have tried it, and we have an Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Knowledg that is able to convince us and all the World, that it is far enough from our own will: Man is far enough from being able to ſave himſelf, from being ſaved by his
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:65307:75"/> own will, he can run on to Damnation, there is a Current goes with his Affections, and with his Corrupt deſires, they go with the Current and Stream: As long as a Man goes on in Sin he Swims down the Stream.</p>
            <p>Now many after they have long gone on in Sin, and their evil ways, they think of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to God, for they think there is a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter way, and a ſurer way, and a ſafer way for their Souls, than to go on in wickedneſs; ſo there is; if there be ſo, ſaith the ſincere Soul, O that I might walk in it, Why doſt thou not? I am convinced that I ſee a more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent way than my way is, a better walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Converſation than my Life is, but Alas! It is too hard for me to walk in it. Why? What is the matter? What makes it hard? Becauſe of my own will, I cannot walk in it and have my will, I cannot walk in it and enjoy my Affections and Deſires, and my Intereſt in the World. This is no wonder that thou telleſt me; now thou art Convinced of a better way, and wouldſt walk in it, and thou canſt not walk in it but thou muſt take up a Daily Croſs; we might all of us tell that, and read it before. I pray God you may come to read it within, what a Croſs it is you are to take up, and what a way it is you are required to walk
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:65307:75"/> in, that it is the way o God, the way that leads to Heaven, it is a Narrow way; the way that the Devil would have you to walk in is a Broad way, there is no Rub in it.</p>
            <p>O! Would you but once come to Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience how hard it is to walk in <hi>that way that leads to Life;</hi> you will find that you cannot do it without ſelf denial. It comes to this point, I read of it before, but now I find it ſo; ſuch a Man, or ſuch a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man will ſeriouſly apply themſelves to live blameleſs, harmleſs and Inoffenſive towards God and Man, they will ſet a Bridle and a watch before their mouth, that they might not ſpeak a vain Word, they will take care of the frame and Temper of their Minds, that they Sin not in their Thoughts; that they Sin not with their Lips, nor with their hands: This is not as I was wont to do, I was uſed to have my liberty, now I find my ſelf yoked, I dare not Sin againſt God. Now I find by experience what I heard before that no Man can follow Chriſt, without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying himſelf and taking up a Daily Croſs.</p>
            <p>I would have you experienced in this work; wicked Men think it is a pleaſant Life to follow the Devils work and to walk <hi>in the Broad way;</hi> but the way of ſelf-deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:65307:76"/> is uneaſie, there is much ſtrife and oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition in that way; If I have a mind to ſpeak a Vain word I am Limitted, if I have a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to wrong my Neighbour and cheat and defraud him, I am Limitted; I am not to do it, that belongs to the Broad way; if a Man will ſeek after the Lord, and walk in the way of Holineſs and Righteouſneſs, the end where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is Peace, he will find it is a Narrow way wherein he cannot enjoy his own will; ſuch a one muſt be a <hi>David,</hi> who ſaid, I behaved my ſelf as a weaned Child; that is, as one that is affraid to be Beaten.</p>
            <p>But thou wilt be ready to ſay, I am a Man, and not a Child, I am come now to be a Man; a Man of Parts, I have ſeen much and read much, and would you have me become a Child? What a great Man was <hi>David?</hi> If you ſpeak of a Man, he was a Man of Dignity and Honour, a Man of Valour and Experience; yet when he ſpeaks with reſpect to the frame of his mind before the Lord, he ſaith, he behaved himſelf <hi>as a weaned Child;</hi> as one that feared to be bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, feared to commit an Offence: He fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Rod of his God upon him, he feared Judgment would come upon him, he feared ſomething of Judgment upon his Conſcience. <hi>David</hi> was an Old Teſtament Man, but he
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:65307:76"/> had regard to that which never waxeth old, but is the ſame in all times new and old, Alpha and Omega. Chriſt Jeſus was his leader be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was born of the <hi>Virgin Mary;</hi> his Word was a Light to his Feet, and a Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorn to his Paths. <hi>David</hi> had Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with God, who did lift up the Light of his Countenance upon him.</p>
            <p>And when Chriſt himſelf came to Preach upon Earth, he ſaith himſelf: <hi>Every one that comes into the Kingdom of God, muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a little Child.</hi> He muſt become as a little Child in Simplicity and Subjection, he muſt be under Government; he muſt become like a little Child, or he muſt in no wiſe enter the Kingdom of Heaven. They muſt not think to enter into Chriſts Kingdom be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are Men, Men of Parts, Men of Courage, Men of Underſtanding; Learned Doctors, that are Maſters of Liberal Arts and Sciences. Theſe may help to make them Men, but they muſt be Children, all their Wit and Parts, and Manhood, Courage and Valour will do them no good; for little Children, Babes and Sucklings may under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand more than they of Divine Miſteries, and have greater Communion and Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe between God and their ſouls than they, ſo that whoſoever enters into Chriſts
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:65307:77"/> Kingdom muſt become like little Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
            <p>So that here is a way provided by Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt for Man to come again into the favour of God; which is by Chriſt alone, not by any thing that a Man can do, Chriſt muſt be their leader and their Counſellour, he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone can give them the true knowledg of God. <hi>No Man can know the Father but the Son, and him to whom the Son reveals him.</hi> Men can never attain to the ſaving knowledg of God by ſtudy, and by Diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and reading Books, and Commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and Obſervators of matters of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Time would fail me to ſpeak of the multitude of Books that have been written about the Knowledg of God: You muſt come to Chriſt for Divine Knowledg; Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy, the Knowledg of God, and Divine and Heavenly things is from Chriſt; he ſhall have this Divine Knowledg, be he never ſo ſimple that comes unto Chiſt for it, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have it any other way, for God hath ordained this way; ſaith God, he ſhall have it of my Son, who is the Reconciler, the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour between God and Man, he ſhall be beholding to Chriſt for all. All Mens own works and labours will not Juſtify and ſave them, for God hath Committed the whole
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:65307:77"/> work of Salvation to Chriſt: One would think it ſhould be no great matter for Men to lay aſide their own works and Duties, and ſubmit to Chriſt; but I tell you it is very hard, and I found it hard my ſelf.</p>
            <p>Men think by reading and Learning and hearing this and the other Mans Notions and Opinions they may be edified and proffited, and come to the true knowledg of God; but while they are waiting upon God in the way he hath appointed, they may receive knowledg from Chriſt and be more certain and Infallible in what they do know, than by conſulting all the wiſe Men, and learned Doctors in the World: For no Man knows all at once, and no Man knows all things neither; it is not a thing neceſſary that a Man ſhould know all things in relation to God, for as he is in himſelf he is incomprehenſible. <hi>For no Man knows the Father but the Son, and he to whom the Son ſhall Reveal him.</hi> Yet that which he knows of God he may know it as certain and Infallible.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe a Man know nothing of God, but that he is <hi>the ſearcher of Hearts and the trier of the Reins:</hi> There are many have read this, and ſay they know it; that yet doubt whether there be a God or no: But when God comes within them and convinceth
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:65307:78"/> them of Sin, and ſearcheth them, and brings Judgment upon them for what they have done; then they know Infallibly that God is <hi>the ſearcher of Hearts.</hi> This is not Mans work, this is the work of God; if I find God doth approach my Spirit, I know it is Gods work, I have now got ſome knowledg of God, how came I by it? who gave it me? No body but he that hath all Knowledg, he that was with the Father from the beginning; and was Glorified with the Father before the World began, he gave me this Knowledg; and how did he give it thee? By this Spirit, <hi>for he hath ſent forth the Spirit of his Son into my Heart,</hi> and that Spirit of Chriſt ſearches the Heart, and tryes the Reins: He tells me this is Evil that thou haſt done, this is that which God that made thee hath againſt thee, this thou muſt forſake, and this thou muſt Repent of, here I have an Infallibility of what I know, but I cannot get Rid of my Evil.</p>
            <p>Now if I can believe in that Power by which my Heart is ſearch'd, and truſt in him that hath begun to deal with me, then his work is not only to Reveal his Light to convince me, but to put forth his Power to convert me, ſo that by the Power of that truth by which my Heart is ſearch'd, I come to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted and turned from my Sin, and break
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:65307:78"/> off from it; and when I am broken off from it I am ſure, and have a certainty that it is ſo, that I am broken off from ſuch a Sin, and that my Heart is turned againſt it; I am ſure that now I hate it, and deteſt it, and that God hath turned my Inclination another way. I am ſure this is Gods work, I can witneſs this Infallibly that ſomething is now done in order to my Redemption: But there is ſomething yet Remaining to be done, What then? I will go ſtep by ſtep, by fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing my Guide. I ſhall be ſure to be make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome progreſs every Day to that ſtate to which the Spirit of Chriſt will lead me. Theſe Perſons come to a certain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y of knowledg by their own Experince.</p>
            <p>Some will ſay, take heed of being deluded and decieved by the <hi>Quakers,</hi> ſo ſay I too; Take heed of being deluded by any body, if any go about to perſwade thee to believe that which thou knoweſt to be a Lie, I am ſure they are about to delude thee, I would have every one to have an evidence in themſelves of what they believe.</p>
            <p>Doth a Man believe ſuch a One is a Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard, becauſe the Scripture declareth Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt the Drunkards; the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Wo to the drunkards of</hi> Ephraim? There are Judgments denounced againſt Drunkards
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:65307:79"/> in the Old Teſtament; conſider the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doth not tell ſuch and ſuch by Name that they are Drunkards; but the Spirit of God by a Work and Operation upon a mans Conſcience ſingles him out and charges him with the guilt of Drunkenneſs.</p>
            <p>There is great condemnation pronounced againſt Whoremongers in Scripture, but it doth not tell ſuch who they are by Name, but their Conſciences find them ſo, and give infallible judgment againſt them, and ſaith, <hi>Thou art the Man,</hi> thou art a perſon that God doth Judge and Condemn; <hi>Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers and Adulterers God will Judge;</hi> but that doth not concern thee, and affect thee, except thou be one; I may read this an hundred times in Scripture, and not have a reflection in my own Conſcience, except I be guilty: But when God meets with a guilty perſon and Judgeth and Condemneth him, there will be an infallibility in what ſuch a one knows. If a Whoremonger is reflected upon by his own Conſcience, if his Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence tell him he is the Man; if all the World ſhould flatter him and ſay he is not guilty, he would certainly know that they tell him a Lie.</p>
            <p>So that here is no Dependance upon any mans judgment, but upon an inviſible Judge
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:65307:79"/> in a mans own Heart; Who ſhall delude and deceive this Man; that hath this expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimental knowledg? Thoſe perſons will not deceive a Man that would turn him from the evil of his ways, theſe do not go about to deceive him that will tell him he muſt hearken to that Principle of Truth and Holineſs in his own Heart; they would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him that tell him he is converted when he is not, and leave him there: But when he is really converted and turned from Sin to God, ſome will tell him he is deluded and deceived; I pray God every one of us may be ſo deceived; ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>We are Deceivers, yet True.</hi> All that are truly converted, though Men cry out they are deceivers, though they are deceivers yet true; they are come to the ſavour of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of God through Chriſt, and ſo they ſhall certainly <hi>Come to be partakers of the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance that is undefiled, and that fadeth not away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Friends you know that this hath been the Propoſition of all the Prophets and Apoſtles from the beginning to this Day; the thing that they have propoſed to the Sons and Daughters of Men, hath been to enquire after the knowledg of the true God: It hath been wonderful to conſider what the
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:65307:80"/> Devil hath done to preſent divers Doctrines that he hath found out, and ſtirred up o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to invent a Company of Gods that other People have Adored and Worſhipped. It is hard to find any Nation that do not Worſhip ſome God: It is Natural for Man to deſire to come to ſome God, he thinks he muſt come to ſome God; and cannot be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py if he come not to God: But the Devil hath invented ſo many Gods and ſet Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple a Worſhipping of Idols, the Work of Mens hands; ſuch Gods that are ſo far from helping their Worſhippers, that they cannot help themſelves; they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not wipe off the Duſt from their own Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: And if they fall down they cannot riſe again.</p>
            <p>But this is not our caſe, we have but one God Preached among us, and but one Lord Jeſus Chriſt the Mediatour between God and Man: Our condition is happy in having but one God, in compariſon of theirs that have many Gods.</p>
            <p>If the true God that you Worſhip were but truſted in, you would be the happieſt People in the World. If you do but ſearch, you will find that the Devil hath in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and in this Age, ſtirred up People to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip as many Gods, as he did in other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:65307:80"/> in Antient times, among the <hi>Sidonians,</hi> the <hi>Amorites</hi> and others.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, we Worſhip one God, and truſt only in one God, and one Chriſt, and one Holy Ghoſt, the only living and true God.</p>
            <p>Do not tell me what God a Man profeſſeth to worſhip, but what God he truſteth in, that gives it the Name: Whatſoever a Man truſteth in, that he makes his God; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be Gold and Silver, or the Honours and pleaſures of this World; if he truſteth in theſe things he maketh them his God. Let a Man but ſearch and try himſelf, and he will find ſomething hath got a place in his Heart, that he cannot part with for Chriſts ſake: He will be ready to ſay, I cannot part with my Houſe and Land, with my Wife and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and my Goods and Poſſeſſions, becauſe I have a Confidence in them, and believe they will do me good, and be a Defence for me: I may truſt in times of Peril that theſe things may do me good then. Here is a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Adoration, here is that truſt, that Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that all true Chriſtians ought to have in the true God. And this is placed in theſe Earthly things; now whereſoever the truſt and Confidence is placed in Tranſitory and Earthly periſhing things, theſe Men truſt in tranſitory Gods.</p>
            <pb n="150" facs="tcp:65307:81"/>
            <p>Nothing ſo ſhewes that a Man makes the Lord his God, as when he caſts all his care on him, and puts his whole truſt in him, when he makes a profeſſion and acknowledgment of his dominion and greatneſs, and of all his other Perfections, that by his Wiſdom he can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure for them all that is good, and by his Power put off from them, and ſecure them from Evil. When I make the Lord my truſt and refuge, and truſt him for my God, I chuſe him before all the Gods of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, and truſt in him, above all things un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Heaven, upon the Account of the profun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity of his Wiſdom, and the Almightineſs of his Power; when a Man hath this ſenſe upon him, he will walk before the Lord with Reſignation of Mind, and be willing to be at Gods diſpoſal, and he will not only give up himſelf to God, but he will hearken to him, hear his Voice when he ſpeaks to him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>God who at ſundry times and in divers manners ſpake in times paſt, unto the Fathers by the Prophets, hath in theſe laſt Days ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to us by his Son.</hi> But, Where is his Son, you will ſay? He is in Heaven; but though he is <hi>the High and Lofty one that inhabits E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, yet he dwells with meek, humble and contrite Hearts, that tremble at his word.</hi> If
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:65307:81" rendition="simple:additions"/> I be one of the number of thoſe that tremble at Gods word, I have Gods promiſe that he will come Home to me, and dwell with me: It is well for thee if the over-ruling Power of God hath prevailed upon thee, that thou canſt be willing to be at Gods Diſpoſal, and ſay, Lord, What wouldſt thou have me to do?</p>
            <p>Therefore Friends I would adviſe you all, in Love to your Souls, that when God deſires your Hearts, that you would give them up to him, that there he may delight to dwell, and have his habitation: Hearken to Gods Voice; and have regard to his word, which is a more ſure word than any Mans in the World: <hi>There is a more ſure word of Prophecy,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>unto which you will do well to take heed.</hi> This will check you and reprove you when you do Evil, and ſhew you where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you have Tranſgreſſed, and will encourage you, and be a Comfort to you when you do that which is good. This will <hi>make you wiſe to Salvation, and throughly furniſh you and give you underſtanding for every good work.</hi> This word will tell you, this you muſt not do leſt you offend God, and wound your Conſcience, and grieve the Holy Spirit; this word will help you ſo to ſpeak as to Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter Grace to the hearers; ſuch a one as
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:65307:82"/> hath regard to this word, hath a Chaplain in his own Boſome: That will direct and teach him how to ſtear his courſe, and order his Converſation among Men, and how <hi>to ſerve God acceptably:</hi> This <hi>High Prieſts Lips will preſerve knowledg,</hi> even Jeſus Chriſt, The Righteous, who ſpeaks to us in his Word; we can do nothing but by his Direction: If you come to him to lead to you into all truth, he will bring you the Father, reconcile you to him, that you may obtain his Favour and Everlaſting Life; when one of Chriſts Diſciples ſaid; <hi>Shew us the Father, and it ſufficeth us;</hi> Jeſus ſaith unto him; <hi>He that hath ſeen me, hath ſeen the Father: And, How ſayeſt thou then, ſhew us the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</hi> If you ſubject your ſelves to Chriſt, and to the Government of his Spirit, he will bring you to that Life and Immortality that <hi>fadeth not away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This hath been our Labour and Travel from time to time, to Preach Chriſt among you, and not to Preach our ſelves, and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Church for our ſelves; but to gather a People in to Chriſt, who is Lord of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth: We would Preach Chriſt Jeſus the Lord, we would not have you Admire Mens words and ſayings, and charge your Memory with them: But we would
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:65307:82"/> have you remember the words and ſayings of Chriſt; who is the great Mediatour to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile Man again to God, that you may know him by his Power working effectually in your hearts; we Labour for nothing elſe, and we want nothing elſe. <hi>We are Ambaſſadors for Chriſt, as though God did beſeech you by us: We pray you in Chriſts ſtead be ye Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to God:</hi> That you may ſo Live, that <hi>whether you Eat and Drink, or whatſoever you do, you may do all to the Glory of God;</hi> your great Creatour, that hath given his Son to Die for you, and <hi>Redeem you from all Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that you might be a peculiar People zealous of all good Works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore let God have all the Honour and Glory, for all his mercies and Bleſſings; Let us render to him Hearty Praiſes and Thankſgivings, for his wonderful Love, and ackowledg that it is a great priviledg that we may obtain by Jeſus Chriſt, even to be brought again to the true knowledg of the living God, which we loſt by our Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>His Prayer after Sermon.</head>
               <p>GLorious art thou in thy Appearances O Lord, and very wonderful is thy Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and thy ways paſt finding out: And in
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:65307:83"/> this thy glorious Day, thou art opening a way for the Sons and Daughters of Men to return to thee: And O Lord thoſe whoſe Eyes thou haſt opened rejoyce, and are Glad, becauſe they have ſeen the way of thy Salvations and the breathings of their Souls are, that their Feet may be kept therein, and that they may make ſtraight ſteps in their way to thy kingdom: And O Lord we are ſenſible that our ſtrength, and our Power, and our Ability is only in thee; and therefore are the Souls of thy Children bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſubjected to thee: Waiting for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing of thy Power, that as our Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are renewed from Day to Day, that thou wouldeſt make known thy Power in us, that we may feel the ſtretching forth of thy hand to ſave thy little Ones, out of the hands of the Deſtroyer. And ſo Powerful God of life, break forth more and more in thy Glory, and make known thy Power, in expelling the Clouds of darkneſs and ignorance; and bring the Minds and Underſtandings of thy People, to know thee more and more, till they come to the bleſſed Inheritance among the Saints in Light; Holy and Powerful Father break in upon thy People by thy Almighty Power, and ſcatter the dark Clouds of Temptation, and cauſe the light of Life to ſhine upon them; thou that haſt commanded the Light to ſhine out of
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:65307:83"/> darkneſs, do thou ſhine into the Hearts of the Sons and Daughters of Men. Open their Hearts that they may receive thy Truth, and make tender their hard Hearts, that they may live to thee that Created them; and give a comfortable Account to thee of their Thoughts, Words and Actions, and let them turn to thee before it be too late to repent them. Powerful God of Life, thy mercies and loving kindneſs do abound to a little Remnant that do believe in Chriſt and do truſt in thy great Name: Thou haſt been with them in their fiery tryalls and tribulations, and to this Day thou haſt been the glory of our Aſſemblies, and the joy of our meetings: We are ſenſible of thy holy Power working in our Souls, and of thy renewing thy love upon us: All that want a full ſenſe thereof, that are ſeeking and crying after thee for it; O let them be br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ught to a due ſenſe of God: O ariſe for the help and the Comfort of the Sorrowful, the Sighing and the needy Soul; pour forth the treaſures of thy love upon them that follow hard after thee, and breath for deliverance, that ſo Powerful God of life, praiſes may ariſe to thee, for all thy mercies and abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bleſſings, for thy goodneſs and loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs beſtowed upon us, from time to time. Moſt Powerful God of life and light, let the Eye of thy Favour be turned upon this Land of our
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:65307:84"/> Nativity; ſpare the inhabitants of this City and Nation, that they may ſeek after thee, let them know the weight of thy Hand upon them, to bow them down to humility and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs of Heart. Give them Repentancee for their Sins; Living God of life diſplay thy Power to all from the higheſt to the loweſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, and advance the kingdom of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, to whom thou haſt given a Name above every Name, and let his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and glory be exalted over all, and ſhine forth in the midſt of us; Bleſſed Father of Life, give wiſdom to our Counſellers, that they may Counſel for thee. Make known thy will and ſend help from Heaven to all that ſtand in need thereof, and that wait upon thee for it: Give them thy Holy Spirit that they may be guided in thy way; let thy Son Jeſus Chriſt have the ſtearing and Governing of all things, and let Glory be rendered to thy great aad worthy Name, and keep us in the Love of God and in Union one with another; let the ſtroak of thy Power remain upon the Hearts of all, whoſe Hearts thou haſt touched at this time; let them be bowed down always in thy Holy Worſhip, and remain in a belief of thy truth, and ceaſe to do evil and learn to do well, and walk ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptably before thee, that ſo Tranſgreſſion may be finiſhed, and Sin and Iniquity may be put to
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:65307:84"/> an end; and that Truth and Righteouſneſs may be ſet up, and ſhine among us, and that our Souls may rejoyce in thee, that we may mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie and praiſe thy Power, and Glorifie thy Name; for thou art worthy of all Honour, praiſe and glory, and humble thankſgivings for the manifeſtation of thy love and Power: All which we deſire to offer thee through Jeſus Chriſt, who art God over all bleſſed for ever and ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="sermon">
            <head>Sermon VII. The Inward Preacher Or, The Office of Conſcience. <hi>Preached at</hi> Grace-Church-Street. June, 21. 1692.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>MAny have been ſent among you, that from Living experience have declared
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:65307:85"/> their Teſtimony for the truth, that you might all be brought to wait for the teſtimony of Truth in your ſelves. This is that which will ſtand you in ſtead to know the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of truth in your own Hearts to be for you. Therefore you are to wait, eſpecially at ſuch times as theſe, to hear the Voice of Truth in your own Souls. For whatſoever the Preacher preacheth, if the Truth in thine own Heart doth not ſpeak Peace, it is not well with thee. Whatſoever teſtimonies are born of the Truth it ſelf; it is the Truth that muſt bear teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of thee: That unerring Word that gives to every one an Infallible evidence of their Peace with God, or againſt that which hinders them.</p>
            <p>You know our labour hath been to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade all People to hearken unto the Truth in themſelves, and to make it their buſineſs and travel and endeavour that they might have unity with the Truth in their own Hearts, that their Conſciences may not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn them.</p>
            <p>For ſuch as you in whom God hath raiſed his witneſs, and hath exalted his Truth for a Judge: You are not Ignorant, nor covered over with darkneſs as many others are; you do not remain in doubt, but you know the Truth, and have an Anſwer of Peace in well
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:65307:85"/> doing, and a condemnation in evil doing; not Adminiſtred to you only by Preachers without, but by the evidence and demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Spirit of God in your own Hearts. This is that ſtanding Miniſtry which God hath raiſed, which can never be put down again, but as each one may put it down in themſelves.</p>
            <p>I grant that Men may put it down: You have read, and had it plainly witneſſed to you, even <hi>killing the juſt and Crucifying the Lord of Glory, and of ſpiritual</hi> Sodom <hi>and</hi> Egypt: Theſe things you have read of, and you that are turned to the Light, know the meaning of thoſe ſayings by woful experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; for when ever you have turned aſide from a due ſubjection to rhe Grace of God, by which we are convinced, then there hath been a piercing, <hi>and Crucifying the Son of God a freſh, and a vexing and a grieving the Holy Spirit by which you ſhould be Sealed to the Day of Redemption;</hi> then there hath been Anguiſh and Tribulation upon your Souls. And if this be minded, it will plant a fear upon the Heart, and make you affraid to do the like again, but where this Tribulation, and Anguiſh is neglected and put off; there a cuſtome of Sin takes away the ſenſe of Sin: As you know many have had more Judgment
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:65307:86"/> at ſometime upon them for a vain word, or a vain Thought, than afterward they have come to have for the moſt abominable wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Action; How come this to paſs? Was Sin ever the better? Or hath it changed its Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture? No, but they are further off from the ſenſe of the evil of it, this is the word of Truth, to which you muſt ſtand or fall, this is the Stone that whoſoever falls upon it ſhall be broken and tendered: But if they ſtay till the weight of Truth fall upon them, it will grind them to Powder.</p>
            <p>They that will have a life of liberty; let the Truth ſay what it will, I will have my liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and uſe my Tongue as I liſt; I will be wanton and proud, and envious and malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, though I know theſe things to be nought, and the witneſs in my Conſcience teſtifies that theſe things are wicked, and contrary to the will of God, yet I will have them; whoſoever comes to this Mind, the Stone is near falling upon them and they will be ground to Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, they are like the barren Earth which beareth Thorns and Briars, and is rejected, <hi>and is nigh unto Curſing, whoſe end is to be burned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore Friends I entreat you to hearken to the Word of the Lord, it is a holy Word, an old Word, many have
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:65307:86"/> profeſſed it: There are ſome Preachers that will cry, Hearken to the Word of the Lord in ſuch a Chapter, and ſuch a Verſe; My Teſtimony this Day is Hearken to the Word of the Lord; but where ſhall we find it, ſome will ſay? I tell you, it is written with the Finger of God in your own Conſciences, and is either for you or againſt you: Let your Profeſſion amongſt Men be what it will, this Miniſter of the Covenant hath no reſpect of Perſons, or regard to Profeſſion, he will not excuſe this or that Man, becauſe he makes a greater Profeſſion of his Name than others; this rather is his Judgment, and his Condemnation ſhall be more ſwift and ſharp upon him that makes a Profeſſion of Chriſts Name: <hi>If Judgment begin at the Houſe of God, what ſhall the end of them be that obey not the Goſpel of God?</hi> Theſe that take upon them a ſtrict Profeſſion, they do greater diſhonour to God, than thoſe that cry out there is no Reformation, there can be no Living without Sin; theſe Profeſs what they do, and they do as they Profeſs: But when People come to Profeſs Holineſs and Righteouſneſs and Profeſs a Power alſo by which Righteouſneſs is obtained; but live not ſtrictly according to their Profeſſion; theſe are they, <hi>That cauſe the Name of God to be
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:65307:87"/> Blaſphemed among the Heathen;</hi> more than they that ſay there can be no living with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Sin,</p>
            <p>Now this Witneſs of God hath no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to Profeſſion, but hath reſpect to the Sate and Frame of the Mind of a Man or Woman that they ſerve God with, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be with ſincerity and uprightneſs of mind, and with breathing deſires, that <hi>They may know the good and acceptable Will of God, and what is well-pleaſing in his ſight.</hi> And that they might perform that which is, according to his Heavenly will. Where this ſincerity is, where this cry of the Soul is the Lord hath regard to it; but where Peoples Religion is only to bear up a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and hold up an external Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Communion one with another; when this ſincerity is wanting the Lord ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hors their Worſhip, it is an abomination to God, and no benefit or advantage to themſelves: It is not for the glory of God that they make a Profeſſion, but for ſome deſign to themſelves: and ſo they become abominable,</p>
            <p>This was the ſtate of <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, and it is the ſtate of a great many now, that think they do great matters if they conform ſo far to the Truth, as that outwardly they may
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:65307:87"/> not be charged with a Lie, but that they are of ſuch a Society: it is well if ſome would come ſo far as to maintain their Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety with Gods People and their external Profeſſion; but if they have not regard to Truth in their own Conſciences, what is their Profeſſion worth? What will all thy Unity with them ſignifie? If there be a breach between God and thine own Soul, who can heal that breach? What will their Profeſſion ſignifie and amount to at laſt? But, <hi>Go you curſed into Everlaſting Fire prepared for the Devil and his Angels.</hi> And all the reaſon to be rendred for it is this; Depart from me, <hi>Ye are workers of Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> He did not ſay in that ſentence, ye are Lyars, you never Prophecyed in my Name, and I never preached in your Streets; but allowing what they ſaid to be Truth, that they had made a Profeſſion, and held Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with other Chriſtians; allowing theſe things, yet notwithſtanding it is, <hi>Go ye curſed;</hi> and the reaſon of that Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence is, <hi>You are workers of Iniquity,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let the dread of the God of Heaven reſt upon you. My Friends, it is another thing to make a Profeſſion of the Lord God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth, than moſt are aware; <hi>Let every one that Names the Name of Chriſt
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:65307:88"/> depart from Iniquity,</hi> What is Iniquity? It is all things that a Man or Woman doth to gratifie their own wills contrary to the will of God, that is Iniquity: Where had all Men Liberty? Where had <hi>Adam</hi> and his Sons their Liberty to fulfil their own wills and to contradict the will of God? Yet nothing is more common in Nations, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries and Families, than for People to aſſume a Liberty to perform and fulfil their own will, and to bring about their own Intereſt, Deſigns and Contrivances; though at the ſame time they are convinced that it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the will of God. Where this Liberty is taken, there Iniquity is wrought; that is Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity which is unjuſt, that which is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt him upon whom we have all our dependance every moment for Life and Breath, for Food and Raiment, and every thing we enjoy; we have a dependance upon that God that made us; yet vain Men and Women aſſume a Liberty of gratifying their own Wills, and ſetting up for the Fleſh.</p>
            <p>You may remember that paſſage of the good Apoſtle when he ſaw ſome Libertine Profeſſors of Chriſtianity grow looſe and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs; it is well they thought that they did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge God in their Meetings, and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; but as to the Affairs of the World,
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:65307:88"/> they had forgotten that God was concerned in thoſe things; the Apoſtle takes notice of ſuch a Libertine looſeneſs, <hi>Go to now, you that ſay, to Day or to Morrow we will go into ſuch a City, and continue there a year, and buy and ſell and get gain: Whereas you know not what ſhall be on the Morrow; For what is your Life? It is even a Vapour, that appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for a little while, and then vaniſheth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way: For that you ought to ſay; if the Lord will, we ſhall live and do this or that.</hi> You ought to live in ſubjection to him that made you, you ought to have regard to Gods honour in whatſoever you do, <hi>Whether you Eat or Drink, or whatſoever you do; do all to the glory of God.</hi> Is not this Scripture? Is not this found amongſt the Apoſtles Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings? Do not we hold the Name of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans which was given to them at <hi>Antioch?</hi> Yea we are called Chriſtians, and theſe writings of the Apoſtle are holy writings, and what then is the matter that we take ſo little notice of them? That men do not apply theſe whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Exhortations to the particularities of of their Converſation; but that they go from Countrey to Countrey, and from one place to another, and do what they pleaſe, without having any regard to give their ſubjection to to the Great God: This
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:65307:89"/> Looſneſs hath brought into the minds of ſome ſuch a Liberty that they live without God in the World; when they go ſometimes to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Meetings, and when they hear the Name of God mentioned, it may be there come a little awe upon their minds; and they have ſome regard to that God that gave them Breath and being, for the preſent: But if there be not Religion; if there be not a Tie; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion ſignifies a Tie, a being bound to God; if men be not bound and tied to God, by that which is made known to them, every one will deſire that <hi>which is good in their own Eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore it is neceſſary for you my Friends, above all People, you that are come to your meaſure of the Miniſtration of the Spirit, and know it, what it doth ſpeak; Such a thing I did this Morning, and I am reprov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for it: Such a thing I did well, and I am Juſtified and warranted in the doing of it: Thus it is when a thing is well or ill done; Sometimes ſome Men Act two or three Days together and never bring their Actions to the rule, that is like a Man that is building and never minds his rule, ſo what he builds up Tumbles down again upon his Head. You know there is ſomething in you, that hath a ſpeaking Voice, an Infallible Voice, and gives Judgment on your Actions, and paſſeth a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:65307:89"/> either of Juſtification or Condemnation upon you. If you would live ſo as to anſwer God in what you do, you need not fear an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering Men: I do not fear anſwering Men in all I do or ſpeak, if I do but anſwer mine own Conſcience, I fear no Man, though they be of another perſwaſion, in their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment oppoſite to me; if I keep peace in mine own Conſcience, I ſhall anſwer the principle, of Truth in my adverſaries Conſciences, though they hate me, and deſpiſe me, and ſeek occaſion againſt me, if my Actions an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the Truth of God in my own Heart, they will anſwer the Truth in any Mans Heart: This makes a Man as bold as a Lion.</p>
            <p>When the People of God obtain a Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to be true and juſt, and holy and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous; all Men will expect Holineſs and Righteouſneſs at their hands: What if I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs to be one of thoſe People? If I have not the Truth in my own Heart. This reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on though I put it on as a Cloak to hide my Inſincerity, the want of that Truth takes away my Courage. It is Truth in all Men in the World that hath a Power, and it is the Power of Holineſs and Righteouſneſs that makes wicked Men affraid, and therefore the Apoſtle argues upon that ſubject, the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate is clothed with Power, what Power hath
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:65307:90"/> he? The Power of Juſtice, and the Power of the Sword; What Sword hath he? A Sword of Juſtice, and he is <hi>a Terrour to evil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doers, but a praiſe to them that do well.</hi> It is true, if I have done evil; if I meet with a Man that is but my Equal; if in buying and ſell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Commerce, I have wronged him and deceived him, though he knows not of it: Yet I am affraid of him, I am fearful that he will diſcover me and find me out: But if I ſpeak the Truth, and do that which is honeſt in the ſight of all Men, I ſhall not fear any Man; there is no Nation under Heaven but there is a principle of Truth to be found amongſt them, in the Hearts of Men: If I Act according to the principle of Truth in mine own Heart, there is the ſame principle of Truth in all Men. If I walk up to the principle of Truth in my ſelf, I ſhall likewiſe walk up to the principle of Truth in all Mens Hearts; if mine own Heart doth not condemn me, all the World cannot condemn me.</p>
            <p>If profeſſors were reſolved to anſwer the principles of Truth in their own Hearts, and go through ſtitch in the profeſſion, they might live Couragiouſly: Truth will Crown them with Victory. But if they do not live accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the rule and ſtandard of Truth, they are like Salt that have <hi>loſt its ſavour which is trod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:65307:90"/> under feet of Men.</hi> But where all are one in Truth, they are gathered into the Truth, and they will live according to it, ſo far as they are convinced of it: If you will give them a World they will not give away an Hairs breadth of the Truth which they have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed; when Truth thus comes to have Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, then Truth ſhall overſpread the Earth, and the <hi>kingdoms of the World ſhall become the kingdoms of the Lord and of his Chriſt,</hi> and righteouſneſs ſhall rule, and the Scepter of it be ſwaied over the Nations, and they that Rebel againſt it ſhall be broken by it, and they that are found in it ſhall have Dominion, and they ſhall condemn Hypocrites and Diſſemblers: Now if you would grow up into this Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, you have an opportunity for it, becauſe the Truth is Revealed in your own Hearts.</p>
            <p>They who go about to walk in the Truth meerly from what they hear the Miniſters of Truth Preach, laying up in their minds a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Doctrines, Notions and Tenets, they will ſtumble and fall, but they that will heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to the Truth in their own Hearts and regard the Voice of it in all their ways and undertak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; theſe have a Miniſter at Home with them, they have a Chaplain in their own Houſe; if there be any thing they know not, and if they know not what to do they ask this Miniſter
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:65307:91"/> of the Sanctuary; others they will ask their Miniſters, but your Miniſter is at Home with you: Where hath God appointed any Man to rule over your Conſciences; no, God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Chriſt only to guide and govern your Conſciences, to be the Author of Faith and the Finiſher of it too: You that are come to to the Diſpenſation of the Spirit of Chriſt keep to the teſtimony in your own Hearts; then we have fellowſhip with one another in the Truth, and we have cauſe to bleſs God for it; that God hath ſo opened the Heart of one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards another, that the ſuffering of one is the ſuffering of all, and the Conſolation of one the comfort and rejoycing of all: But, Alas! Who is in this fellowſhip? Only thoſe that are in fellowſhip with the Truth, in their own Heart, are really ſo: If a Man ſhall break fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with Truth in his own Heart, he will make no bones of breaking fellowſhip with his Brethren: As ſoon as Men break fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with Truth, they are unruly, Heady, troubleſom and make no matter of ſplitting and tearing and rending of fellowſhip with others. How comes it to paſs that thou haſt done this? thou didſt not thus whilſt thou feared Sinning againſt the witneſs of God in thine own Heart. But when Men have once made Light of the great Miniſter of the Goſpel in their own
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:65307:91"/> Hearts, it is an eaſie matter to make light of all the reſt; if, as Chriſt ſaith, <hi>They have done ſo to the Green Tree, no wonder that they do ſo to the Dry Tree; If they deſpiſe me</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>do you think they will love you?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is moſt evident in a great many at thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Day, they Diſpute againſt Truth; they have taken a Liberty to ſpeak contrary to the Truth in their own Hearts, then they cry down the Miniſters of it: Do you think any body doth ſo that keep their firſt tenderneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>? When they were firſt convinced the Power of the Lord reſted upon them; when the Power of God firſt wrought upon you and brought you to Yea, and Nay, and to plain ſimple Language and Habit, this was with j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y and delight for Chriſts ſake. They that keep up this tenderneſs and ſimplicity of Mind; there is no ſcattering, nor rending, or tearing among them, they keep the Unity of the Spirit in the bond of Peace, and they are kept together in one.</p>
            <p>Friends, you have an opportunity in your hands, ſee that you make uſe of it; you may bear up and not be deceived by Men or Devils, If you keep faithful to the Principle of Truth in your own Hearts. Let what Reproach and Perſecution ſoever come, here is a Standard, a Foundation and
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:65307:92"/> a Rule for you to be Governed by: Every hour of the Day, ſearch your Hearts and try your Conſciences by it. As you do this and keep to the Rule of the new Creature, of the Regeneration, being changed from a Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Birth to an Incorruptible Birth: <hi>If you he born of the Incoruptible ſeed;</hi> the Devil cannot corrupt you; Evil paſſions cannot corrupt you; if you keep upon that Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation that is Incorruptible in it ſelf, then nothing will corrupt you, nor your ways and manners: If you will then live accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſimplicity of the Goſpel, you will ſerve God and be examples to others in the Life of Holineſs and Righteouſneſs, and hereby God ſhall be glorified. This is that which will ſhine forth to the whole Nation, and give a good Report to Truth: But if any that Profeſs the truth be found falſe to their Profeſſion and be found unholy, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and over-reach his Neighbour, the party loſeth by it, and the Devil reioyceth at it.</p>
            <p>Thus we know the Life of Righteouſneſs is brought forth through the Spirit of Truth, and outſhines all, and will reach Gods wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in them that are afar off, and bring them near; and happy and bleſſed are they that are found in this Divine work, conforming their Lives and Converſations according
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:65307:92"/> to the new Creature: Peace be upon them, <hi>And upon the whole</hi> Iſrael <hi>of God:</hi> There is a Miniſter that abides with you, that goes home with you, it is his Teſtimony that you muſt ſtand or fall by: If any one ſhould be a falſe Profeſſor and be cryed up, if he be not ſincere he hath not Peace, though he flutter a while and makes a ſhew, the Worm of guilt Gnaws him and Torments him; ſuch as theſe have not Peace with God, nor fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with the Church: Though they ſeem to be a live yet they are Dead, as it was with the Churches in <hi>Aſia, they had a name to live, yet they were Dead;</hi> though they have an empty Name, ſuch a one is a living Man or Woman, are eſteemed Friends to the Church; but though they are commended and cryed up, and have a Name to live, yet they are Dead, <hi>there are a few names in</hi> Sardis <hi>which have not defiled their Garments, they walk with me in White,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>for they are worthy: I know thy works that thou haſt a name, that thou liveſt and art Dead:</hi> See what Chriſt the Bright Morning Star could do; he could look into a Meeting and ſee whether few or many had only a name to Live, or were really alive, if they were Dead as to Sinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Truth, though they had been among the Church they would help to break it down, but not to build it up.</p>
            <pb n="174" facs="tcp:65307:93"/>
            <p>You that have his Divine life ſtill ſtirring in you, and feel the operation that firſt quickened you to God; prize this principle of the Divine life above all: What is there can rob you of it? Value not the Friendſhip of the World: Alas! What can it Amount to? Count it as Dung in compariſon of Chriſt Jeſus, look upon all things with a ſound Eye: Peace with God is of that concerment that you cannot be happy here or hereafter without it; the Friendſhip of the World I can be without, and the cuſtomes and faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the World I can be without, I can ſpare theſe things; but the Favour of God I cannot be without, <hi>and growth in Grace and the knowledg of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and a ſincere Profeſſion of the Goſpel, I cannot be without theſe things.</p>
            <p>My Friends, though you do not make a ſhew and Flutter in the World as ſome others do, yet your glory is within they that are living Members of this Divine body, the glory and beauty, and brightneſs of ſuch, appears in the ſight of God. If you grow in grace you will be a Comfort one to another, and as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>You are our Epiſtle written in our Hearts kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wn and read of all Men.</hi> The Lord preſerve and keep you ſimple, keep you in all Sincerity, in that Truth that hath wrought in your own hearts, that you may have acquaintance with your teacher, that he may not be driven into corners, for you may do it and ſtop his mouth and ſilence him too. If you let your Perverſe will Rule, you may ſlay the Juſt, but there will come a Day of his Riſing, then down go you: Whatſoever Men may get by it at preſent, when Truth riſeth, when the juſt one that was ſlain hath a Reſurrection in them, then moſt certain down they go; While you have an opportunity in your Hands and an Intereſt in the Covenant of Life, walk with God according to the Counſel and Dictates of his Holy Spirit, that you may be brought to an heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:65307:93"/> Fellowſhip, and to partake of the Good things that God hath prepared for his Children.</p>
            <p>My Friends, Pray, prize your ſeaſons, let no Day ſlip for fear you may miſs a Day at laſt; wait upon the Lord and let his fear and a Holy awe be always upon your Hearts: Then peace will be upon you and there will be acceptance of all that you do, <hi>Mark the Perfect Man and behold the upright, for the End of that Man is peace;</hi> when he can reflect upon his paſt Life and ſay, I have walked before the Lord with a perfect Heart and done that which is good and well pleaſing in his ſight, and have not turned aſide to the right Hand or to the left, but the ſtandard of Truth hath been the guide of all my Spiritual and Temporal Actions. If truth hath been thy guid here, then Truth ſhall be thy Portion hereafter: If Truth guide thee in thy way, then thou ſhall rejoyce with the Saints, and receive an Inheritance with the People of God, and enjoy that glory and felicity which God hath prepared for them that Love him.</p>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>His Prayer after Sermon.</head>
               <p>EVerlaſting, Glorious, Eternal God of Life, whoſe kingdom ruleth over all; thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is an everlaſting kingdom, a Glorious and Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Day hath dawned, wherein thou art making thy ſelf known to the Sons and Daughter of Men, and thou haſt opened an Eye in a Remnant, which the God of this World had blinded, to ſee the Glory of it: For though we have lived without God in the World, yet thou art near to us, and thou haſt called us to Repentance, and inſpired our Souls with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to thee, and to the Remembrance of thy name. Praiſes and Everlaſtings Thankſgivings belong unto thee, who art the Author of our Salvation, who haſt reached out thy Hand and laid hold upon us, and ſought us out when we ſought thee not, and haſt made known thy Power and love for our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption
<pb facs="tcp:65307:94"/> and Salvation; and thou wilt make it known more and more to every upright and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere mind: O Powerful Father of Life, how hath thy Power and Goodneſs been Revealed on our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half for thine own Name ſake? Thou haſt ſtood by us in all our Tryals and Exerciſes, and we have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ound thee a God nigh at Hand, and thou haſt brought a Remnant to deſire nothing ſo much as the Injoyment of thy Preſence; thou haſt brought them to be ſenſible, that without thee they can do nothing; therefore in all our Aſſemblies and Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings we deſire to be Acquainted with thy Power, to hear thy Word which ſpeaks Life to our Souls by which we may live: And Dear and Powerful Father, the Continuation of thy goodneſs among us doth greatly engage the Hearts of thy Children to offer up Praiſes and Thankſgivings to thee; Thou haſt inclined the Minds and Hearts of thy People to wait upon Thee, and haſt opened their underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to receive thy Heavenly Truth, and thoſe rich and Heavenly treaſures which thou offereſt them; and haſt provided a Cup of Salvation to refreſh the Poor and needy Soul. O Living God of Life, reach forth thy Hand, to ſupport and ſave thoſe that are Breathing after thee, that are ſenſible of their want of thy preſence, and are frequenting the Aſſemblies of thy People, with ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and deſire that they may enjoy a Bleſſing from thee. Living God of Life, Touch their Hearts with the Finger of thy Power, and let them know that thou art ready to open the Treaſures of thy Love, and Life unto them, through the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that their Souls may be Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, and they may offer up to thee Sacrifices of Thankſgiving. And let all thy Children every where render to thy Holy Name, through Jeſus Chriſt, Bleſſing and Honour and Praiſe; who art God over all, Bleſſed for ever and ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:65307:94"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of Books Printed for <hi>Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Crouch,</hi> at the <hi>Bell</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey,</hi> near <hi>Cheapſide.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Hiſtory.</head>
               <p n="1">1. ENglands Monarchs: Or A Compendious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the moſt remarkable Tranſactions, from <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> to this preſent; adorned with Poems, and the Pictures of every Monarch, from King <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror to K. <hi>William</hi> and Q. <hi>Mary.</hi> With a Liſt of the Nobility, the Knights of the Garter, the number of the Lords and Commons who have Votes in both Houſes of Parliament; and many other uſeful par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars. Price one ſhilling.</p>
               <p n="2">2. THE Hiſtory of the Houſe of Orange: Or, a Brief Relation of the Glorious and Magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Atchievements of His Majeſties Renowned Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors, and likewiſe of His own Heroick Actions, till the Late Wonderful Revolution. Together with the Hiſtory of <hi>William</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> King and Queen of <hi>England, Scotland, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> &amp;c. Being an Impartial Account of the moſt Remarkable Paſſages and Tranſactions in theſe Kingdoms from their Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Happy Acceſſion to the Throne to this time. By R. B. Price One Shilling.</p>
               <p n="3">3. THE Hiſtory of the two late Kings, Charles the II. and James the II. being an Impartial ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the moſt remarkable Tranſactions, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable paſſages, during their Reigns; and the ſecret French and Popiſh Intrigues and Deſigns managed in thoſe Times. Together with a Relation of the happy Revolution, and the Acceſſion of Their preſent Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties, K. <hi>William</hi> and Q. <hi>Mary</hi> to the Throne, <hi>Feb.</hi> 13. 689. Pr. 1<hi>s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb facs="tcp:65307:95"/>4 THE Hiſtory of Oliver Cromwel, being an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Account of all the Battels, Sieges, and other Military Atchievements, wherein he was inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in England, Scotland and Ireland; and likewiſe of his Civil Adminiſtrations, while he had the Supream Government, till his Death. Relating only matters of Fact, without Reflection or Obſervation. By R. B. pr. 1<hi>s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. THE Wars in England, Scotland and Ireland, containing a particular and Impartial Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of all the Battels, Sieges, and other remarkable Tranſactions, Revolutions and Accidents, which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened from the beginning of the Reign of K. Charles the Firſt, 1625. to His Majeſties happy Reſtauration: The Illegal Tryal of K. Charles I. at large, with his laſt Speech at his Suffering; and the moſt conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able matters till 1660. with Pictures of ſeveral Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents. Price one Shilling.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>HIſtorical Remarks and Obſervations of the Antient and Preſent State of</hi> London <hi>and</hi> Weſtminſter, ſhewing the Foundations, Walls, Gates, Towers, Bridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, Churches, Rivers, Wards, Halls, Companies, Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Courts, Hoſpitals, Schools, Inns of Courts, Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Franchiſes, and Priviledges thereof; with the moſt remarkable Accidents, as to Wars, Fires, Plagues, and other occurrences, for above 902 years paſt, Pr. 1<hi>s.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. ADmirable Curioſities, Rarities and Wonders in England, Scotland, and Ireland; or an account of many remarkable perſons and places; and likewiſe of the Battles, Sieges, prodigious Earthquakes, Tempeſts, Inundations, Thunders, Lightnings, Fires, Murders and other Occurences and Accidents for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hundred years paſt: Together with the Natural and Artificial Rarities in every County in <hi>England.</hi> With ſeveral curious Sculptures. Price one ſhilling.</p>
               <p n="8">8. THE Hiſtory of the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> being an Account of the Ancient Inhabitants, and
<pb facs="tcp:65307:95"/> of all the Battles, Sieges, and other conſiderable Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions both Civil and Military in that Countrey, from the firſt Conqueſt thereof, under King <hi>Henry</hi> II. till its entire Reduction, by His Majeſties Arms. Toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the moſt remarkable Paſſages, that have ſince happened there to this time. By R. B. Pr. 1s.</p>
               <p n="9">9. THE Engliſh Empire in America, or a proſpect of His Majeſties Dominions in the Weſt-In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, namely, New-found-land, New-England, New-York, New-Jerſey, Penſylvania, Mary-land, Virginia, Carolina, Bermudas, Barbuda, Anguila, Monſerrat, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minica, St. Vincent, Antego, Mevis or Nevis, St. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtophers, Barbadoes and Jamaica: With an account of their Diſcovery, Scituation and Product: The Religion and Manners of the Indians, and other excellencies of theſe Countries: To which is prefixed a relation of the diſcovery of this New World, and of the remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Voyages and Adventures of <hi>Sebaſtin Cabot,</hi> Sir <hi>Martin Frobiſher,</hi> Capt. <hi>Davis,</hi> Capt. <hi>Weymouth</hi> Capt. <hi>Hall,</hi> Capt. <hi>Hudſon,</hi> Sir <hi>Tho. Cavendiſh,</hi> the E. of <hi>Cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berland,</hi> Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh</hi> and other Engliſh Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies, to divers places therein. Illuſtrated with Maps, and Pictures of the ſtrange Fruits, Birds, Beaſts, Fiſhes, Inſects, Serpents and Monſters found in thoſe parts of the World. Price one ſhilling.</p>
               <p n="10">10. A View of the Engliſh Acquiſitions in Guinea and the Eaſt-Indies: With an Account of the Religion, Government, Wars, ſtrange Cuſtoms, Beaſts, Serpents, Monſters, and other Obſervables in thoſe Countries. And among others, the Life and Death of Mahomet the Grand Impoſtor, with the Principal Doctrines of the Turkiſh Religion as they are diſplayed in the Alcoran. Two Letters, one written by the Great Mogul, and the other by the King of Sumatra in the Eaſt-Indies, to our K. <hi>James</hi> I. of an extravagant ſtile. The cruel Executions in thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:65307:96"/> parts, with the manner of the Womens burning them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with their dead Huſbands. Together with a deſcription of the Iſle of St. Helena, and the Bay of Souldania; intermixt with pleaſant Relations. Pr. 1s.</p>
               <p n="11">11. THE <hi>Engliſh</hi> Heroe: Or, Sir <hi>Francis Drake</hi> Revived. Being a full Account of the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Voyages, admirable Adventures, notable Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries, and Magnanimous Atchievements of that Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant and Renowned Commander. As, I. His Voyage in 1572. to <hi>Nombre de Dios</hi> in the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> where they ſaw a Pile of Bars of Silver near 70 foot long, 10. foot broad, and 12. foot high II. His incompaſſing the whole World in 1577. which he performed in two years and ten months, gaining a vaſt quantity of Gold and Silver. III. His Voyage into <hi>America</hi> in 1585. and taking the Towns of St. <hi>Jago,</hi> St. <hi>Domingo, Carthagena,</hi> and St. <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> IV. His laſt Voyage into thoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries in 1595. with the manner of his Death and Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial. Reviſed. Corrected, and very much enlarged, reduced into Chapters with Contents, and beautified with Pictures. By <hi>R. B.</hi> Price One Shilling.</p>
               <p n="12">12. TWo Journeys to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> Containing firſt, An account of the Travels of two Engliſh Pilgrims ſome years ſince, and what Admirable Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents befel them in their Journey to <hi>Jeruſalem, Grand Cario, Alexandria,</hi> &amp;c. 2. The Travels of 14 Engliſh Merchant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in 1669. from <hi>Scanderoon</hi> to <hi>Tripoly, Joppa, Kamah, Jeruſalem, Bethlehem, Jericho,</hi> the River of <hi>Jor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan,</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> and back-a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>po.</hi> To which is added, a Relation of the gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> aſſembled in the plains of <hi>Ajayda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n <hi>Hungary,</hi> 1650. to examine the Scriptures concerning Chriſt. By <hi>S. B.</hi> an Engliſh-man there preſent: With the notorious deluſion of the <hi>Jews,</hi> by a counterf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Meſſiah, or falſe Chriſt at <hi>Smyrna,</hi> in 1666, and the event thereof. Laſtly, The Extirpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:65307:96"/> of the <hi>Jews</hi> throughout <hi>Perſia</hi> in 1666. Epiſtle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Agbarus</hi> to our Saiviour, with our Saviours Anſwer: Beautified with Pictures. Pr. one ſhilling.</p>
               <p n="13">13. EXtraordinary Adventures of ſeveral Famous Men: with the ſtrange Events, and ſignal mutations and changes in the Fortunes of divers Illuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trious places and perſons in all Ages; being an account of a multitude of ſtupendious Revolutions, accidents, and obſervable matters in divers States and Provinces throughout the World; with Pictures. Price 1s.</p>
               <p n="14">14. THE Hiſtory of the Nine Worthies of the World: Three whereof were Gentiles; 1. Hector Son of Priamus King of Troy. 2. Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the great King of Macedon, and Conquerour of the World. 3. Julius Caeſar firſt Emperor of Rome. Three Jews. 4. Joſhua Captain General and Leader of Iſrael into Canaan. 5. David King of Iſrael. 6. Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das Maccabeus a valiant Jewiſh commander, againſt the Tyranny of Antiochus. Three Chriſtians. 7. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur King of Brittain, who couragiouſly defended his Countrey from the Saxons. 8. Charles the Great K. of France, and Emperor of Germany. 9. Godfrey of Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len King of Jeruſalem. Being an account of their glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious lives, worthy actions, renowned Victories and Deaths. Illuſtrated with Poems and the Picture of each Worthy. By R. B. Price One ſhilling.</p>
               <p n="15">15. FEmale Excellency, or the Ladies Glory, Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated in the Worthy Lives and Memorable Actions of nine Famous Women, who have been renowned either for Vertue or Valour, in ſeveral Ages of the World: As 1. Deborah the Propheteſs. 2. The valiant Judith. 3. Queen Eſther. 4. The virtuous Suſannah. 5. The Chaſt Lucretia. 6. Voadacia Q. of Brittain, in the Reign of Nero Emperor of Rome, containing an account of the Original Inhabitants of Brittain. The Hiſtory of Danus and of his fifty Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
<pb facs="tcp:65307:97"/> who murdered their Huſbands in one Night: Of the valour of Voadacia, under whoſe conduct the Brittains ſlew 70 thouſand Romans, with many other remarkable particulars. 7. Mariamne Wife of K. Herod 8. Clotilda Queen of France. 9. Andegona Princeſs of Spain. The whole adorned with poems and pictures to each Hiſtory. By R. B. Price One Shilling.</p>
               <p n="16">16. WOnderful Prodigies of Judgment and Mercy, diſcovered in above 300. memorable Hiſtories; containing, 1. Dread<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ul Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon Atheiſts, Blaſphemers, and Perjured Villains. 2. The miſerable ends of many Magicians, &amp;c. 3. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable predictions and preſages of approaching Death, and how the event has been anſwerable. 4. Fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Judgment upon bloody Tyrants, Murderers, &amp;c. 5. Admirable Deliverances from imminent dangers &amp; deplorable diſtreſſes at Sea and Land. Laſtly, Divine goodneſs to penitents, with the dying thoughts of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral famous Men, concerning a future ſtate. Pr. 1s.</p>
               <p n="17">17 UNparallell'd Varities or the Matchleſs Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Paſſions of Mankind; diſplayed in near 400 notable Inſtances and Examples, diſcovering the tranſcendent Effects; 1. Of Love, Friendſhip and Gratitude. 2. Of Magnanimity, Courage and Fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. 3. Of Chaſtity, Temperance and Humility: And on the contrary, the Tremendous conſequences; 4. Of Hatred, Revenge and Ingratitude. 5. Of Cowardice, Barbarity and Treachery. 6. Of Unchaſtity, Intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and Ambition. Imbelliſhed with Proper Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures. Price 1 s.</p>
               <p n="18">18. THE Kingdom of darkneſs: Or the Hiſtory of Demons, Specters, Witches, Appariti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Poſſeſſions, Diſturbances, and other wonderful and ſupernatural Deluſions, Miſchievous Feats and Mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Impoſtures of the Devil. Containing near 80 memorable Relations, Foreign and Domeſtick, both
<pb facs="tcp:65307:97"/> antient and modern. Collected from Authentick Re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cords, Real Atteſtations, Credible Evidences, and aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Authors of undoubted Verity. Together with a Preface obviating the common Objections and Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>adduces and Atheiſts of the Age, who deny the Being of Spirits, Witches, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> With Pictures of ſeveral memorable Accidents, Price 1 s.</p>
               <p n="19">19. SUprizing Miracles of Nature and Art, in two parts; containing, 1. The Miracles of Nature, or the wonderful Signs, and prodigious Aſpects and Apperances in the Heavens, Earth and Sea; with an account of the moſt famous Comets, and other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diges, from the Birth of Chriſt to this time. 2. The Miracles of Art, deſcribing the moſt Magnificent Buildings, and other curious Inventions in all Ages, as, the ſeven Wonders of the World, and many other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Structures and Rarities throughout the Earth. Beautifyed with Pictures Price 1 s.</p>
               <p n="20">20. MEmorable Accidents and Unnheard of Tranſactions, containing an account of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral ſtrange Events: As the Depoſing of Tyrants, Lamentable Shipwracks, Diſmal Misfortunes, Strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems of War, Perilous Adventures, Happy Deliveran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, with other remarkable Occurrences, and ſelect Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorical paſſages, which have happened in ſeveral Countries in this laſt Age. Printed at Bruſſels in 1691. and Dedicated to His preſent Majeſty, William King of England, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Publiſhed in Engliſh by R. B. Pr. 1 s.</p>
               <p n="21">21. MArtyrs in Flames, or Popery in its true Colours being a Brief Relation of the horrid Cruelties and Perſecutions of the Pope and Church of Rome, for many hundreds of years paſt, to this preſent time, in Piedmont, Bohemia, Germany, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Lithuania, France, Italy, Spain, Portugal, Scotland, Ireland, and England; with an abſtract of the cruel Perſecutions lately exerciſed upon the Proteſtants in
<pb facs="tcp:65307:98"/> France and Savoy, in the year 1686, and 1687. Toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a ſhort account of God's Judgments upon Popiſh Perſecutors. Price 1 s.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Miſcellanies.</head>
               <p n="22">22. <hi>DElights for the Ingenious,</hi> in above Fifty Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect and Choice Emblems, Divine and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, Antient and Modern, curiouſly Ingraven upon Copper Plates, with 50 delightful Poems and Lots, for the more lively Illuſtration of each Emblem, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by inſtruction and good counſel may be promoted and furthered, by an honeſt and pleaſant Recreation; to which is prefixed, A Poem, intituled, Majeſty in Miſery, or an Imploration of the King of Kings, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by K. Charles I. with his own hand, during his Captivity in Cariſbrook Caſtle in the Iſle of Wight, 1648. with a curious Emblem. Collected by R. B. Price 2 s. 6 d.</p>
               <p n="23">23. EXcellent Contemplations Divine and Moral, written by the Magnanimous A.L. Capel Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron of Hadham; together with ſome account of his Life, and his affectionate Letters to his Lady the day before his Death, with his Heroick Behaviour and laſt Speech at his Suffering. Alſo the Speeches and Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages of of D. Ham, and the Earl of Holl. who ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered with him: With his Pious Advice to his Son. Price 1. s</p>
               <p n="24">24. VVInter Evenings Entertaintment, in two parts, Containing, 1. Ten Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Relations of many Rare and Notable Accidents and Occurrences: 2. Fifty Ingenious Riddles, with their Explanations, and uſeful Obſervations and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals upon each. Enlivened with above 60 Pictures, for illuſtrating every Story and Riddle. Excellently ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated to the Fancies of Old or Young, and uſeful to chearful Society aud Converſation. Price 1 s.</p>
               <p n="25">
                  <pb facs="tcp:65307:98"/>25. DElightful Fables in Proſe and Verſe, none of them to be found in Aeſop, but collect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from divers Ancient and Modern Authors, with Pictures and proper Morals to every Fable. Several of them very applicable to the Preſent times. by R. B. Price bound one ſhilling.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Divinity.</head>
               <p n="26">26. THE Divine Banquet, or Sacramental De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions, conſiſting of Morning and Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Prayers, Contemplations and Hymns for every day in the Week, in order to a more Solemn Preparation for the worthy Receiving of the Holy Communion, repreſenting the ſeveral ſteps and degrees of the Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows and Sufferings of our bleſſed Saviour, till he gave up the Ghoſt: As, 1. His Agony in the Garden. 2. His being betrayed by Judas. 3. His being falſly accuſed, ſmitten, buffetted, and ſpit upon before Caiphas the High Prieſt. 4. His condemnation, ſcourging, crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Thorns, and being delivered to be crucified by Pontius Pilate. 5. His bearing his Croſs. 6. His crucifixion. 7. Our Saviour's Inſtitution of the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sacrament. Together with brief Reſolutions to all thoſe ſcruples and objections uſually alledged for the omiſſion of this important duty. With eight cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Sculptures proper to the ſeveral parts, with Graces. Imprimatur Z. Iſham, R. P. D. Hen. Epiſc. Lond. a Sacris. Price 1 s.</p>
               <p n="27">27. A Guide to Eternal Glory: Or, brief Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to all Chriſtians how to attain Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Salvation: To which are added ſeveral other ſmall Tracts: As, 1. Saving Faith diſcovered in three heavenly conferences between our Bleſſed Saviour, and, 1. A Publican. 2. A Phariſee. 3. A doubting Chriſtian. 2. The threefold ſtate of a Chriſtian: 1. By Nature: 2. By Grace: 3. In Glory. 3. The
<pb facs="tcp:65307:99"/> Scriptures concord, compiled out of the words of Scripture, by way of queſtion and anſwer, wherein there is the ſum of the way to Salvation, and ſpiritual things compared with ſpiritual. 4. The Character of a true Chriſtian. 5. A brief Directory for the great, neceſſary, and advantagious duty of Self-examination, whereby a ſerious Chriſtian may every day examine himſelf. 6. A ſhort Dialogue between a Learned Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and a Beggar. 7. Beams of the Spirit, or Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial Meditations, enlivening, enlightning, and gladding the Soul. 8. The Seraphick Souls Triumph in the Love of God; with ſhort remembrances and pious thoughts. 9. Hiſtory improved, or Chriſtian Applications and Improvements of divers remarkable Paſſages in Hiſtory. 10. Holy Breathings in ſeveral Divine Poems, upon divers Subjects and Scriptures. Price one Shilling.</p>
               <p n="28">28. YOuths Divine Paſtime; Containing Forty Remarkable Scripture Hiſtories, turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to common <hi>Engliſh</hi> Verſe. With Forty Pictures proper to each Story; very delightful for the virtuous, imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the vacant hours of Young Perſons, and prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vain and vitious Divertiſements. Together with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Scripture Hymns upon divers occaſions. Pr. 8 d.</p>
               <p n="29">29. THE Young Mans Calling, or the whole Duty of Youth, in a ſerious and compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate Addreſs to all young perſons to remember their Creator in the days of their Youth. Together with Remarks upon the Lives of ſeveral excellent young Perſons of both Sexes, as well Ancient as Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern, who have been famous for Virtue and Piety in their Generations. With twelve curious Pictures, Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrating the ſeveral hiſtories. Price 1 s. 6 d.</p>
               <p n="30">30. THE Vanity of the Life of Man repreſented in the Seven ſeveral Stages thereof; With Pictures and Poems expoſing the Follies of every Age. Price Eight pence.</p>
               <p n="31">
                  <pb facs="tcp:65307:99"/>31. MOunt Sion, or a draught of that Church that ſhall ſtand for ever. Together with a view of that World which ſhall be broken in pieces and conſumed. By William Dyer, Author of Chriſts Famous Titles, and a Believers Golden Chain. Price One Shilling.</p>
               <p n="32">32. DIſtreſſed Sion Relieved, or, the Garment of Praiſe for the Spirit of Heavineſs. A Poem. Wherein are diſcovered the grand Cauſes of the Churches trouble and miſery under the late diſmal Diſpenſation. With a compleat Hiſtory of, and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation for thoſe Renowned Worthies that fell in England, by Popiſh rage and cruelty, from the Year 1680. Humbly Dedicated to Their Preſent Majeſties. By Benjamin Keach, Author of a Book called, Sion in Diſtreſs, or the Groans of the true Proteſtant Church. Price one ſhilling.</p>
               <p n="33">33. ANtichriſt Stormed, or the Church of Rome proved to be Myſtery Babylon the Great Whore, Rev. 17. by many and undeniable Arguments, Anſwering all the Objections of the Papiſts, and all others. Together with the Judgment of many An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient and Modern Divines, and moſt Eminent Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters concerning the riſe and final ruin of the Beaſt and Babylon, proving it will be in this preſent Age. With an Account of many ſtrange Predictions re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to theſe preſent Times. By Benjamin Keach. Price One Shilling.</p>
               <p n="34">34. THE Devout Souls Daily Exerciſe in Prayers, Contemplations and Praiſes, containing Devotions for Morning, Noon, and Night, for every day in the week; with Prayers before and after the Holy Communion: And likewiſe for Perſons of all conditions, and upon all occaſions: With Graces and Thankſgivings before and after Meat. By R. P. D. D. Price bound Six pence.</p>
               <p n="35">
                  <pb facs="tcp:65307:100"/>35. SAcramental Meditations upon divers ſelect pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Scripture, wherein Believers are aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in preparing their hearts, and exciting their affe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctions and graces when they draw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to God in that moſt awful and ſolemn Ordinance of the Lord Supper. By Jo. Flavel Miniſter of Chriſt in Devon. Price one Shilling.</p>
               <p n="36">36. JACOB Wreſtling with GOD, and prevailing: Or, a Treatiſe concerning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Neceſſity and Efficacy of Faith in Prayer: Wherein divers weighty Queſtions and Caſes or Conſcience about praying in Faith, are ſtated and reſolved: For the comforting and ſatisfying of weak and ſcrupulous Conſciences: The Conviction of formal Hypocrites, awakening of all Saints, both weak and ſtrong, great and ſmall, to this great Duty of Prayer. By Tho. Taylor, formerly at Edmunds Bury, now Paſtor to a Congregation in Cambridge. Price one Shilling.</p>
               <p n="37">37. SEveral Sermons, or Declarations of Mr. Stephen Criſp, late of Colcheſter in Eſſex; exactly taken in Characters or Short-hand, as they were delivered by him at the Publick Meeting-houſes of the People called Quakers, in Grace-Church-ſtreet, in Devonſhire Houſe, London. And now faithfully Tranſcribed and Publiſhed. Together with his Prayer at the end of every Sermon. Price bound one Shilling.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>All Printed for</hi> Nath. Crouch, <hi>at the</hi> Bell <hi>in the</hi> Poultrey <hi>near</hi> Cheapſide.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:65307:100"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
